<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Redintegratio amoris, or A union of hearts, between the Kings most excellent Majesty, the Right Honorable the Lords and Commons in Parliament, His Excellency Sir Thomas Fairfax, and the Army under his command; the Assembly, and every honest man that desires a sound and durable peace, accompanied with speedy justice and piety. By way of respective apologies, so far as Scripture and reason may be judges. / By John Cook of Grayes-Inne, Barrester.</title>
            <author>Cook, John, d. 1660.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1647</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 239 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 47 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A80408</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C6026</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E404_29</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R201862</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99862351</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99862351</idno>
            <idno type="VID">114508</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A80408)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 114508)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 64:E404[29])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Redintegratio amoris, or A union of hearts, between the Kings most excellent Majesty, the Right Honorable the Lords and Commons in Parliament, His Excellency Sir Thomas Fairfax, and the Army under his command; the Assembly, and every honest man that desires a sound and durable peace, accompanied with speedy justice and piety. By way of respective apologies, so far as Scripture and reason may be judges. / By John Cook of Grayes-Inne, Barrester.</title>
                  <author>Cook, John, d. 1660.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 86, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Giles Calvert, and are to be sold at his shop at the black spread-Eagle neer the west-end of Pauls.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1647]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Publication date from Wing.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf and the last leaf are blank.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aug: 27".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Peace --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:114508:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Redintegratio Amoris,</hi> OR A Union of Hearts, between <hi>The Kings Moſt Excellent Majesty,</hi> the Right Honorable the <hi>LORDS</hi> and <hi>COMMONS</hi> IN PARLIAMENT, His Excellency Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax,</hi> and the Army Under his Command; The Aſſembly, and every honeſt man that deſires a ſound and durable Peace, accompanied with ſpeedy Juſtice and Piety.</p>
            <p>By way of reſpective Apologies, ſo far as Scripture and Reaſon may be Judges.</p>
            <p>By JOHN COOK of Grayes-Inne, <hi>Barreſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>The falling out of lovers is the renewing of love.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Giles Calvert,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop at the black ſpread-Eagle neer the Weſt-end of <hi>Pauls.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:114508:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:114508:2"/>
            <head>The principal matters are,</head>
            <p>
               <hi>That</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>1.</hi> NAture is of Gavelkind Tenure.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>2.</hi> All lawful authority is derived from the people, who cannot by any Covenant inſlave themſelves.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>3.</hi> Good Kings raign by <hi>Gods</hi> approbation, Tyrants by his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, till the people can free themſelves.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>4.</hi> What Law is, what Rebellion is.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>5.</hi> That Anarchy is better then Tyranny.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>6.</hi> That in quiet Kingdoms much Iniuſtice is to be ſuffered ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then to oppoſe the Governors till it be inſufferable, <hi>and</hi> then it is ne reſiſtance of authority, becauſe God never did, nor man can give any ſuch authority.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>7.</hi> Some Scriptures anſwered and ſuch reverence to be given to divine authority as to beleeve that there was a reaſon for every thing, though we cannot reach it.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>8.</hi> That Biſhops for Religion and ſome former Judges, in point of Prerogative, are of equal credit.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>9.</hi> What und<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d Lord Keeper <hi>Littleton</hi> and others.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>10.</hi> Twelve politick Judges to execute quick and cheap Juſtice, requiſite to felicitate this Kingdom, with an Expedient for it.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>11.</hi> Eſſentials not to be loſt for Formalities.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>12.</hi> The Law and the Prophets to be rather ſtudied then law <hi>and</hi> profit.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>13.</hi> A Cauſe at firſt as plain as a bul-ruſh comes to be as hard as an oak.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>14.</hi> That <hi>Parliamentum</hi> is <hi>parium lamentum, and</hi> that Kings originally agreed to refer the peoples complaints to whom ſoever they would chooſe, <hi>and</hi> that Parliaments never dye intentionally.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>15.</hi> The mixture of the three eſtates commended, yet if one of three o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ligors fail, the other two muſt pay the debt, for Juſtice muſt be d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>16.</hi> That the Judgment of Parliament is inevitable for all poſitive
<pb facs="tcp:114508:3"/> Laws by vertue of the fifth Commandment.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>17</hi> Kings are not leſs free, by reaſon of Parliaments, no more then men are leſs ſafe upon Pauls for the Rails.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>18.</hi> To queſtion the Juſtice of the Parliaments Cauſe is to doubt whether Proteſtant or Popiſh be the true Religion.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>19.</hi> Yet ſo as the King had ſome colour for what he did in Gods Ordinance, which the Parliament, if they ſhould break truſt, have not, <hi>and</hi> his late party adhering to the letter of Scripture and ſome Law caſes, <hi>Touch not mine anointed, &amp;c.</hi> had the ſame colour as Papiſts for tranſubſtantion, by <hi>This is my body.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>20.</hi> Mr <hi>Jenkins</hi> eaſily anſwered <hi>and</hi> Dr <hi>Fearns</hi> matter com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſtible.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>21.</hi> Reaſons to induce his Maieſty to beleeve that the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment did nothing but in diſcharge of their great truſt, without which they could not have anſwered it to the Kingdom; <hi>and</hi> that his Maieſty would frame arguments for that purpoſe.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>22.</hi> That the Parliament would conceive that his Maieſty acted according to his preſent light, for the ſatisfaction of his Royal Conſcience, his Royal Allies <hi>and</hi> many of his people at home, <hi>&amp;</hi> would frame arguments for his Maieſty, beſides that the Law lays all the blame upon his evil Counſellors.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>23.</hi> That this is a principal expedient to beget a right under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding and endeared and loyal Affection between his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty and people.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>24.</hi> How his Maieſty is head of the Church, and one Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for his Maieſty, when the ſeveral Parliaments in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> preſent acts for eſtabliſhing of the Proteſtant and Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Religious ſeverally, what his Maieſty is to do, and that the King of <hi>Poland</hi> ſwears to maintain both thoſe Religions.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>25.</hi> That the Lords are intruſted by the people (though not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected) as <hi>Guardians</hi> of the Kings Contract with the people, <hi>and</hi> that all ſubordinate Officers are to mind the duty of their places, more then the deſires of thoſe that preferred them.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>26.</hi> Two things in the Houſe of Commons queſtioned, the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers not being ſworn <hi>and</hi> their not Adminiſtring oaths, <hi>and</hi> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>27.</hi> The Lords ſupplicated to be indulgent to tender Conſciences, being exempted from the Preſbyterian diſcipline.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>28.</hi> Three Ordinances begg'd. <hi>1.</hi> Redemption for our poor bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren,
<pb facs="tcp:114508:3"/> ſlaves to the <hi>Turks. 2.</hi> Liberty for poor Priſoners that are ready to ſtarve. <hi>3.</hi> Some ſpeedy courſe to abate the price of corn, leaſt poor people be famiſh't.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>29</hi> An Apologie for the Armies not diſbanding, who have bin true to the Covenant, <hi>and</hi> ſeek nothing but for what they firſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged, <hi>and</hi> have been the breath of many of their noſtrils, who would not have their breath in the Kingdom.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>30.</hi> The Declaration againſt them a Nullity, the Revoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it, a great honor to the Parliament and Army: What ſpirits the Armies oppoſers are of.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>31.</hi> The two great expedients for a ſubſtantial ſettlement of the Kingdom, Reformations in Courts of Juſtice, <hi>and</hi> Liberty for ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Conſciences, cannot as mens intereſts now ſtand, be effected without the Continuance of the Army.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>32.</hi> That the main intereſt of this Kingdom, is to be as zealous for the Proteſtant Religion, as <hi>Spain</hi> is for Popery.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>33.</hi> The Intereſt of all honeſt men, is ſpeedily to <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nite, ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially for Gods people.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>34.</hi> That the difference was not whether the Kingdom ſhould be Proteſtants or Papiſts, but Proteſtants at large, or ſtrickt Profeſſors.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>35.</hi> That ſhould the Army diſband til Liberties are ſecured, they would be a <hi>ludibrium</hi> to all the world, <hi>and</hi> culpable of all the ſufferings of Gods people.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>36.</hi> Some late Arguments againſt the Parliament anſwered, <hi>and</hi> the Honor of that high Court in all things to be maintained, ſo as the Honor of God do not ſuffer, nor the peoples liberties de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>37.</hi> No man to grow rich in a time of Civil War, Nor uſury then to incur; ſome <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurers within the ſtatute <hi>de judaiſmo,</hi> and a proviſion that there may not be a begger in <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>38.</hi> God wil not ſuffer any good Governors to be deſtroyed, ſo long as they Adminiſter Juſtice, but tis dangerous for the ſupream Court to deny the people their Juſt Liberties.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>39,</hi> Forreign Negotiations againſt Proteſtants, <hi>and</hi> the private Intereſts of ſome which are contrary to Publique Liberties are Grounds for the Armies continuance.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>40</hi> Religion introduced by blood every where but in England, a Propheſy concerning the ſword to that purpoſe, therefore truths which coſt dear are to be loved.</item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:114508:4"/>
                  <item>
                     <hi>41.</hi> That war is lawful to defend Religion, not to promote it; that the ſword maybe imployd for Religion as the ſervant of juſtice.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>42.</hi> Who are the hinderers of Irelands Releif, and how Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt with his left hand may fight againſt his right.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>43.</hi> That H. <hi>7.</hi> did wel to kil R. <hi>3. and</hi> long may his Royal race inherit in our preſent Soveraign Lord King Charles <hi>and</hi> his princely Progeny.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>44.</hi> The Author loves the Aſſembly, yet conceives that Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty had been long ſince ſetled but for them, who make the ſmal dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences between the Conformiſts <hi>and</hi> Reformiſts wider.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>45.</hi> The abſurdity of that Common Argument, that if Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents be permitted, then Papiſts muſt: Errors in Religion, to be tolerated, but not againſt Religion.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>46.</hi> That there are more differences between the Papiſts then are in this Kingdom; therefore we are to ſpend our wit upon them and our love upon Proteſtants: Pope Joan, in the dark, as good as my Lady.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>47.</hi> A moderate Preſbytery commended for reſtraining vice, <hi>and</hi> for external beauty, but a rigid Preſbytery dangerous to this Kingdom: men wiſer in the <hi>South</hi> then in the <hi>North,</hi> the danger of Coactive violence in matters not fundamental.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>48.</hi> Whether it be as lawful to fight for Chriſts Kingly Office as for his Prieſtly Office, <hi>and</hi> whether Chriſtians may preſume of Gods extraordinary power in caſe of Arms without an extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary warrant.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>49.</hi> What Liberty of Conſcience is deſired, and that natural men know not what belongs to ſpiritual priviledges, <hi>and</hi> what uſe may be made of the late Common-prayer-book.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>50.</hi> A requeſt to the Aſſembly to become ſuitors for juſt Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and to the Army, not to mingle their intereſts, by any means, with thoſe that ſhal oppoſe the High Court of Parliament.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:114508:4"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Redintegratio Amoris,</hi> OR A Union of Hearts, between <hi>The Kings Moſt Excellent Majesty,</hi> the Right Honourable the Lords and Commons in PARLIAMENT, His Excellency Sir Tho. Fairfax, and the ARMY under His Command, The Aſſembly, and every honeſt Man, that deſires a ſound and durable Peace, accompanied with ſpeedy Juſtice and Piety.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter a ſhower how glorious is the Sun! The War being ended what endearments ſhould there be between all true-hearted <hi>Engliſh men?</hi> When hands are tyed, the great buſineſs is to unite hearts: 'Tis the wiſdom of <hi>State,</hi> when the heart of <hi>War</hi> is broken, to deal Honorably with the <hi>Conquerors,</hi> and gently with the <hi>Conquered;</hi> 'Tis the glory of a <hi>State,</hi> as wel as a man, to paſs by an infirmity; and far more noble to forgive him whom thou mayſt kill, then to kill him whom thou mayſt forgive: The Title of this <hi>Treatiſe</hi> I hope will pleaſe every man but ſuch as
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:114508:5"/> feed only upon poyſon (which creatures ſoon after break in pieces) that are grown rich in a time of poverty, or fear a Day of Account before the Day of Judgment; ſome only can fiſh in troubled wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters; the matter of it I hope wil reliſh wel to wel-tempered pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates, that have the ſalt of reaſon; for my own particular, it hath ever been my hearty prayer, and what I have prayed for, I have ventured to write for, though I know very few that have gained any thing by the Preſs, beſides their own contentment, but hard cenſures; but he that is wiſe when men are fools, is true when they are lyars; I am not in love with my own conceptions, and yet will father them that they be not illegitimate; and the mother con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving them is a ſingle heart, as an <hi>Engliſh man;</hi> the ſubject is weighty and many tickliſh points; but ſtrong affections may be diſcerned by weak performances, and I hope men are more merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful then formerly; thoſe that love, wil excuſe, let others bring reaſon for reaſon &amp; I am ſatisfied; to give the <hi>Reader</hi> rational ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction I muſt dig deep for theſe precious <hi>truths,</hi> for taking too much upon truſt, and that to be reaſon which only looks like it, hath occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioned our late miſchiefs: And 'tis as hard to make ſome men beleeve the <hi>Truth,</hi> as it is to diſſwade others from <hi>Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherein as it is ſaid of <hi>Errors</hi> that to reduce them to their firſt original is to refute them; baſtards love any diſcourſe but to hear of their originals, ſo in all matters of Reformation by, the Interven-of the Sword the foundation, Root, higheſt wel-ſpring, foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, end, and grounds of all government is in the firſt place to be ſounded, fathomed, and diſcovered, which under favour have been the great defect in many writers in this late Com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſtion, that ſpeak of obedience to higher powers, of the un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>awfulneſs of reſiſting, and of the Rights and Liberties of the people<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from the Fountain, but following the ſtream<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of former Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorities, and practiſes of other times, which have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="5 letters">
                  <desc>•••••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nance of example, but not the leaſt force of a Law <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ſtriving to know by the Cauſes, why ſuch a Government is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed or Law is made, as by the effects that ſo they find it to be. Which Impolitiques, is the Reaſon why there are ſo many Practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to be reformed in Courts of Juſtice; the Judges finding the courſe of the Court, which they ſay makes the Law to be ſo, they never look further at the reaſon why it is ſo; for if they did but
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:114508:5"/> conſider the end and primary intention of all Laws, <hi>viz.</hi> the execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of juſtice; which conſiſts in giving every man his own, they would rather diſpence with 10000, formalities and niceties in Law, then neglect the doing of juſtice; rather ſuffer all the courſes of the Court to be broken and ſhivered into attomes, then ſuffer one poor man to be undone by a miſpleading or <hi>Error</hi> in the procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, for juſtice is of <hi>moral,</hi> and of perpetual equity, but the courſe of a Court is but Ceremonial, &amp; the Ceremonial Law of God al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways gave place to the <hi>moral:</hi> when it appears fairly to the <hi>Court,</hi> that the Debt is due, or that the Plaintiff hath title to the Land; if there be as many <hi>Errors</hi> and miſtakes in the pleadings as there are <hi>ſtars</hi> in the <hi>Firmament,</hi> the Judg muſt break through all forms to make the Plaintiff maſter of his <hi>right;</hi> and to object matters of form and confuſion, is but to tyrannize over poor men, that are not able to buy Juſtice, and to be more careful of the ſhoo then of the foot that wears it; Reſembling herein the ſtranger that admiring the height of St. <hi>Marks-Tower</hi> in <hi>Venice,</hi> thinking the Foundation could not be deep by reaſon of the water, was very ſtudious to know, whereupon ſo goodly a Fabrick ſtood: the people ſaid it was ſo, but how it came about was for the Senate to know the reaſon; they troubled not themſelves about it, but I muſt dig deep for this precious truth and go to the ground of the point, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ound in the groundſels, the building is not to be ſuſpected; and I conceive:</p>
            <p n="1">1. That by nature, all men are born alike free, as we hold all by <hi>Frankalmoign,</hi> ſo nature is <hi>Gavelkind</hi> tenure, and there is no power natural but parental, further then every man doth expreſly or implicitly impower other men over him, and every <hi>Father</hi> is a King in his own family; <hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob</hi> in <hi>Cana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi> had no Government but Domeſtical, Parental, or Proparental. And though I cannot agree with <hi>Learned Charron,</hi> that the <hi>Jews</hi> had power of life &amp; death over their Children, which he would prove by <hi>Abrahams</hi> offering up <hi>Iſaac,</hi> which he ſuppoſes <hi>Iſaac</hi> being about 25. would not have ſuffered his Father to have bound him, if by Law he had not had power to kil him; and that the ſame Law continued amongſt the <hi>Romans,</hi> which no Parents would a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe or exerciſe only to keep their Children in obedience, yet this is clear that by the Law of nature, the child is to be obedient to the Father, and when the child is ſet to School or an Apprentice;
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:114508:6"/> it is the fathers power which he puts into the Maſters hands to correct the child; which commiſſion the Maſter may not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed; and therefore that moderate correction which the Law allows to be given to Scholars and Apprentices, is to be inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the Fathers conſent, for if the Father ſhal indent with the Maſter not to correct his child; if he ſtrike him I conceive an Action of Treſpaſs wil lie againſt him, and this power con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinues till the child be able to provide for it ſelf, for by the civil Law the Father is bound to provide for his baſtard till it be 25. at which time it is preſumed able to help it ſelf, grounded upon Natures Law, that beaſts and birds feed their young ones till they can cater for themſelves and no longer, and ſo it ought to be with us where the child is natural and not legal.</p>
            <p n="2">2. This Nature, which makes all alike free, apts and fits ſome with gifts to command, others to obey; 'tis a ground in Nature that wiſe men ſhould govern the Ignorant, the <hi>Patriarchs</hi> were never impowered, but carried things ſo ſweetly that men freely obeyed them; for when people ſhal perceive that wiſe and honeſt men aim at nothing ſo much as the publick good, every man thinks himſelf happy to be under ſuch Governors, and indeed to prefer ſuch men into places of <hi>Judicature</hi> is rather a preferment to the people then to them; for as by wiſdom the world was made, and as it is enlightned by the Sun, ſo by Reaſon the <hi>Lord</hi> wil have it governed; and as in Nature he that is born blind muſt be guided by thoſe that can ſee, ſo muſt ignorant and ill-diſpoſed people be ordered and commanded by thoſe that have the gifts and Spirit of Government and ſuch as are vertuouſly diſpoſed. But all Government is to be aſcribed to neceſſity and reaſon: For the world becoming populous, vitious and licentious, a Government was neceſſary; and though the primary Laws of <hi>Nature,</hi> as obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to Parents, to hurt no body, and to do as we would be done unto, be imprinted in the heart of every man, and ſufficient to condemn the Gentiles; yet they are ſo defaced and corrupted by the fall of <hi>Adam</hi> and original ſin, that <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Nature,</hi> for the good of mankind, not only commended but comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded a <hi>Government,</hi> for man is a ſociable <hi>creature,</hi> and ſociety is natural; for in <hi>Hermites</hi> Nature is not changed but tranſgreſſed.</p>
            <p n="3">3. All juſt <hi>power</hi> and <hi>authority</hi> is either from God immediately who is <hi>Lord</hi> of all and may appoint one to be ſole <hi>Monarch</hi> over
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:114508:6"/> all the world, if it pleaſe him, as formerly he appointed <hi>Kings;</hi> or in the people who impower one or more over them. <hi>Saul</hi> and <hi>David</hi> had extraordinary Callings, but all juſt <hi>power</hi> is now de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived from the people,<note place="margin">1 Sam. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> yet in the caſe of <hi>Saul</hi> it is obſervable that the people out of <hi>pride,</hi> to be like other Nations, deſired a King, and ſuch a King as the Heathens had, which were all <hi>Tyrants;</hi> for they that know any thing in <hi>Hiſtory</hi> know that the firſt four <hi>Monarchs</hi> were all <hi>Tyrants</hi> at firſt till they gained the peoples conſent. <hi>Nim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod</hi> the great hunter was <hi>Ninus</hi> that built <hi>Ninivy</hi> the firſt <hi>Tyrant</hi> and <hi>Conqueror</hi> that had no title,<note place="margin">Gen. 10.9.</note> and ſo were all Kingdoms which are not Elective till the peoples ſubſequent conſent, and though it be by diſcent, yet 'tis a continuation of a Conqueſt till the people conſent and voluntarily ſubmit to a <hi>Government,</hi> they are but ſlaves and in reaſon they may free themſelves if they can; for conqueſt gains a title amongſt beaſts, not amongſt men. In <hi>France</hi> the King begins his Reign from the day of his <hi>Coronation,</hi> the <hi>Archbiſhop</hi> asks the people if he ſhal be King, the twelve <hi>Peers</hi> or ſome that perſonate them ſay Yes, they girt the <hi>ſword</hi> about him, then he ſwears to defend the Laws: and is any thing more <hi>natural</hi> then to keep an Oath? And though vertuous Kings have prevailed with the people to make their <hi>Crowns hereditary,</hi> yet the <hi>Coronation</hi> ſhews the ſhel that the kernel hath been in<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Samuel</hi> was a good Iudg, and there was nothing could be objected againſt him, therefore God was diſpleaſed at their inordinate deſire of a King, and it ſeems to me that the <hi>Lord</hi> declares his diſlike of all ſuch Kings as the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens were, that is, Kings with an unlimited power, that are not tied to any Laws; for he gave them a King in his wrath, therein dealing with them as the wiſe Phyſitian with his d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſtempered &amp; im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patient <hi>Patient,</hi> who deſiring to drink wine, tels him the danger of inflamation, yet wine he wil have, and the Phyſitian conſidering a little wine wil do but a little hurt, rather then his <hi>Patient</hi> by fret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſhould take greater hurt, preſcribes a little white wine where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Phyſitian doth not approve his drinking of wine, but of two evils chooſeth the leaſt: The <hi>Jews</hi> would have a King for <hi>Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty</hi> and <hi>splendor</hi> like the Heathens, God permits this, he approves it not, it ſeems to me that the <hi>Lord</hi> renounces the very <hi>Genus</hi> of ſuch Kings that have no Laws to govern by but their own wils:<note place="margin">Gen. 10.49</note> for if it be obiected that God had promiſed them a King and a Scepter in <hi>Iſrael:</hi> I anſwer that when God cals any man to ſuch high honor
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:114508:7"/> he gives him anſwerable abilities: when he places any man upon the bench of juſtice he never ſets himſelf beſides the cuſhion; beſides he told thoſe Kings whom he anointed what their duty was, not to exalt themſelves overmuch above their brethren,<note place="margin">Deut. 17.</note> to delight themſelves in the Law of God; out of which I infer that the <hi>Turks, Tartars</hi> and all people that live at the beck and nod of <hi>Tyrannical</hi> men may and ought to free themſelves from that <hi>Tyranny,</hi> if, and when they can; to deſire too great a King is to have a River too impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous; for ſuch <hi>Tyrants</hi> that ſo domineer with a rod of Iron do not govern by Gods permiſſive hand of <hi>approbation</hi> or <hi>benediction,</hi> but by the permiſſive hand of his <hi>providence,</hi> ſuffering them to ſcourge the people, for ends beſt known to himſelf until he open a way for the people to work out their own infranchiſements.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That no Government is divine, I mean, by Gods approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, (for extraordinary callings I know none in theſe days) but that which is juſt and rational, for there can be no ſuch con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyance of power as is deſtructive of humanity; therefore for millions to be at the Command of one man, to obey him univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſally in all things, is irrational; for wiſe men are but men, and the beſt men are but men at the beſt, ſubject to the faults of the iraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible and concupiſcible faculties.</p>
            <p n="5">5. That to aſſume a Government without a title and to act be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond Commiſſion, to the deſtruction of thoſe whom they ſhould preſerve, is all one in reaſon; and ſo King <hi>James</hi> (that <hi>Phoenix</hi> of his age for ſolid learning) agrees that there may be a Tyrant as wel by male-Adminiſtration as he that comes in by Conqueſt: To ſpeak of the ſeveral Conqueſts that have been made in this Kindom by the <hi>Romans, Saxons, Danes</hi> and <hi>Normans,</hi> as alſo whether <hi>William</hi> the Conqueror came in upon his Remittor by ancient title I judg impertinent, but this is clear as Chryſtal that our An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors did voluntarily ſubmit to Kingly politick Government; that if the Conqueror were a Tyrant for want of title, the ſubſequent conſent of the people made him or his Succeſſors lawful Kings be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing equivalent to an election; as <hi>Leah</hi> by an after-conſent became <hi>Jacobs</hi> lawful wife though he was miſtaken in the marriage; and an <hi>error</hi> in the perſon nullifies the <hi>Matrimony.</hi> And the act of our Predeceſſors is as ſtrong and binding to us as if it had been our own perſonal conſent: A Law being the act and deed of the body po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litick in Parliament, voted by the whole Kingdom as the whole men
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:114508:7"/> ſees &amp; hears, inſtrumentally performed by the eyes and ears;<note place="margin">Pan. angli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um. Pan Ae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lium. Pan-Sicili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um. The firſt Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> wherein by intendment every man, woman, and child, is vertually preſent by <hi>repreſentation,</hi> or elſe a ſtatute could not bind them; and a Law binds not only their <hi>makers</hi> but their <hi>ſucceſſors,</hi> for <hi>Corpora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> never die; as the <hi>River of Thames</hi> keeps thought name the new waters perpetually ſucceed: And though it be not ſo clear when this conſent was given, yet we find that King <hi>H.</hi> the 1. <hi>Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleark</hi> youngeſt ſon to <hi>William</hi> the <hi>Conqueror,</hi> in the 16. year of his <hi>Reign</hi> called a <hi>Parliament</hi> at <hi>Saliſbury;</hi> which I do not conceive ſo much to be derived from the <hi>French</hi> word ſignifying Freedom of debate, as <hi>Parliamentum quaſi pariam Lamentum,</hi> the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint of the People<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> when there is any difference between the King and his Subjects, his Majeſty gives them leave to chooſe out of themſelves whom they pleaſe as <hi>Arbitrators,</hi> or <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>mpiers</hi> to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine the matter, wherein the Subject thought himſelf ſecure that he might chooſe his own <hi>Judges;</hi> and this was but equal be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the King choſe the <hi>Judges</hi> of the Law; and though it doth not appear that this agreement between the King and people, was reduced into writing (becauſe that eaſy co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſervatory of printing was not then invented) yet who knows but that it was written and ſince defaced, or Imbeziled; for my part I cannot imagine our <hi>Anceſtors</hi> to be ſo <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rrational,</hi> that they would ever agree that any man ſhould raign over them as their lawful King, by their ful conſents, but upon this condition, that when they found them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves oppreſſed and burthened, his <hi>Majeſty</hi> ſhould be obliged to call a Parliament, and to agree to ſuch Laws <hi>(quas vulgus eligerit)</hi> as the Parliament ſhould preſent unto him for their happy Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and not to diſſolve them till they had done the buſineſs they were intruſted to do for the good of the Kingdom; for Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments never dye intentionally; and why may not ſuch an <hi>Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> be loſt? As we know the Records of many <hi>Statutes</hi> are not to be found; yet it is written in the heart of every underſtanding man that ſo it was; for how irrational is it to imagine that the King was not bound to call Parliaments,<note place="margin">36. E. 3. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> which by <hi>Statutes</hi> ought to be every year or oftner, as need ſhal require: and if the <hi>King</hi> might diſolve them when he pleaſed what fickle things were <hi>Kings,</hi> what vain things were <hi>Parliaments;</hi> and though it have been ſtrongly obje<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ed, that when things have been wel ſetled, the King is to have the negative voice in making new Laws,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:114508:8"/> though not in expounding the old; becauſe a Kingdom may ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt without making new Laws, but not without executing the preſent Laws: I ſay that the objector is defective in ſtated Policy; for the alteration or enacting of new Laws, is as abſolutely neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary as to execute thoſe which are made; a Kingdom may be as wel undone for want of the Kings negative voice, as for not execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Laws already eſtabliſh't, for the wiſeſt <hi>Parliament</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not foreſee what wil be beſt for the Common good the next <hi>year;</hi> Such Exigencies of State may happen, and I obſerve that what hath been objected by the Kings late <hi>par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> to the <hi>contrary,</hi> hath been that the Law is otherwiſe, but words are the leaſt part of Reaſon; that which <hi>Mr. Jenkins</hi> writes is moſt true according to the <hi>Authorities</hi> which he vou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches; but what <hi>Authority</hi> is it; ſome of the <hi>Judges</hi> of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Law; very good, by whom were they made <hi>Judges?</hi> By the King. How came they by their places? The Eccho is, buy them, for until the ſtatute of 5. <hi>E.</hi> 6. All judicial places were ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally bought and ſold, as <hi>Horſes</hi> in <hi>Smith-feild;</hi> for a cheif Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices place, it may be 10000. hath been given, and how long to continue? during the Kings pleaſure; was it ſafe for them to argue for the <hi>Liberty</hi> of the Subject againſt the Kings <hi>Prerogative?</hi> the Temptation was <hi>very great</hi> to be for the Kings ſide in all <hi>Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments;</hi> beſides, <hi>Parliaments</hi> have been diſcontinued and ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lived: for my own part I do not much value his judgment, In a queſtion of <hi>prerogative,</hi> who holds his place at the <hi>Princes plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure;</hi> for to ſtand to my own judgment or the judgment of him whom I elect is much alike; yet as there have been in all ages ſome that have ſtood for the <hi>Honor of Chriſt,</hi> and reſiſted unto the death; ſo there have been ſome that have argued for the Peoples Liberties. <hi>Bracton</hi> ſaies, <hi>Rex non habet parem in regno ſuo niſi Comites,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Forteſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ue.</note> 
               <hi>Barones, et communes in Parliamento, et hanc poteſtatem a populo effluxam Rex habet.</hi> Another, that <hi>Rex eſt ſingulis ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor, univerſis minor,</hi> that the King hath no Peers in his Kingdom but the <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Commons in Parliament,</hi> that the King is grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then any Subject, but leſs then all his Subjects, and that he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rives all his power from the people. <hi>Fits Herbert</hi> and <hi>Shelley,</hi> that the King is ſervant to all his Subjects; ſet over them for their good; and this is the voice of right reaſon, 'tis impoſſible to ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, that ever any man ſhould have the conſent of the people, to
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:114508:8"/> be their King upon other conditions, without which no man hath right to wear the <hi>Diadem:</hi> for when the firſt <hi>Agreement</hi> was concerning the power of <hi>Parliaments,</hi> if the <hi>King</hi> ſhould have ſaid, <hi>Gentlemen, are you content to allow Me my Negative voyce, that if you vote the Kingdom to be in danger unleſs ſuch an Act paſs, if I refuſe to aſſent, ſhal nothing be done in that caſe?</hi> Surely no rational man but would have anſwered: <hi>May it pleaſe Your Majeſty, we ſhal uſe all dutiful means to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure Your Royal Aſſent, but if You ſtill refuſe, we mſt not ſit ſtill and ſee our ſelves ruined, we muſt ſave the Kingdom without Your Conſent, though we hope not againſt it:</hi> But then ſaith the <hi>Obiector,</hi> where is the Kings power? I anſwer, nothing at all diminiſhed: his <hi>Maieſty</hi> hath more power then he can ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine for the preſervation and happineſs of the Kingdom, which is the end of all <hi>Superiority,</hi> but nothing for the <hi>deſtruction and deſolation</hi> of the <hi>people:</hi> we ſay God is <hi>omnipotent,</hi> and yet he cannot ſin nor do any iniuſtice: ſhal we ſay that the Kings power is diminiſhed, becauſe he may not hurt the people, or that a man is leſs in health becauſ he hath many Phyſitians to attend him? nothing leſs: for 'tis impotence and weakneſs to do hurt and iniury: but the King is impowred for the good of the people: true, but he may not ſay that is for the Kingdoms good, which they ſay is for their hurt: what I do for my own good I may undo. Methinks this ſhould ſatisfie every noble Prince; let my Subjects in Parliament pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound what Laws they pleaſe for their own ſecurity, 'tis a great eaſe to me: if the Laws be not good they may thank themſelves, if they be good the honor is mine, my conſent being as the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter-builder that gives the form and life to the Architecture; and if the Subiect ſuffers I cannot be blamed; but if the contrary ſhould be Law what miſerable things were Subiects; who wil truſt his own father with his life? And who can be merry if a King or Governor may divide his head from his body, or him from his deareſt relations by impriſonment, or otherwiſe, when he pleaſeth; but here lies the root of all our miſery; we take all for gold that gliſters, every thing to be reaſon that looks like it, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very caſe to be <hi>Law</hi> which we find written in our <hi>Law</hi> books; whereas <hi>Law</hi> is reaſon adiudged in a Court of Record, where rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is the <hi>Genus,</hi> &amp; the Court makes the difference from <hi>extraiuditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al</hi> diſcourſ w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> may be <hi>rationally,</hi> yet is not <hi>legally</hi> iuſt, if it be not
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:114508:9"/> reaſon the pronunciation of 10000. <hi>Judges</hi> cannot make it <hi>Law</hi> no more then the <hi>Venetian Madonnas</hi> can by their huge high heels in reality add one Cubit to their ſtature; as for example 'tis a Max me in <hi>Law</hi> that the King can do no wrong, therefore if he kill or raviſh 'tis neither Murder nor Felony; I ſay 'tis againſt reaſon, therefore againſt <hi>Law;</hi> for if the King may kill one man he may kill one hundred, and what Courtier dare give any faithful advice when the King may without controul kill him or ſtrangle him, and ſo not be guilty of blood; as the grand <hi>Turk</hi> that ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving promiſed to ſpare a mans blood, cauſed him to be ſtrangled, and ſo ſhed no blood: or ſomething like the caſe of the <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Gloceſter</hi> by King <hi>H.</hi> 7. this was acknowledged by the <hi>Tyrant,</hi> who having a mind to kill his <hi>brother,</hi> his <hi>Chancellor</hi> told him he might not by <hi>Law</hi> commit <hi>Fratricide,</hi> but, ſaith he, is there not a <hi>Law</hi> that I may do what I pleaſe? and let but Mr <hi>Jenkins</hi> anſwer, whether thoſe Judges, whoſe <hi>Authorities</hi> he vouches were not of opinion that whatſoever the King did, it is in <hi>Law</hi> no offence, and then all that he hath written or can write againſt the Parl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ament wil not bear the weight of a feather: and I humbly intreat all indifferent men that read books more for ſatisfaction then a deſire to contend for any party, but to anſwer me this queſtion: Why ſhould there be any more credit given to the opinion and <hi>authorities</hi> of the Judges, ſpecially ſuch as payd dear for their places, in matters of difference between the King and his Subjects in point of property, then there was to the Biſhops for matter of Divinity: were they not both the Kings creatures alike? Was it the way of preferment by ſtanding for the liberty of the Subject to get great eſtates? Have not the Iudges in many Countries been the raiſers and firſt founders of great and noble Families? And were thoſe eſtates got by pleading for the liberty of the ſubject a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Prerogative?</hi> We know who it was, not long ſince, that got a vaſt eſtate, and thinking to ingratiate himſelf with his Prince, ſaid, he was ſeldom or never of counſel in paſſing any Pattent but he reſerved ſome ſtarting hole to make it voyd in <hi>Law</hi> if need were, which was as good as an act of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption. This is the <hi>grand Error,</hi> that ſubordinate officers are accountable only to the King, and the King to God, whereas all <hi>Judges</hi> and <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> are intruſted by the people: if the people give power to the King to choſe them, 'tis out of a
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:114508:9"/> confidence that his <hi>Majeſty</hi> wil nominate ſuch as ſhal moſt faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully ſerve the peoples good, and when <hi>Arbitrators</hi> are impow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to chooſe an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>mpire,</hi> he may be truly ſaid to be choſen by the parties litigant: this ruines Juſtice, when men in places of <hi>Authority</hi> more eſteem him that gives them their Commiſſion, then the buſineſs that they are imployed about; when their eyes are more intentively fix't upon the ſtars of their inclinations who preferred them, then upon the publick good of the Kingdom, for whoſe ſake they were preferred: for when a Magiſtrate is made great, the principal intent and meaning of the Law is not his great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and honor, but to advance publick juſtice: I, but ſays one, he is ſuch a mans creature, raiſed by him <hi>E viliſſimo pulvere,</hi> muſt not he requite his love, and pleaſure his Father? No, juſtice is blind and knows neither father nor mother; the <hi>Judg</hi> looks not at the manner of the conveyance of his power, how he comes by his <hi>Authority,</hi> but at the matter of his Commiſſion, and the true end of <hi>Judicature:</hi> the right underſtanding of one Scripture, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.13, 14. makes a good <hi>Judg,</hi> the words are plain, and being learned (for learning is a ſpecial gift ſanctified for matters of policy and government) obſerves, that Kings are a humane Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance as wel as Corporations and Societies, and concludes that all thoſe Scholaſtical diſcourſes of Kings, being <hi>Jure Divino,</hi> are but tryals of Wit; and by <hi>Supream</hi> he intends that the <hi>King</hi> is ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream to adminiſter the Law, not to make Laws, much leſs break them, and Governors ſent by him are for the puniſhment of evil doers, and for the praiſe of them that do wel, the want of this conſideration ruined the <hi>Judges</hi> in point of ſhip-money, the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt part whereof were very very learned men.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Haec eſt, crede mihi, cunctorum cauſa malorum</l>
               <l>Scripturas Domini non didiciſſe ſacras.</l>
            </q>
            <p>I know this <hi>Error</hi> in judgment undid the Lord Keepers, <hi>Finch</hi> and <hi>Littleton,</hi> men of brave ſpirits, had they been for publick li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties: <hi>Lord Chief Iuſtice. Banks</hi> a man profoundly ſtudied: And Mr <hi>Jenkins</hi> being made a Iudg thinks himſelf bound in honor, <hi>Junare in verba:</hi> Engliſh men have ever been moſt thankful to thoſe whoſe favor hath been their quickning ſpirit: 'tis pity any man ſhould be undone for his ingenuity, and though the <hi>Law</hi> be
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:114508:10"/> rather politick then moral, yet I wiſh repentance may be expiatory ſo far as <hi>Salus</hi> be not indangered: O but, ſays one, all the great <hi>Lawyers</hi> followed the King! Not ſo neither, I am ſure the poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick <hi>Lawyer</hi> ſtayd behind: Ambition and Avarice make many a man argue againſt their own liberties how many men in the world are content to be ſlaves to ſome few, that millions may be in ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vility to them: it being demanded in a Counſel why ſo many there preſent ſhould be of opinion that the Pope was above the Counſel, it being againſt themſelves: Honeſt <hi>Verideus</hi> ſaid, the anſwer was eaſie, becauſe the Pope had ſo many Cardinals caps, fat Biſhopricks and rich Offices to beſtow, and the Counſel had none at their diſpoſing. The Biſhops preached at <hi>Court</hi> to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance <hi>Prerogative above Law:</hi> ſaying, my <hi>Lord the King is like an Angel of light:</hi> now Angels all accountable to God only: that the King is <hi>Iure Divino,</hi> and are ſubordinate Officers <hi>Iure humano:</hi> whereas the Apoſtle calls Kings a humane Ordinance, and there is not a man in the <hi>Army</hi> from the moſt noble General to the loweſt Officer, but is as much <hi>Iure Divino</hi> as the Kings Maieſty or the ſo much deſired <hi>Preſbytery:</hi> That <hi>David</hi> never offended againſt <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>riah,</hi> for he ſaith, <hi>againſt thee, thee only, O Lord, have I offended:</hi> giving the reaſon that <hi>Bathſheba</hi> was his ſubiect, and that a man may do what he wil with his own: and that his <hi>Majeſty</hi> was to repent of any oath that he had made for doing Iuſtice, for being intruſted by God, the oaths are voyd: <hi>Poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitenda preſumptio, non perficienda promiſſio:</hi> The Iudges in like manner ſay that the <hi>King</hi> is a ſpeaking <hi>Law,</hi> and carries all the <hi>Laws</hi> in his breaſt and might call <hi>Parliaments</hi> and diſſolve them at his own pleaſure: which if it were ſo, what a fooliſh thing was it to ſend for Writs and trouble the Counties with ſuch <hi>Iudibrious Elections,</hi> like him that in the beginning of his Will deviſed 20000 l. to his wife, but in the latter end for divers good cauſes and conſiderations him thereunto moving, revoked the ſaid <hi>Legacy,</hi> and left her nothing: When <hi>Iezabel</hi> had a mind to <hi>Naboths</hi> Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard it was no hard matter to get Iudges to declare the right againſt the ſubiect: In dark times of Popery how eaſie was it for Princes to prefer ſuch men to great places that would be Inſtruments to execute what ever they would have to be
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:114508:10"/> done; but I have better thoughts of the preſent times for now ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicial places are wel got, and by conſequence wel uſed. I dare ſay there are not more honeſt men (the number conſidered) the of any profeſſion in the world, then are toward <hi>Law</hi> in this Kingdom, and the Subjects would quickly find their uſefulneſs to the ſtate, were there but one good ſtatute to cut off at one blow all unneceſſary delays in matters of <hi>Juſtice, Root</hi> and <hi>Branch</hi> [which are far more hurtful to the Kingdom, then ever Biſhops were] which God and the Parliament grant. The <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror</hi> having a mind to a Subiects horſe, ſaid all is mine, therefore this horſe is mine: the 2 great <hi>Civilians, Bartolus,</hi> and <hi>Baldus</hi> were retained: one for the King ſaid, the property of all goods belongs to the <hi>Emperor;</hi> for he that may command the lives may command the goods of his Subiects, and the uſufruict and poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion only is the Subiects: the other <hi>Lawyer</hi> ſaid for the Subiects, that the property is in the Subiect, and dominion only in the King according to <hi>Law:</hi> the Chancellor being <hi>Judg</hi> ſaid, all is the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perors: who gave the horſe to his Counſel, and told the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects Councel he ſhould never be a Iudg ſo long as he continued of that opinion: but let no man obiect that I ſeem to aſperſe thoſe learned Iudges which are at reſt: I honor the memory of all good Common-wealths-men: and my opinion of them is that accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Delatory forms of proceedings, they were good Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces between party and party, but when the Kings Prerogative and the Subiects liberty came in Competition, I affirm it confidently that all Iudgments have not been according to right reaſon: witneſs the caſe of the Shipmony, Knight-hood money, Tunage, Poun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage, and Monopolies of all ſorts, which they did not declare ille<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal: And how many Gallant worthys have they ſuffered to live or dye in Priſon, whom they ought to have ſet at liberty by <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beas corpus?</hi> And he that looks into matters with a ſingle eye, may eaſily diſcern that the Fountains from whence theſe late ſtreams of blood have iſſued, were no other but the pride of the Biſhops (a Generation who hated to be reformed therefore juſtly aboliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) and the puſillanimity and cowardice of the Iudges; for if the Biſhops had been indulgent to honeſt people, and not Lorded it o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the Lords inheritance, (poor ſouls they would have been content to have ſuffered much for quietneſs ſake, might they have but had the freedom of their Conſciences in a
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:114508:11"/> peaceable manner) and the <hi>Judges</hi> been couragious to have exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted impartial <hi>Juſtice</hi> between the King, and Courtiers and the Subiect: and in doubtful matter to have inclined to Liberty, the ſword had never been unſheathed.</p>
            <p>And for theſe preſent Reverend <hi>Judges,</hi> I have Honorable thoughts of them, but this I muſt ſay (elſe I ſhould be a Traytor to my Country) that they tye themſelves too much to old forms, and in Courting the ſhadow of formalities, and conſerving the courſe of their Court, they neglect the ſubſtance of morall <hi>Juſtice,</hi> in not helping ſpeedily every man to his due when the matter comes fairly before them, for I muſt live and dye upon it, that he doth not deſerve the name of a good Judg that when the right appears to the <hi>Court;</hi> doth not help the party to it: beleeve it there is not ſo great an enemy to the Liberty of the Subject, as this over-doting upon old forms, as if the Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monial Law of the <hi>Jews</hi> were to be revived in the Common Laws of England; If a Judg or <hi>Chancellor,</hi> 300 years ago, delivered an <hi>Erronious</hi> opinion, this muſt bind us becauſe he ſaid ſo; and ſo if one Judg once err, this Kingdom muſt be undone perpetually be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Law is ſo; Right reaſon is the wiſe mans preſident: where <hi>Judges</hi> are learned and ſolid what need they <hi>ſearch for Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidents?</hi> And why may not we make Preſidents for others as wel as they for us? I never yet knew a politique <hi>Judg</hi> in England that, conſidering the end of the Law is to ſpeedy juſtice, would diſpence with writs to do right; loſe formalities to find eſſentials: twelve Such politique <hi>Judges</hi> would quickly make the Kingdom happy for moral juſtice: Taxes we ſee are multiplied in all Countries, but what way is there to make the Kingdom amends for all the precious blood and treaſure that hath been ſpilt and expended? Truly one Ordinance for quick and cheap juſtice would do it abundantly, that the poor may have juſtice for Gods ſake, and the rich for rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable Conſiderations: The favorites of ſtate have always magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied the happineſs of Engliſh men above all other nations in regard of the Aſſizes that twice a year <hi>Queen</hi> juſtice rides her <hi>Progreſs,</hi> and <hi>Juſtice</hi> is ſent them home to thier doors; but I profeſs the Kingdom is a great looſer by it, 'tis a meer ſpunge to ſuck away their moneys for little or no Conſideration, matters of the Crown only excepted, and why more haſt to hang a man for ſtealing a ſheep then to help a poor man to his juſt Debt? for what a charge
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:114508:11"/> is it to try a <hi>Niſi prius?</hi> and when the matter of fact is tryed the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is never the neerer; judgment is far of, the Defendent may dye, or elſs writs of <hi>Error</hi> brought: that a man is not behold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo much to the Law as to a good purſe to obtain his right; therefore this I would humbly beg of the Parliament for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent (becauſe to ſettle a Court of <hi>Judicature</hi> in every County wil require time and much wiſdom to foreſee and prevent ſubſequent inconveniences) that the Reverent <hi>Judges</hi> may every Circuit, if poſſibly to begin this Summer circuit, be enabled by Commiſſion to hear and determine, beſides the <hi>Niſi priſes,</hi> all private differences between party and party throughout the whole Kingdom, the matter to be brought before them by Petition the Defendent to have timely notice in perſon, or at his dwelling houſe by <hi>Affidavit</hi> of two witneſſes, in caſe he appear not; both parties, to bring their wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes and evidences, and the matter being heard to be ſpeedily en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and execution by the Sherif accordingly, unleſs it be very weighty, and then to be adjourned to <hi>Weſtminſter;</hi> whereby a difference may be ended in a moneths time, for 5. l. charge at the moſt, which now coſts 50, or 100. l. and is 3 years at the leaſt in deciding, and ends moſt commonly with the ruin of one party; and the other gets ſuch a blow that is long in recovering. I know this wil be counted a dangerous deſign tending to overthrow the Law, but it is only by ſuch as fear rather the overthrow of their own profit more then they value the <hi>Law</hi> and the Prophets; for I am ſure they cry out for quick and cheap juſtice: and I wil burn my books, nay venture my life upon it, that no man can render a reaſon nor frame an objection againſt this, but that I can eaſily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fute it, if this be granted as a <hi>maxime</hi> of ſtate, that the Publique good and quiet of many is to be preſerved before the private profit of a few, ſay not that I ſhal hereby wrong my own profeſſion: 'tis all one if I did in reference to the Publique good: but this is a great miſtake, <hi>Lawyers</hi> would get more by ſpeedy Juſtice, for who had not rather give his Councel 40. s. to end his buſineſs in a day, then attend many moneths, and give him 10. s. a time for motion upon motion, references and references: beſides no wiſe man wil go to Law for: as matters are carryed, the worſt end by Arbitriments is better then the beſt can be expected by the Law, all things compu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, unleſs in ſpecial caſes; and ſo what is loſt in the hundred is found in the Shire: pray do not ſay this wil prejudice the City, and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:114508:12"/> keep away Termers: ſuppoſe it were ſo, why ſhould all the blood in the body be drawn into one veine? When one member ſwels too much the body pines: but that's another miſtake: for men would beſtow that in Cloaths and Commodities which they now ſpend in Law-ſuits: but I hope time wil make us wiſe: but then comes the old objection, wil you have all things arbitrary and uncertain? Nothing leſs, but every Controverſie to be ended ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to reaſon and every former Preſident, and Judgment to be authentical and binding ſo far as there is reaſon for it, and not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe: the contrary practiſe is as dangerous to the ſtate as im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicite faith in matters of ſalvation: for I would but ask this que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion: If a Judg beleives in his Conſcience that former Preſidents were againſt reaſon, whether if he obſerve them he doth not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in condemn himſelf, but if he ſee reaſon for the <hi>Judgment,</hi> then it is his own <hi>Judgment</hi> that leads him, and not the bare Authority of his Predeceſſors; but it wil be alledged that reaſon is malleable, and one reaſon may be brought againſt another: truly in <hi>matters</hi> of moral <hi>Juſtice</hi> tis hard to imagine any great difficulty: that cauſe, which at firſt is a bul-ruſh, comes to be a <hi>Gyant:</hi> differences for the moſt part are plain and very eaſie at the firſt beginning of the <hi>ſuit;</hi> but when by motion upon motion, the cauſe is put out of its courſe, the <hi>matter</hi> grows ſo intricate that a poor <hi>Clyent</hi> can ſcarce get out of the <hi>Labyrinth:</hi> but my meaning is not that every rational man ſhould be able to underſtand the reaſon of a <hi>Law</hi>-caſe: but that, that cannot be given <hi>Law</hi> when there is a good reaſon to be given againſt it: as put the caſe there is a verdict for a <hi>Juſt debt,</hi> now whatſoever can be alleadged that ſuch a proceſs did not iſſue regularly, yet reaſon ſays that the Debt ought to be preſently paid; and this can be no more called confuſion, then <hi>Mithridate</hi> deſerves the name of Poyſon.</p>
            <p>And now if I ſhould proceed Methodically, I ſhould argue whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Parliament have ſufficient grounds to raiſe Armies as they did, but that is but to argue whether the Proteſtants or the Papiſts be of the true Religion: and next I ſhould lay down what thoſe juſt grounds and Arguments were: but that would ſavor of Preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, having been ſo fully and ungainſayingly declared by both Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and might be unſafe if I ſhould omit any: and at the beſt prove tedious to the reader, my deſire being not to build upon any mans foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, nor to bring Arguments which have been expoſed to Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:114508:12"/> view already, though I judg them better then my own, yet 'tis but a kind of coſenage to the reader, to invite him to make ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral purchaſes of the ſame matter, a trick more Common then Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable in this Printing age: yet ſomething I muſt ſay concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning thoſe matters; which is this, that the Arguments and motives which ſwayed me, to adhere ſo cordially and conſtantly to the Parliament againſt the late <hi>Oxford</hi> party, were rather Scripture grounds and reaſons of ſtate, and ſelf preſervation, then Law-caſes and Printed authorities; for I always conceived that the King was obliged, to call Parliaments, as often as the generallity of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple beſought him, and to diſolve them til the Parliament ſaid, <hi>om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia bene</hi> was againſt his oath, and that he was to conſent to all ſuch Laws as ſhould humbly be preſented to his Majeſty by both Houſes; and when I find in our Law books, that the King is a God upon earth, as God is a King in heaven (alas <hi>Mr. Jenkins</hi> ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth too meanly and lowly of the Kings prerogative) both in thoſe Incommunicable Excellencies of Infinitneſs and divine perfection; as alſo his Majeſties power and perpetuity, that by a <hi>non obſtante,</hi> he may diſpence with a ſtatute Law: a pure invention to ſet the King above the Law: I thought thus, that ſeldom did any man re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe to be a Biſhop or a Judg, and when I read thoſe caſes that it hath been often adiudged that the King could do wrong, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the meaning is that the King ſhould do no wrong; a letter wil much alter the caſe: for I find that when ſmal offences and treſpaſſes are not puniſh't, a reaſon rendred that the Law regards not ſmal things; the book to warrant it carrys the ſenſe, that the Law reckons not the minuts and the odd hours, which make the Leap year; and I find <hi>Mr. J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nkins</hi> (though certainly a man deeply learned in Law Caſes, and in the Hiſto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ical part of the laws; I wiſh he had ſo wel ſtudied the end of Government, which is the welfare of the people) vouching Authorities by the halfs, for where he ſays that <hi>Bracton</hi> ſays, the King hath no ſuperior or e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual but God, he omits what the book adds, unleſs it be the <hi>Lords and Commons in Parliament:</hi> and ſo a man might as wel argue, that our bleſſed Savior ſaid, hang all the <hi>Law and the Prophets;</hi> becauſe he ſaid upon theſe two Commandments, hang all the <hi>Law</hi> and the <hi>Prophets.</hi> When I read that the King may pardon murder, ſpecially if the word murder, be not in the pardon, I find it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to Scripture, and therefore take it to be no <hi>Law:</hi> and when
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:114508:13"/> I read that the King by his Prerogative may make a 20. s. piece by Proclamation to go currant for 40. s. or to be worth but 6. d. I conceive this to be againſt reaſon, and ſo againſt <hi>Law,</hi> worſe then that abominable project of braſs money, as the Honorable Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons were pleaſed to call it; for if I have 20. s. in my pocket and the King may proclaim this to be worth but 6. d. then may he take 19. s. and 6. d. from me, and then where is the liberty of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects? Therefore I conceive that the Kings Prerogative in moneys is for the wel ballancing of trade, and equallity of exchanges be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween us and other Nations: in caſe that other Forraign King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms or ſtates ſhould inhanſe or debaſe their moneys, the King may do the like for the good of this Kingdom: that our moneys be not exhauſted and drawn out of the Kingdom, if it ſhould be much dearer here then there; but the pureſt fallacy that I have met with, is that, how can the Parliament grant a pardon to others, when themſelves ſent to the King to <hi>New-caſtle</hi> for a pardon: as if a General pardon which is uſually granted at the end of every Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament, ſhould prove the Parliament men guilty of all the offences thereby pardoned: A general pardon which is in effect as an act of Oblivion, ſuppoſes no particular man guilty, but <hi>tollit reatum quoad mundum:</hi> but a ſpecial pardon pre-ſuppoſes the offence: and muſt be pleaded: and ſo reaſon ſpeaks it out that the King hath no Prerogative, whereby to hurt the people, but wholly for their good, ſave only in matters of honor and pleaſure, and in a favourable conſtruction of his Grants to be conſtrued according to his intention, and not deception: which Priviledg every Subject in reaſon ought to enjoy, and I wiſh heartily that his Majeſty may enjoy all his ancient and undoubted Royalties, and Prerogatives, that are according to Scripture and right reaſon: beſides which there is nothing that can judg between a Prince and his people but the ſword: and let his Majeſties Honor be ſuperior by many ſtories, then it was for the preſervation of the Kingdom, in all things not injurious to the Subject, which his Majeſtie ſaies is all that he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires: and God forbid he ſhould have any leſs, but let him not have power to hurt his Subjects, for he that by <hi>Law</hi> may do ſo, though he were the beſt man living, yet he is a Potential Tyrant, and his Subiects may fear him, but they can never love him: and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit of ſuch a power, is enough to ſpoyl the beſt Prince living: I know ſome <hi>Hiſpanialized</hi> Courtiers and Common Lawyers that
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:114508:13"/> having reſted in the <hi>Letter</hi> of the <hi>Law,</hi> not looking into the true meaning of it, have made his <hi>Maieſty</hi> beleeve that the <hi>Parliament</hi> have done him wrong, and taken away his Forts and Caſtles from him. What reaſon can Mr <hi>Jenkins,</hi> or any man give why the King may not as wel command all the money in the Kingdom as all the ſtrength in the Kingdom, or all the horſes in the Kingdom in order to the <hi>Militia?</hi> As the Pope commands temporals in order to ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuals, for money is the ſinew of War: Whereas his <hi>Maieſty</hi> was never intruſted by the people againſt themſelvs, but againſt forraign forces, and that I take to be the meaning of the Oath of <hi>Suprea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy,</hi> which was intended againſt the Pope, that the Pope is in no ſort head of the Church, other meaning I know none in a ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual way but civilly, and ſo it was declared by that gracious Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> about the 13. year of her raign, which is or ought to be printed: For did ever any rational people put the ſword into the hands of any man to have the point of it turned againſt themſelves? that 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 8. proves that Kings are to fight the peoples battels, not the people to fight their quarrels: and if it be obiected that the King never intended to hurt the ſubiect with their own ſword; I anſwer that that is all one, if the people ſay otherwiſe, for they muſt iudg, &amp; becauſe al the people cannot meet together, therfore the <hi>Parliament</hi> muſt judg, for not to argue the point concerning the power of the Militia, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> is but to argue whether a man be bound to kil himſelf. Put the caſe there were 20. men travelling together in a dangerous wilderneſs, they intruſt one as a Captain to carry the ſword, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend them againſt all aſſaults, &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mand them in order to their beſt ſafety, and make him Governor: at laſt they are of opinion that this Cap. intends to betray them, they intreat him to redeliver the ſword, he promiſes to be faithful to them: now in this caſe if there were no apparent ground of <hi>jealouſie</hi> and <hi>diſtruſt,</hi> the 19. are to be blamed for their <hi>levity</hi> &amp; <hi>diſloyalty,</hi> but yet this <hi>Governor</hi> is bound in juſtice and common honeſty to reſtore the ſword and not to make a <hi>war</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the 19. to reduce them to obedience; for if they wil be <hi>deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> who can help it? God doth not ſave any man againſt his wil, but of unwilling makes him willing: nor muſt a Kingdom be ſaved a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their wils: a Prince is not to lead his people by their noſes, but to open their eyes to ſee their own welfare and imbrace it: which if they wil not, their deſtruction is of themſelves, they do ill, but the <hi>Lord</hi> wil not have them cudgelled into obedience, for this we find an example in Scripture of the 10. Tribes which revolted
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:114508:14"/> from <hi>Rehoboam</hi> their lawful King who had 180000. choſen war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours to fight againſt them,<note place="margin">2 Chro. 11</note> but the Lord forbad; and though that be called a <hi>rebellion,</hi> in the laſt <hi>verſe</hi> of the former <hi>Chapter,</hi> the reaſon of that is, becauſe <hi>Rehoboam</hi> was King by Gods inſtitution and immediate appointment, and in ſuch a caſe m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ght <hi>Rehoboam</hi> have ſaid, <hi>ye have not rejected me but the Lord;</hi> but now all lawful power is originally in the people, and all lawful Governors choſen by them;<note place="margin">A Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queror hath <hi>Jus in re,</hi> not <hi>ad rem.</hi>
               </note> (for a <hi>Conqueſt</hi> is but a great <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>obbery</hi>) good <hi>Kings</hi> raign by Gods approbation, <hi>Tyrants</hi> by his permiſſion til the people can free themſelves; Kingdoms at firſt were Elective till good Kings prevailed to have their children ſucceed them, and certainly <hi>hereditary Kingdoms</hi> are beſt to prevent Factions: and therefore the 19. wil have their Captain command them no longer; he may not fight againſt them, if he could procure any to take his part: nor wil it avail to ſay that the 19. are Ignorant or diſtracted; for he muſt not queſtion the judgment of his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectors: if the people know not how to chooſe a King, then the Election is voyd, and ſo a defective title, but they that have judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to conſent, for reaſons beſt known to themſelves, may alter and diſ-aſſent, for this eaſe ſtands upon a ſpecial reaſon, differing from all caſes of bargains and contracts, that rights veſted cannot be deveſted, and what pleaſed at firſt may not diſpleaſe at laſt: the King is born for the good of his ſubjects, not they for his good, further then to give him <hi>honor, reverence and recompence:</hi> this is the wil of God to prevent Wars, which muſt otherwiſe follow inevitably: and 'tis a principle of <hi>right reaſon</hi> that as things are <hi>creat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d,</hi> ſo by the ſame power they are <hi>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſolved;</hi> they which may <hi>inſtitute</hi> may <hi>deſtitute;</hi> it ſtrengthens our faith in the <hi>reſurrection,</hi> that the ſame power which made us of nothing can raiſe us out of the duſt. Miſtake me not, I ſay if all the 19. ſhould ſo agree, if but 3. or 4. ſhould adhere to the Captain, I d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>liver no opinion in that caſe: but I am againſt that opinion that if any County or burrough. Town ſhal ſend for their Knights and Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſſes to return home and vote no longer, that in this caſe they ought to come back, becauſe no man can be repreſented longer then he pleaſes; this erew to deſtroy the frame of the <hi>Government:</hi> For though every ſeveral Shire and Burrough make their ſeveral Elections, yet they are ſent not only to vote for the good of their own County or Town, but for the general good of the Kingdom;
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:114508:14"/> and they make not ſeveral diſtinct <hi>repreſentative</hi> bodies, but one intire <hi>repreſentative</hi> body in the nature of a <hi>joyntenancy:</hi> as the Soul is in every part of the body, ſo every Member ſits in the Houſe for the good of the whole Kingdom, as if choſen by all the people: the ſeveral Elections being by <hi>agreement</hi> for the more conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency. But when B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rgeſſes are choſen for one Town, all the reſt give their conſents to ſuch an Election, and ſo in Law it may be called the Election of them all, as between partners in a Drade, one brings 1000 l. the other as much, this is layd out in Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities as a common ſtock, now none of them <hi>alone</hi> hath power over any part of the goods, though it may be purchaſed with his money, but all things is to be done by a joynt conſent, no diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution to be by parts, that is to diſmember the body, otherwiſe this would follow, that if two Burgeſſes voted only for that Town which ſent them, if one voted in the <hi>Affirmative</hi> and the other in the <hi>Negative</hi> nothing ſhould be done in that particular: but that which I chiefly intend in this <hi>diſcourſe</hi> is not only that there may be a right underſtanding but endeared affections between the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Parliament:</hi> and truly I know no way like this, to be perſwaded of each others ſincerity, that they acted according to their judgments &amp; that <hi>light</hi> which they had revealed to them: that his <hi>Majeſty</hi> would beleeve, as the truth is, that the <hi>Right Honorable Lords</hi> and the <hi>Honorable Commons</hi> did nothing but what they conceived themſelves in Honor and Iuſtice obliged to do for the ſafety of the Kingdom, and that otherwiſe they could not have anſwered it to thoſe whom they repreſented: and that the <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament</hi> would be perſwaded that his <hi>Majeſty</hi> did nothing but what he conceived himſelf in Honor bound to do, without which he could not have given an Account to God nor his people with comfort; for poſſibly there may be an <hi>invincible Ignorance</hi> of one anothers right. The <hi>Cananites</hi> were in poſſeſſion of a lawful title, the <hi>Lord</hi> commands <hi>Ioſhua</hi> to diſpoſſeſs them; who having a Command from God may lawfully fight, and they not knowing of Gods Command might lawfully defend themſelves: now in this caſe if the Lord had not intended a <hi>National Church</hi> &amp; the deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the <hi>Cananites,</hi> why might not an <hi>Iſraelite</hi> and a <hi>Cananite</hi> have been good friends, and ſaid thus one to another, truly what you did you had ſome colour of reaſon for it, at leſt you thought you did for the beſt, it may be I ſhould have done ſo, had I been
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:114508:15"/> in your caſe: therefore let us do as we would be done by, as there have been <hi>Arguments</hi> framed againſt each others proceedings, ſo I wiſh heartily that the <hi>Kings Majeſty</hi> and thoſe evil Counſellors who were about him (hee's now guarded with Angels in compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon) would argue thus for the Parliament; the Kingdom petitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned both Houſes to raiſe Arms for their preſervation; what could the Parliament do in ſuch a caſe, having voted that there was an apparent deſign to inſlave the people? had it been ſufficient for the Members to have told the people; Truly we gave his Majeſty faithful advice, beſought him to reform what was amiſs, but he heark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to his Courtiers and would not; and ſo we left him to do what he pleaſed. What would the Kingdom have ſaid in ſuch a caſe? would they not have exclaimed againſt their Knights and Burgeſſes, as the <hi>French</hi> do againſt their twelve Peers which being intruſted to oppoſe Tyranny prevaricated. Oh ye unfaithful men I was there ever ſo great a breach of <hi>Truſt</hi> in the world heard of? Did we Elect you to infranchiſe us, and do you ſuffer us to be inſlaved? Would you not put us into a Poſture of war to defend our ſelves, but ſuffer us to be deſtroyd inſenſibly, ſince you wil not deliver us, our <hi>freedom</hi> muſt come ſome other way; what can be ſaid in reaſon againſt this? And ſo that the <hi>Parliament</hi> would argue for his <hi>Majeſty,</hi> amongſt others to uſe but this: What? muſt his Majeſty give his Royal Aſſent to all ſuch <hi>Laws</hi> that both Houſes ſhal preſent unto him? Put the caſe then, that the <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Commons</hi> in <hi>England</hi> preſent an <hi>Act</hi> for the free exerciſe of the <hi>Proteſtant Religion</hi> in this Kingdom, and the <hi>Lords and Commons</hi> in <hi>Ireland</hi> preſent an <hi>Act</hi> to his Majeſty for the eſtabliſhing of Popery in that Kingdom; what ſhould his Majeſty do in ſuch a caſe? Muſt not his Maieſty ſee by his own eys and make uſe of his own Iudgment and diſcreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on what is fitteſt to be done therein? Are not the ſinews of the <hi>Leviathan</hi> perplexed, as <hi>Iob</hi> ſpeaks, is not this a ground to ſcruple the verity of that <hi>doctrine,</hi> that his Maieſty ought by his oath to ratifie ſuch <hi>Laws</hi> as ſhal by both Houſes be agreed upon? I have known many Clyents reconciled after tedious ſuites, and long en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoring the ruine of one another; but it hath been upon this ground, that they have verily beleeved that nothing was done by either of them maliciouſly, but in order to the obtaining of their ſeveral rights; and that by Gods bleſſing hath been an expedient, not only to tye their hands, but to unite their hearts, that it may be
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:114508:15"/> ſo between the King and Parliament, is my dayly prayer: til it be ſo, this Kingdom wil not be ſetled in peace and tranquillity. The very truth is, that by the Letter of Scripture and ſome Law caſes, the King had a Colour to do what he did, as Gods Ordinance, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving an undoubted right to the Crown by deſcent, as his proper in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance which no other Court in the Kingdom could have the leaſt ſhadow of reaſon to do if they ſhould break truſt with the people.</p>
            <p>I have but one ſtair more to mount before I come to the Army, and that is, how far the Kingdom is to be obedient to the King and Parliament in all caſes? And herein I deſire to be carefully obſerved; becauſe the Kingdom cannot be convened in it's diffuſive body, therefore it is formed into an artificial body in the high Court of Parliament, which without all queſtion is the Supream Court, from which there is no appeal to any other, concerning poſitive Laws, for the deciding, and determining of the arduous and moſt difficult affairs of the Kingdom, both for titles of land when they pleaſe, and all the great turnings and windings of ſtate, it being moſt proper to determine the greateſt matters in the higheſt Court; in which caſes though the judgment of Parliament be not unerrable, becauſe the members not impeccable: yet it is Inevitable; for the Publique judgment of ſtate reſides there; and it is the wil of God that for the preventing of wars and bloodſhed that there ſhould in every nation be ſome ſupream Court to whoſe determinations every private man is to ſubmit, as it is in <hi>Deut.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 17.11.</note> poſſibly many <hi>of the <hi>Iews</hi> might conceive that the <hi>ju<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>gment</hi> of the <hi>Iudg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s</hi> &amp; <hi>Levites</hi> was not always right, yet it muſt ſtand to prevent a greater evil; I am not of opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with learned M <hi>Jenkins,</hi> that acts of <hi>Parliament,</hi> which carry a ſeem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng repugnancy are voyd, or that the Judges have power to controle acts of Parliament, and conſtrue them to be void, for this is to erect a higher tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunal; the Judges are obliged to expound the Statute according to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of the makers, otherwiſe they that are at the Oars ſhould row againſt them that ſit at the ſtern. The intent of the <hi>Legiſlators</hi> is the <hi>Empreſs</hi> and <hi>Qeen Regent,</hi> which the Judges are ſtrictly to obſerve, and the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>efore that objection of a repugnancy in the countenance of this Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>liament (for how can ther<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> be a Parliament every 3 year, if this continue 7 years) is but a flouriſh, for in all acts, grants, and wils, ſuch an Expoſition is to be made that every word may have its weight and be of force the meaning is pla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n, that after this Parliament the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e ſhal be a Triennial Parliament, &amp; ſome incongruity, no more then when a man makes a Leaſe for 7 years &amp; after from year to year, and no ac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſhal be conſtrued to be voyd when by any reaſonable intendments it may be made good; the Judges being Aſſiſtants in the upper Houſe, cannot but know the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:114508:16"/> of the ſtatute if it ſhould be penned obſcurely, and by the ſame reaſon they ought as wel to take notice of every private act as thoſe which are general, and not to hazard the right of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect upon a nicity of Pleading which is ſo fatal to many mens rights: but it behoves <hi>Mr. Jenkins</hi> to hold that Iudges may expound acts of Parliament to be void: when himſelf being a Iudg in <hi>Wales,</hi> nullified Ordinances of Parliament, made for the liberty of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect, which he ought to look upon as an Ordinance of God, not to be diſputed but obeyed: but this is the fruit of his ſtudying <hi>Law</hi> upon the Sabbath days: whereof he was wont ſo much to glory, that he gained one year in 7, in his ſtudy: but all the hurt I wiſh him, is, that he would now ſtudy the Law of God, which is the only touchſtone of all humane Actions, and the Archetype of all Governments: and what is againſt it, is pure innovation. But this I agree, that a ſtatute againſt the law of God or nature is void, for man having no hand in making the laws of God or nature, they may not intermeddle in the Changing or repealing of them: but any poſitive law made by man, may be altered by the ſame Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority: and therefore the meaning of that in <hi>Dan.</hi> like the <hi>Laws</hi> of the <hi>Medes</hi> and <hi>Perſians,</hi> which are unchangeable, is to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, either that thoſe <hi>Laws</hi> were only a ratification of the Law of God or nature: a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Counſel of <hi>Trent,</hi> that gave Authority to the holy Scripture, or elſe that they might not be altered by the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror without the peoples conſent. In the next place I conceive that no fundamental law of this Kingdom can be altered by the King and Parliament: but my meaning is, that nothing is fundamental but what is for the ſafety and happyneſs of the people: that which was no Law before it was written, that may be altered; but the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs of the people was a <hi>Law</hi> before all written <hi>Laws. Magna Charta</hi> was <hi>Law</hi> before it was written, and collected but for ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſier Conſervation, being for the peoples happyneſs: and that ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute in 42. <hi>E.</hi> 3. that every Law made againſt <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> ſhal be void, is no more then the voice of Reaſon: for the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation cannot be removed, ſo long as the building ſtands. It trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles me to hear, when I am ſaying that <hi>Lawyers</hi> ought not to make the trouble and diſquiet of poor men, the Baſis of their Grandor; And that it were happy for the Kingdom, if the Parliament would device ſome expedient for ſummary juſtice: what ſaies one, wil you deſtroy all, and change the fundamental Conſtitutions of the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:114508:16"/> Kingdom? As if the eaſe and welfare of the people ſhould be their deſtruction; I look upon it as one of the moſt neceſſary works to be done in this Kingdom, and that wherein there wil appear much oppoſition, and if it be not ſuddainly done, it wil not be done in this Generation; our Laws are actually or potentially the beſt in the world, for if any thing be amiſs, the Parliament may reform it ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to right reaſon, which is the ſoul of al humane Laws without exception, &amp; no Law ought to live longer then the reaſon of it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinues: away with all bugbear objections, and after <hi>Naſeby</hi> fight lets never diſtruſt God for any thing: I mean let us have ſuch Laws as are not directly againſt Scripture: and for which ſome reaſon may be given beſides the courſe of the Court: for that, for which probable reaſon may be rendred on both ſides, is not fundamental; as the eldeſt ſon to inherite the whole eſtate: certainly there ought in all reaſon ſome proviſion to be made for the young Children, if the Father make none for them in his live time: but true it is, that many poſitive Laws are fundamental ſecundarily, to alter which would be ful of danger and inconveniences, unleſs it were moſt evident, that great utility would thereby ariſe and accrue to the Kingdom: but that is not my preſent work, ſomething I intend concerning Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment in general rules by which no man can conceive himſelf preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diced: as by general rules of Phyſick, no wiſe man can expect to be cured.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the people girt the ſword about the King, the King ſays our Law books, is the fountain of honor, and it is true for the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples good, therefore doth the King make Judges and Magiſtrates great, that they may not be afraid to do right and juſtice to their brethren, ſo that indeed the ſtate confers honors by the King, as the King gives the Alms by his Almoner: they preſume that the King wil make no Lords but ſuch as ſhal be an honor to the Kingdom, in whom the Kingdom ſhal be preferred: the Judges Robes are for the Kingdoms good, to ſtrick a terror into offenders; if the Kingdom or the Parliament which is the ſtate contract, can juſtly except againſt thoſe which are honored, that is, if they by their greatneſs oppreſs the people, and Lord it over poor men, the honor ought not to continue, for all Priviledges and Preeminences are forfeited by abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers: no Priviledg which is a private <hi>Law</hi> muſt oppoſe Publique welfare: Indeed nothing done without the ſtates allowance is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowable, that is nothing againſt the fundamental good of the people;
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:114508:17"/> and truly the main end of Parliaments is, to ſuperviſe the Publique Magiſtrates, to ſee that Miniſters of juſtice be juſt and execute ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice impartially: If Kings did always prefer good men and conferr the great offices of truſt and judicial places upon the moſt idone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and beſt men in the Kingdom, which are <hi>Infra Cauſam meriti,</hi> that beſt deſerve them, there would be the leſs need of Parliaments; I mean officers of the Kingdom, for there are officers of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire for the Adminiſtration of Publique juſtice, and officers of the Emperors as his Domeſtical ſervants; anſwerable to our diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the Kings natural Capacity, and his politique Capacity, art is always the perfection and never the deſtruction of nature. Let me but humbly obſerve a little defectiveneſs in ſtate policy concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Kings Councel: That the Regal heires have not in their princely education, Tutors to inſtruct them in that which moſt concerns the good of the Kingdom, which is, Councellors to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint them in the fundamental laws of the land: how improper is it, that the <hi>Kings</hi> Counſel ſhould be leaſt of Counſel with his <hi>Majeſty:</hi> but by per-audience to gain other Clyents, and be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged in other mens buſineſs, when they ſhould be attending his <hi>Majeſty,</hi> ſtil preſenting the law before him, which is the golden rule of juſtice. <hi>Judg Forteſcue</hi> holds it neceſſary for the peopl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s happineſs, that the King ſee with his own eys, what is for his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples good, that ſo he may reward the moſt vertuous, the <hi>Fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nch King</hi> is enioyned to pray ſo much every day, to be exemplary to the people, how happy would it be if the nobles and Grandees of ſtate would ſtudy that fundamental and true end of Government, which is the w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lfare of the people! The young Prince of <hi>Perſia</hi> hath 4, Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors for Religion, as many for the <hi>Law,</hi> but 2, for Martial Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploits (for they ſaid for the King to know how to ride the Great horſe is but half as good for the Subiects, as to know the law by which he wears his Crown) and one Tutor for every moral vertue, patience, courteſy, temperance, chaſtity &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Not to argue whether we live under a Government mixt and co-ordinate, or ſimple and ſubordinate; 'tis a common Tenent that the Empire <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Spain</hi> are <hi>merum Emperium, England, Sweden, Denmark</hi> and <hi>Poland</hi> a mixt Empire, the <hi>Venetians</hi> a pure Ariſtocracy, <hi>Holland, Geneva,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Juriſdictio ſine Imperio:</hi> that, of the 6. Kings that be in Chriſtendom, <hi>Fran<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e</hi> and <hi>Spain</hi> have too much power, <hi>Sweden</hi> and <hi>Poland</hi> too little for their title, <hi>England</hi>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:114508:17"/> and <hi>Denmark</hi> juſt enough to make themſelves ſplendid and their people happy. All agree that the King cannot make a Law without a Parliament, and I cannot but exceedingly magnifie the mixture of the 3. eſtates; the <hi>ſuperlative truſt</hi> by Law is in the King, Lords and Commons; ('tis but loſs of time to look back into the power of the Biſhops, for 'tis not much above 100. years ſince there were <hi>Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes</hi> enforced for the Popes ſupreamacy) yet ſo as if the Lords and Commons perceive that the King by evil advice undermines the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects liberties to the manifeſt indangering of <hi>Salus,</hi> they muſt then neceſſarily ſuſpend the operation of that mixture; as when 3. men are to cary a weight, if one plucks back his ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, the other 2. muſt bear it: for the conſideration of publick utility is always equivalent to a neceſſity, <hi>Cauſae neceſſitatis &amp; util tatis aequiparantur in Jure:</hi> and therefore it is an <hi>error</hi> to ſay the people do not truſt the right honorable Lords becauſe they do not chooſe them: Their Nobility was acquired and is continued by noble actions; thoſe noble Peers that have not deſerted the Parliament, but continued faithful and adventured their lives and honors for the publick ſafety deſerve e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal praiſes, and in the multitude of ſuch Counſellors there is much ſafety to this Kingdom; for all true Honor conſiſts in vertuous en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowments and their improvements, the principal whereof is faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs to the Kingdom, expreſſing their honorable endeavors after that in works of <hi>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rcy, juſtice, peace</hi> and <hi>love.</hi> The King is ever preſent by his power; the Lords preſent in their perſons, and the Kingdom repreſented by their choyceſt members, who are impow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for themſelv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s and the whole Kingdom, ſo the whole Kingdom is figuratively preſent by a part taken for the whole (therefore the words <hi>Comm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſioners</hi> or <hi>Arbitrators,</hi> or <hi>Feoffees</hi> in truſt, of excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding their power and ſuch inſtances uſed by many, are in my opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion very improper); now the honorable Houſe of Commons being beſt acquainted with the Kingdoms Condition, all good laws do move primarily from them, which being tranſmitted to the Lords for their Lordſhips concurrence, it is no ſmal ſecurity to this Kingdom in peaceable times, to have the reaſons of the <hi>Law</hi> ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly debated &amp; perpended in the preſence of the reverend <hi>Iudges;</hi> for ever, amongſt Eagles eyes, two eyes may ſee more then one, and after their <hi>Lordſhips</hi> Concurrence, the Kings Majeſty deſires to be ſatisfied of the reaſon and equity of the <hi>Law</hi> before he gives his Royal Aſſent; by ſuch wiſe and great deliberations Counſels prove
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:114508:18"/> moſt mature and happy, as Corn that is long in ripening. I conceive that the noble Peers were originally intruſted by the people as Guardians of the Contract which the King made with them, and theſe noble <hi>Lords</hi> follow the King as the <hi>Planets</hi> the Sun in the <hi>Zodiack,</hi> from whom they receive their light and ſplendor for the publick good; and the prevarication of ſome which have given his Majeſty pernicious Counſel, as <hi>Eve</hi> tempted <hi>Adam</hi> (that had been ſufficient to have undone himſelf and his poſterity, but that the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>England</hi> lays the blame upon the evil Counſellors) makes the fidelity and gallantry of the reſt more glorious and illuſtrious: I would but humbly beg from that noble body, thoſe great lumina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of State, that as their <hi>Lordſhips</hi> and their noble Families are exempted from the <hi>Preſbyterian Di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cipline,</hi> ſo they would be nobly pleaſed to diſpenſe with ſuch who with any quiet of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence cannot conform thereunto; that no coactive violence may be offered to ſuch as be religious and peaceable in their differences, for that no rational doubt can be deſtructive of State-policy, as that noble Pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r ſaith,<note place="margin">Lo. <hi>Brooks.</hi>
               </note> who went to heaven in a fiery Charriot. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon my knees I would humbly beg of our moſt honorable Worthies 3. things:</p>
            <p n="1">1. An Ordinance for the Redemption of our poor brethren in <hi>Argiers</hi> and <hi>Tunis,</hi> which are Captives and Galley-ſlaves to the <hi>Turks:</hi> If money be wanting, oh, why is there not more general Collect<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ons for that bleſſed purpoſe, far better then to give to free-ſchools, and becauſe they are far of;</p>
            <p n="2">2. That in the <hi>interim</hi> the many poor ſlaves and hunger-bitten Priſoners, in and about this great City and other places of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, which are ready to ſtarve, and no more able to pay thoſe moneys which they lie in for, then to flie; and certainly to clap a man in priſon til he can flie or pluck down <hi>Pauls,</hi> would be a great blemiſh to the Government of this Nation: Reaſon commands no impoſſible things, and a good Ordinance to be made for the ſale of mens eſtates for the paym<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nt of their juſt Debts.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That ſome effectual courſ maybe thought upon to abate the price of Corn, ſpecially barley, that the poor might not ſtarve, which might eaſily be done by allowing fewer ale-houſes, and the ſtatutes for ſelling a quart of beer or ale for a peny, ſpeedily put in execution. What a ſad thing is it, that in a plentiful Kingdom many poor people ſhould be ready to ſtarve: oh, where are the bowels of Engliſh Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates?
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:114508:18"/> why ſhould rich men have ſuperfluities til poor men have neceſſaries? Let the King and great ones feaſt and the poor many times faſt, but let no man ſtarve; truly the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ery Eſſence of a Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament is freedom; a new Pope kept a Gawdy day to reioyce, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe all his ſins were forgiven, and that he was now free from the cenſure of all men: and being a Gentleman, ask't a Cardinal, what ſhal I do now to ſhew my love to the <hi>Romans?</hi> ſaid he, pray Sr. forgive us all our ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, and make us as free as your Holines. The Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor ſhal be the Parliaments, the happineſs, the peoples. And here I would humbly pray thoſe excellent Juſticiaries to receive all com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints, Petitions, and Informations from whomſoever they come: I have thought ſometimes attending ſome clients buſineſs, and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring poor ſuitors complain of their long attendances, but if a man had ſome Information to give of a new <hi>Spaniſh-Fleet,</hi> or ſome dangerous <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nvaſion to be made againſt this Kingdom, he could ſcarcely be heard: in <hi>Holland</hi> when the general ſtates are in Councel at the Hague, there are always ſome appointed to come forth to receive any information that can be given for the Publique good, and if any man ſays he hath buſineſs of Importance to Communicate, he go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s into the Counſel houſe: if it be frivolous he is wel laughed at for his pains, and it may be fined: but to what purpoſe ſhould there be a freedom of debate in a Counſel<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> if there be not freedom of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation to the Counſel?</p>
            <p>In the laſt great froſt the River near <hi>Anwerp</hi> (that beautiful town in <hi>Flanders,</hi> which <hi>Charl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s</hi> the 5. ſaid, was fit to be ſeen only up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Holidays) was all frozen over as the Thames was: and about 2. a clock in a fair Sunſhine afternoon, there being at the leaſt 1000. people upon the River, the Councel being ſate, there comes an old fiſherman running and ſweating to the Common-Counc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l door, and ſaid, he muſt be admitted inſtantly about extraordinary buſineſs, who went in and told the Councel, that if they did not uſe ſome po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licie to get the p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ople of from the River, they would inſtantly be drowned: for he perceived by the clouds, or ſome skil that he had, that the Thaw would be ſo ſuddain, that the ice would break within a quarter of an hour. The Councel without any further diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute (for the matter had not been great if he had been miſtaken) Commanded inſtantly the bells to be rung backwards, and the drums to be beat up, which the people upon the River hearing, thought it was a fire in the City, or that the enemy was approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:114508:19"/> or ſome other extraordinary matter, made all poſſible ſpeed From the river; yet not ſo faſt but that there were at the leaſt 50 drowned, for it grew dark of a ſudden; there was a great ſhower the Ice broke, and the Thaw ſo unexpected that in probability had not this poor mans information been received, the moſt of them had loſt their lives. How hard a thing is it for Clients and Counſel too to get into many places of Juſtice? The Door-keepers are ſo haſty and angry if a man do but ask them any queſtion in the moſt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſive language, and many of the Clerks ſo teaſty and briniſh, as if they were compoſed of that pillar of ſalt that <hi>Lots</hi> wife was turned into, and ſo unaccoſtable that I profeſs a man may far eaſier have ſucceſs to a noble Lord, or a worthy Member then to them: 'tis a ſhame to ſee how they make poor Clients dance attendance after their pipes; I profeſs if they do not reform their curriſhneſs they ſhal be known to all the Kingdom for their inhumanity; I confeſs the ingenuity, and readineſs to give content with all civility, of thoſe which attend the right honorable the Lords and Commons, and ſome others, is much to be commended: O but how difficult a matter is it to get a motion in ſome places of Juſtice? if a man could be diſpatcht after four or five attendances it were brave, and that which is moſt lamentable, 'tis all one if a mans Client be a priſoner: whereas a politick Judg would ask at his firſt ſitting, Is there any motions concerning life or liberty or dower for Widows or Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phans, and diſpatch poor men firſt; &amp; them that can ſpare moſt Fees let them tarry; I know one that hath been aſſigned Councel for 26. <hi>Paupers</hi> &amp; could never be heard or above four or five of them; <hi>'tis a po nt of great <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ngenuity in Lawyers to m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ve firſt for hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> poor C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nt without his Fee; I have heard many of my lea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ned Maſters that they would freely move for any poor man as often as, he ſhould deſire, if it m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ght not hinder them f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r their other Clients; 'tis a gallant ſpirit trul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, though it be t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> commend our ſelves, yet 'tis a truth, and a man may commend him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to be co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>manded and imployed as <hi>David</hi> did; but ſome are l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ke Rocks and wil not be moved. What do you to me with your <hi>Paupers</hi> at the latter end of the day? When God knows he came two or three hours before the Cou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t was ſate. What! do you think all to be heard? As if we came n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t to be h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a d bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to hear others.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3. That free people in their right wits never covenanted againſt the Law of God o Nature, nor meant to inſlave themſelves to the luſts of one or more whom they elected or conſented to be their Governors; for the end of Govern<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ent is the welfare, peace, liberty, ſafety, propriety, and all kind of ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pineſs of the people; were it n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t for which there would be no end of Governors nor Laws, nor can a Kingd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m be bound to any condition deſtructive to any of her own Members. Law is but the rule, ſafety is the and of Government; now the end as it is firſt in intention, ſo it is always
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:114508:19"/> more noble then the means, for the means, as means, is always inferour to the end, as he for whole ſake a garment is made, is more honorable then the rayment; ſo health an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſtrength are the chief principal ends of dyet, food and phyſick being the means, therefore are inferior, ſo are all Governors ſubſervient to the peoples welfare, as it is declared in that moſt excellent Declaration of the 17. of <hi>May,</hi> 1646. wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch deſerves to be ingraven in marble Pillars, that the welfare of the people, is the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prem Law; <hi>ſalus pop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>li,</hi> is the end of all ends, for whoſe ſake all poſitive Laws may be ended, and muſt expire like dead men; for the Law is but Lord of particular perſons, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>munity is Lord over it, nay, the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e is no Law of G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d that ſtands in competition againſt the ſafety of the people; ſacr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> muſt do homage to mercy, the morality of the Subjects muſt be ſuſpended to ſave the life of a ſheep, how much more for the welfare of the ſhep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erd; if it be lawful to br<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>k the 4. C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mmandment, in the Lett<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r of it, to ſave a mans life; how much m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re lawful is it to diſpence with the fifth Commandment to ſave the lives of mil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ons? all muſt ſtay and Lady <hi>Salus</hi> muſt firſt be ſecured<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the Letter of the Law muſt not be killing to the people a whole Kingdom can no more be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ject to a dead letter then the <hi>Romans</hi> to their own ſlaves; and as the <hi>Romans</hi> being a people full of generoſity and courteſie never more expreſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>heir gentle diſpoſition then by eaſie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcending to let their bond men at liberty; ſo our Worthies in <hi>Parliament</hi> can never do a work more glorious then to infranchiſe this Kingdom in their ſouls, bodies and eſtates; for which they ſhal deſerve immortal praiſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <hi>Q</hi> But hath not the Parliament an unlimited power and Authority?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <hi>Reſp.</hi> What agreement was between the Counties and the Knights of the Shire, and the Corporations and Burgeſſes when Parliaments were firſt called, no man can direct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y ſay; for my own part I do beleeve that there was ſome fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mal agreement reduced into writings, what power the Kings and Burgeſſes ſhould have, and ſpecified in the Indentures of return made betwe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n the Sheriff and Electors, and the Knights and Bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſes; which truſt the Parliam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt men from t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>me to time, faithfully diſcharging and Contribu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing to all Taxes and Charges out of their o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n eſtates; the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple at laſt were conten<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ve all matters indefinitely to their Knights, and Bu geſſes, and in many Burrough towns, there was ſcarce a man that could write in thoſe days; but the matter is not great, for th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t which li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits all Kings and Councels is the end of Government, which is the proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ty of the people; and all agreem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nts are preſumed to be made for the welfare of the people; No unnatural thing can be preſumed, Autho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ity is a challenge of obedience, legally by ſuch as are impowred by any peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple Power (to ſpeak properly) is an ability to put that Authority in exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution; now all power in the people; which they wel knowing, were not ſo careful as they might have been, to ſet limits and boundaries to Au<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hority, becau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e the ſtrength remaining in themſelves, they could never imagine that any Governors would Command them to deſtroy them<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>elves, and therefore theſe Arguments about ſeizing upon the <hi>Mil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a,</hi> and forts of the Kingdom are weak and invalid; if the meaning be any other ways th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n this, that it is Rebellion for any or many private men to reſiſt the King, and contemptuouſly to oppoſe the ſupream Court of the Kingdom, becauſe they are leſs then his Majeſty,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:114508:20"/> but that both Houſes of Parliament can commit Treaſon, acting for the good and by the power of the Kingdom, is to argue that a man may com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit Treaſon againſt himſelf, and that a man is bound with his right hand to cut off his left hand; things which nature abhors.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> But what if a free people ſhould make a general Letter of Attorney to ſome Governors to make what Laws they pleaſe againſt nature and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity? May not a man tye himſelf to a poſt as the old Uſurer that would bind the young heir to a Table?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <hi>Reſp.</hi> I anſwer, the authority is voyd and revocable, for no power can be given that is deſtructive of humanity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> But what if the Governors wil not let it go, but act accordinly? for Domination is a ſweet morſel, not eaſie to be parted with.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <hi>R.</hi> I anſwer, that in ſuch a caſe the pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ple are bound by the Law of God and Nature, by force to redeem their liberties, they which be impowred muſt be overpowred, for free men can give away their freedom no further then as it conduceth to juſtice univerſal and paticular. <hi>Pha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aohs</hi> Law to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy all the <hi>Iſraelitiſh</hi> males, or <hi>Herods</hi> cruelty, or <hi>Lycurgus</hi> Law to kill all weak or old people, or a Law to eat but twice a week, doth any man que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, but theſe may be reſiſted?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> But is not this contrary to <hi>Rom.</hi> 13?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>R. Truly 't<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s very obſervable that that Chapter ſhould be ſent to that people which are the only oppoſers of Civil Magiſtrates, but the mean<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>g is that none may reſiſt Gods Ordinance; a people may reſiſt all but the O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dinance; now no Tyranny is Gods Ordinance, there is no ſuch autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; if I be bound not to reſiſt authority, 'tis a good plea to ſay there is no ſuch authority; therefore all Tyranny is reſiſtable, and that is but to reſiſt the violation of the Ordinance; if a King would kill any man againſt Law, there is no queſtion but he may reſiſt to ſave his life, for ſelf-preſervation is by the Law of Nature; for when I can have no Juſtice, the Law makes me a Judg in my own caſe, as if a thief ſet upon me to rob me, I may kill him becauſe there is no juſtice neer to help me; ſo if the higheſt Court in any Kingdom would kil the Kingdom, they may kil and diſſolve that Court becauſe otherwiſe they can have no juſtice upon it; for no man can give away the right of defending his life until he hath forfeited it. I aſſure you if Kings and Governors be caſt at the Bar of Reaſon, the Scripture wil never relieve them; for God and Reaſon never differ but in <hi>metaphyſicks;</hi> Did ever God impower any man to do injuſtice, or to erect a Court to inſlave their brethren? Shal not the Judg of all the earth do right? God f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rbid, the end of Governors is juſtice, ſafety and protection, which muſt not be loſt to preſerve forms or private priviledges, which muſt never ſtand in competition with <hi>Salus. Subſtances</hi> muſt not be loſt for formalities, Juſtice muſt be done, God commands it, if the Commanders wil not do it the people muſt, have a care of the main is a good Proverb; the main of all is to prefer the main; I ſpeak all this while when Governors act apparently againſt their Commſſiions and the ſafety of the people; he is a Tyrant whom all the people ſhal call ſo; and that ſupream Court is Tyrannical, of whom all the people ſhal ſay ſo, which is hard to imagine of any general convention; for it is not poſſible to vaſſalize the people but themſelves muſt likewiſe be inſlaved.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:114508:20"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> But if in ſuch caſes blood be ſhed, who ſhall be ſaid to be guilty of it?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſp.</hi> The neglective Magiſtrate is guilty of all following ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orbitances and extravagancies; he breaks the peace that conſtrains me to break it for my own preſervation; nothing is more law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe then that Law that would endanger the Publique welfare; not the Actor but the En<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orcer rebels againſt right reaſon, and ought to ſuffer for double enforcing and accuſing.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> But which is better of an Anarchy or a Tyranny?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſp.</hi> I have read much for ſatisfaction in that particular, and truly I conceive it farre better to have no Government at all then a Tyrannicall one, as being better to have no Governours then to miſſe of the end of Government, which is the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples good; I agree it better to have continuall ſore eyes then to be ſtark blind, and that is no good cure for the tooth-ach to pluck out all the teeth; but the principals of common Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice and honeſty are ſtill remaining in every man, though much defaced, yet not quite obliterated: and that which is ſufficient to condemn the Gentiles, would be a better light to the people then to give abſolute obedience to the will of a Tyrant; for what difference is there between being gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the Devill, and a man that is poſſeſſed with the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill? if there were no Governours in a Kingdome, but every one ſtood upon his guard, if a man were foiled at one time he might get the better at another, if to day he were grieved, to morrow he may be relieved, and no man durſt kill for fear of being killed; for who is ſo ſtrong but may meet with his match? therefore leſſe miſchiefe certainly to have it ſo then a perpetuall ſlavery.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> But it will be objected that Magiſtrates are but in a dangerous condition, if the people upon every diſcontent ſhall be mutinous and quarellous, and upon a ſuppoſition of injuſtice done, preſently take armes to deſtroy Governours and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſp.</hi> Indeed this is diligently to be pondered, and this I take clearly to be the minde of God, that in Kingdomes and States well ſetled, many Acts of Injuſtice are to be ſuffered without reſiſtance, and to bee paſt by inſenſibly: In a great building a ſtone that is ill placed muſt not be removed; certainly
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:114508:21"/> when God commanded obedience to Kings, he conſidered that they were paſſionate men, with like affections, and would have Favourites, as others.</p>
            <p>As ſufferance is counted by the Papiſts the higheſt point of merit; ſo certainly ſufferance is the greateſt wiſdome to prevent a greater ſufferance in matters which are ſufferable; and I could be content to looſe any thing, but my Conſcie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ce and Liberty, and ſpecially for Chriſtians to ſuffer in matters of common Iuſtice, and the things of this world; truly, I ſhould highly commend it, becauſe their Kingdome is not of this world, the loſſe of a Chriſtians outward eſtate is not the loſſe of his inward comforts; nor is every cruell Government Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannicall, it is much better to ſuffer much under the gracious influence of <hi>Iupiter</hi> and <hi>Venus,</hi> then to live as Vulturs and Cormorants under malignant <hi>Saturn</hi> and <hi>Mars,</hi> like <hi>Canni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bals</hi> feeding upon one anothers bloud: If I knew that my Father would come into my chamber and beat me for nothing, I would not reſiſt him, but if I were perſwaded that he were reſolved to kill me, then I ſhould defend my ſelfe, and if it ſhould come to that ſad ſtrait, that I muſt be killed or kill, though poſſibly my affection might chuſe rather to loſe my own life, then to be the death of him that gave it me; yet my judgement would prompt that it is ſel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e murder in me to betray my own life when I may preſerve it, and though I ſhould eſteem my ſelfe moſt unhappy, and rather wiſh that hand that did it had been cut off; yet not diſpaire, becauſe it was againſt my in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention and my will: If I were asked, who was the moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feigned lover of his Countrey, and the Kingdoms beſt friend? I ſhould anſwer in two things, He that is moſt forward to go wayes which are dangerous to himſelfe, and ſafe to his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, whereby I exclude Neuters that will be ſure to ſleep in a whole skin: 'tis not the Innocent Sheeps skin, but the Foxes skins; (when the King of <hi>Sweden</hi> approached <hi>Frankford,</hi> the Citizens ſent to him, that they might be Neutrall till their Faire was paſt, what ſayes he, Are your Faires dearer to you then your Conſciences?) by <hi>Solons</hi> Law Neuters were to be hanged.</p>
            <p n="2">2. He that is content to ſuffer, when his private ſufferings may conduce to the Publike good; for every Engliſh man is a
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:114508:21"/> member of the body Politick, and what is good for the whole, he muſt conclude to be good for him; 'tis true, thoſe that will not execute juſtice, deſerve to be executed themſelves; but conſider whether ſufferance or reſiſtance conduce moſt to the common good; There are ſome Scriptures which ſeem I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, to be contradictory, We reade in the Book of <hi>Ioſhua</hi> and <hi>Iudges,</hi> how a ſuſpition of Idolatry cauſes <hi>Iſrael</hi> to aſſemble to warres againſt <hi>Reuben,</hi> and <hi>Mana<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſeth,</hi> and againſt <hi>Benjamin,</hi> for the Levites Concub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nes, all riſing as one man, ſaying, Deliver us the children of Beliall; and <hi>Jonah</hi> was caſt out of the ſhip, that would have been the wrack of them all; <hi>David</hi> took up armes againſt <hi>Saul</hi> in his own Kingdome, his King, his Maſter, as in his houſe and of his Table and Family, fled to <hi>Sauls</hi> Enemy to <hi>Akiſh,</hi> and offered to ſecond him againſt <hi>Saul,</hi> fortifyed <hi>Ketlah</hi> one of his Towns againſt him; and if <hi>Saul</hi> had ſtopt the Cave to have pined him, doubtleſſe he wou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d have uſed means to get out; and yet God was his Counſellor by diſcovering the Princes of <hi>Keilah</hi> their intentions; and the people cryed all with one voyce, <hi>Jonathan</hi> ſhall not die for the good he hath done to our Countrey: and the Scripture ſpeaks plainly, that tribute is to be paid ſo farre as the ſubjects may pay tribute to God, for this cauſe pay we tribute; I give ſuch reverence to the holy Scriptures, that when I finde a preſident, for which I doe not underſtand the reaſon, I conceive there was a reaſon for it in thoſe times, which is now abſolete; things were done by ſpeciall inſpi ation, which are not exemplary to us, nor may we judge where the Scripture is ſilent whether it was well or ill done; but I am clearly of opinion, that in a Kingdome well compoſed, if one man or 100 men ſhould ſuffer in the Kingdome, that the ſubjects ought not to take up armes ſuddenly to right themſelves, but expect with patience till the Authors and procurors of injuſtice be brought to condign pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment; for when an evill in State Policy cannot be removed without the manifeſt danger of a greater to ſucceed, wiſedome muſt give place to neceſſity, (which all Kingdomes muſt make uſe of ordinarily) and people muſt ſtuddy when the beſt man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Government is not poſſible without great danger to be obtained, to make the beſt of the pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ent; when the beſt things are not poſſible, to make the beſt o thoſe that are; as we ſay,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:114508:22"/> to make the beſt of an ill game, and not to throw it up, and ſay they will play no more, 'tis not the part of a faire Gamſter ſo to doe; when all things are quiet in a Kingdome, then conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der how that which muſt be endured may be mitigated, and the inconveniences countervailed; but if the State collective in the whole body of it, or the State contract in a Parliament or Senate, ſhall upon good grounds conceive that the point of that ſword, which they put into the hands of their Governours to protect them, is by evill adviſe turned againſt themſelves, in this caſe clearly the ſword muſt be wreſted out of the Truſtees hands; if the Maſter and the Mate be drunk, all the Paſſengers muſt ſave themſelves; if the Dogs will not bark, the Geeſe will cry when the <hi>Gaules</hi> are ſcaling the Capitoll: for no in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>convenience can be greater; and this was the Parliaments caſe for raiſing Forces; they wiſely conſidered before they Voted any Army, that in that condition the Kingdome ſtood, the remedy could not poſſibly be worſe then the diſeaſe, for the diſeaſe was the utter ſubverſion of Lawes and Liberties, and the deſtruction of the Proteſtant Religion, at leaſt in the power of it; for truly to ſpeak my thoughts freely, I doe not think that the difference between the late <hi>Oxford</hi> Party and the <hi>Parliament,</hi> was whether we ſhould be Proteſtants or Papiſts, but whether we ſhould be formall Proteſtants at large or Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors in the power of Religion: and God grant that this may no longer be the Controverſy in this Nation.</p>
            <p>But becauſe tediouſneſſe and delay has ever been an enemy to this Kingdome, I ſhall ſay no more in a ſubject that has been ſo much controverted concerning the late unhappy differences, but ſhall apply my ſelfe to the preſent juncture, and firſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Army.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 3.15.</note>BLeſſed <hi>Peter</hi> bids Chriſtians to be ready to make an Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy for their faith; but truly there needs no Apology for the Army, unleſſe it be for their too much patience, in ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Kingdome and themſelves to be ſo long abuſed by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome Incendaries of State, who care not to ſet all on fire to warm themſelves; For had they come to the Houſes the next day after they were declared Enemies, and demanded Iuſtice againſt the cheife Promoters and Contrivers thereof, it had
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:114508:22"/> been moſt juſt, by the Lawes of God and man; and I am confident, that there was never any former Army in the world, but would have done it. That ſuch Gallant men which have kept ſome of the cheife Contrivers heads upon their ſhoulders, for an humble Petition preſented to their Noble Generall, (which all Souldiers by the Law of Armes may doe,) ſhould be voted enemies and diſturbers for that which ſince hath been acknowledged to be but juſt, was the moſt monſtrous ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude that ever was heard of under the Sun ſince the firſt moment of its Creation; and ſure they durſt not ſo juſtly have provoked them but that they knew they were acted by more noble principalls, that though they had the ſword in their hand, yet they durſt not offend God, Religion being to them the ſtrongeſt bridle. But whom God will deſtroy for their great Provocations, he firſt dementates; they have rejected the Counſell of God, and what wiſedome is there in them? Policy is a branch of wiſedome, and all wiſedome is from God: but this I muſt premiſe, that that Declaration was not in judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Law any Act of the Honourable Houſe; for the moſt Honourable Houſes being the Protectors of our Lawes, the Preſerve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, Surveyers, and Defenders of all our lawfull Liberties, and the Haven and Refuge of all that are oppreſſed, it cannot poſſibly bee imagined that they in their great wiſedomes ſhould (unleſſe misinfo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>med) vote them enemies to the State, and diſturbers of the Peace thereof, which with the adventure of their lives have ſaved the Kingdome, and preſerved the Peace thereof. I ſay, under favour, we can no more imagine it, then wee can the Sea to be poyſoned; but it was in Law a Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of their malevolent intentions, who exceedingly miſ-in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed and ſeduced, and did what in them lay to poyſon the very fountain of Iuſtice who ſuddenly contrived it in an illegall way againſt expreſſe order, at an unparliamentary hour, and ſo a meer nullity, rather a Nocturnall ſurpriſe then a ſolemn act of Conſultation: Livery and Seiſin made in the night is void; if a man be rob'd in the night, there is no reliefe for him, it being no time for travell; no diſtreſſe can be taken for rent in the night time, but a diſtreſſe for dammage Feaſant may, for the neceſſity that elſe the beaſts will be gone; and ſo by a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall conſent our Noble Senators have broken their ſleepes, and
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:114508:23"/> ſate upon the Lords day in caſes of great importance; but was there any ſuch pregnant neceſſity to vote that night againſt the Army? I know that the ſupreame Court can never ty it ſelfe to any times or houres; yet if forty Members ſhall goe into the Houſe at twelve at night, when it was adjourned till the next day, and vote any thing to the indangering of the Kingdome in a ſecond and more bloudy warre, is not this a pure nullity? but I ſhall ſay no more concerning that which hath been ſower hearbes to Gods people, that the walls and bulwarks of the Kingdome ſhould be lookt upon by any as thornes and bryars: becau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e I conſider that things extinguiſht may not by Law be revived, but this I am confident that our Noble Worthies and the Army are very great gainers by it; certainly no vote this Parliament has more endeared the Honourable Houſes to all ingenuous men then the revocation and expunging of it; For though it be eaſie for the higheſt earthly Tribunall to be miſtaken by miſ-information, it is the rareſt thing in the world not to juſtify an errour. Every Court is more ſtiffe to maintaine what they have done, then carefull to do nothing but what in right reaſon may be maintained; the magnitude of negotiations and multiplicity of votes, many times like apples may hinder the maturity of one amongſt 10000. which is not the leaſt diſhonour to the great tree of life in our Engliſh Paradice the Parliament, whereupon growes and which is as the very tree of life of all our temporall liberties. Who but a <hi>David,</hi> a <hi>Iob,</hi> a <hi>Peter,</hi> or a <hi>Paul,</hi> will teſtify ſuch a ſweete Spirit of Chriſtian Ingenuity? And St. <hi>Austin</hi> got himſelfe more love and honour by his book of recantations then all his other works beſides, and the Army undoubtedly ha's acquired much honour by that Noble retractation and obliteration, being an actuall and effectuall juſtification, and loſt none by the publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of it, for no duſt can ſtick upon pure marble: yet let not the cheife promoters of it pretend innocency, nothing but repen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ance can be their vindication; Indeed our Saviour ſaies that they ſhall think to do God good ſervice by killing his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, this is their caſe who are the reall diſturbers and troublers o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the peace of this Kingdome; they thought to promerrit by Sacrificeing the Children in the ſight of the Father; There was a great King that was reſolved to pardon all the Treaſons, and
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:114508:23"/> Rebellions committed againſt him, till at laſt he eſpies the blood of his ſon ſprinkled upon the Traytors garments, and then no further condonation; The Lord will beare with tyrants and oppreſſors long, as in <hi>Turkey, Ruſſia &amp;c.</hi> againſt that rule <hi>Nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum violentum eſt perpetuum,</hi> becauſe the times of their Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance God regardeth not, and they meddle not with the apple of his eyes which is conſcience: but that pretenders or profeſſors of Religion, which had ſcarce time to bleſſe God for their own deliverance from Arbitrary power, and the Biſhops domination, ſhould preſently become oppreſſors themſelves and perſecutors of their Brethren; as it is to me one of the greateſt miracles in the world, ſo it clearly prognoſticates their ruine, for pride is the Harbinger of deſtruction, as Thundering and Lightning are not far aſunder, and ingratitude is ſeldome puniſht in another world, What an high eſteeme and good opinion had this Army of the Parliament and City? what abundance of love did they expreſſe to them? deare ſouls! what needed they to have adventured their lives ſo freely more then o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>her men? their ingagement was not mercinary as Auxiliaries in <hi>France</hi> or <hi>Spaine,</hi> who look not at the juſtice of the cauſe, but the beſt ſalary, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long the warre as coveteous Surgeons keep the wound raw for their own advantage, and ſo drink the blood of poore in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocents; but it was an honorary ſervice as lovers of their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try that were reſolved <hi>mori pro Patria,</hi> rather to dy an Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable death then to live a ſervile life, and therefore did not make a truce when they had taken one Garriſon, and give the Enemy time to reinforce, like day labourers that care not how long the harveſt continues, but as if they had contracted by the great to ſave the Kingdome for ſo much; ſurmounted all difficulties, run upon the mouthes of the Thundering Canons (which were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented to deterre men from going to warr) as if they had been ſpirits and not bodyes tangeable, or as if they had coveted no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more then active Martyrdome, and what wonders were wrought by them in the revolution of one yeare requires a better memory and an exacter pen then mine to record, that the generations to come may call them bleſſed; for by this Army the Lord of Hoſts hath reſcued and redeemed the liberties and properties of this Nation, out of the jawes of all oppreſſors; to the end I truſt that being ſo delivered, we
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:114508:24"/> may ſerve him without feare in holineſſe and righteouſneſſe all the dayes of our lives; ſo that I may truly ſay, that this Army (whom the Lord maugre all oppoſition will make glorious In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments of his prayſe) hath been the breath of many of their noſtrils both in Parliament, Aſſembly, and City; they had not long breathed but had been ſtrangled or loſt their heads, had not the Army ſtood in the gap for them, and yet by theſe mens good or rather wicked wills, the Army ſhould not have liberty to breathe in the Land of their Nativity; was there ever ſuch a maſſe of inhumanity and ingratitute heard of? What a blemiſh lies upon the State of <hi>Rome</hi> to this day, for their unthankfulneſſe in the caſe of one <hi>Scipio,</hi> and upon the <hi>Lacedemonians,</hi> for not erecting Monuments of honour for <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cibiad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s,</hi> and <hi>Socrates?</hi> Has not <hi>England</hi> ſins enough to anſwer for, but it muſt be guilty of ingratitude? How would not only <hi>Romans</hi> but <hi>Pagans</hi> have erected Statues for the perpetuall Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the Noble Generall, Lieutenant Generall, and the reſt of thoſe Joſhua's and Worthies which have been as the ſecond ſaviours of this Kingdome? and that which Crowns all, is their ſelf-denyall and humility; willingly do they talk of their errours, but what is well done the Lord hath done it, and it would have beene better but for them; as the Maſter that guides the Schollars hand to make a letter, the ſtraightneſſe is from the Maſter, the obliquity from the Schollar, without whom it had b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>en better; yet they, and the people of God in this Kingdome, cannot but rejoyce, that the Lord made uſe of their hands, in this great work of Reformation; But that I may not only ſhew my own affection to the Army, and take the Readers affection, but convince his judgement and informe the underſtanding in point of rationall ſatisfaction, I ſhall endeavour, I hope not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſucceſſe, to make it very cleare, that the proceedings of the Army in not ſuffering themſelves to be disbanded till the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and the Liberties of the King, and people, be ſetled and vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated; Is clearly juſtifiable by ſuch demonſtrative Arguments, that the impartiall Reader cannot but in his judgment inwardly aſſent thereunto. It cannot be denyed, but that this Army was rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to defend the juſt Liberties of the Subject from all Tyranni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l U<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>urpation, Arbytrary exorbitances and Irregularities, and all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ppreſſive wayes of Government, to which end they have bin
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:114508:24"/> honeſt, faithfull, and true, as the Turtle to his Mate; for if all the malice in the world were infuſed into one eye, it could not diſcern the leaſt ſpot of injuſtice, or violation of truſt in this Army, for he that is true to his end, can never be ſaid to break a truſt; let but every man conſider whoſe actions have been moſt ſuteable, and agreeable to the ſolemn League and Covenant, whether the Armies or theirs that oppoſe them; and then tell me whether it be better to take the Covenant and to break it, or not take it, and yet to obſerve it; whether is better to endeavour the extirpation and weeding out of the precious corn under the notion of tares and weeds, or to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour by all juſt means to hinder and prevent the ſlavery of this Kingdome under the notion of Order and Uniformity. Read but the Preface to the Covenant, which is as it were the key to open the minde of the makers [that having in our eyes the advancement of the Kingdome of Jeſus Chriſt] ſure that can be no other then to ſet up Chriſt in his Kingly Office as Head of his Church, for temporall Kingdome he hath none; and if man muſt raign over the Conſcience, where muſt Jeſus Chriſt raigne? and calling to minde the practices againſt the Profeſſors of the true Religion, what were thoſe practiſes, but to impriſon and perſecute the beſt Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans for their Conſciences? and the power of the Hierarchy was principally erected in the Conſciences of men, therefore all Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neering over mens Conſciences is to be rooted out, and certainly the greateſt errour and hereſy in this Kingdome is to aſſume a power over the Conſciences of Gods people; and an unfained endeavour to amend our lives, there's a perſonall reformation; and to go one before another in the example of a reall Reformation, that muſt be intended a publike Reformation; not to wait upon Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity whether we ſhall ſerve God or no; but the Cobler to go before the Doctor, the Sculler to out-row the greateſt Schollar if he can, and not to hamſtring them that would go foremoſt in the power of godlineſſe, for a mans generall calling of being a Chriſtian does not depend upon the Magiſtrate. But why ſhould not ſuch a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcipline be ſetled univerſally as the greateſt number of wiſe and Learned men ſhall agree upon? The anſwer is eaſie, becauſe in very many Counſels Jeſus Chriſt hath been out-voted by Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, and the Aſſembly doe not ſay that they are priviledged with the priviledge of Infallibility: let the rigid <hi>Presbyterians</hi> in the Aſſembly but anſwer me this Queſtion, whether two parts at the leaſt in three of all the Miniſters in this Kingdome, be not for a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derated
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:114508:25"/> Epiſcopacy, and the Common-Prayer-Book? if ever it come to a Nationall Aſſembly, differences muſt be ended by the major vote; that which they anſwer, that few or none will be cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen, but of the Presbyterian judgement, I cannot believe it, for 'tis a violent preſumption that men will nominate thoſe of their own opinions; if it bee replyed, that we ſee in many places where the Electors have not been very religious, they have choſen the moſt religious Profeſſors for the Parliament, that was not for the love of their Religion, but they knew they were the beſt Common-Wealths men that ſtood for the peoples Liberty; nor would that ſerve the turn if it were ſo, for the elected ought in Conſcience to vote according to the generall meaning and judgement of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectors; wee ſee in the Noble Ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe of Peeres, a Lord that has a <hi>Proxy</hi> may vote for himſelf in the Affirmative, and for the abſent Lord in the Negative, if he ſend to his Lordſhip ſo to doe: if four or more Miniſters were choſen by all the Miniſters of a County, and ſent to a Nationall Aſſembly, theſe men ought not to vote any thing againſt that which they know to be the generall intent, meaning, and deſire of thoſe that ſent them; but whether the generall comportment of the Army in all matters univerſally, and their late Actions, Remonſtrances, and Declarations, be not more purſuant and proſecuting to the true meaning of the Covenant, the firme ſetlement of this diſtracted Kingdome in a ſubſtantiall and compleat manner, then any thing that has been publiſhed by the contrary-minded, let all the world judge. But when will hereſie ceaſe if there ſhould be ſuch an indulgence as you deſire? This queſtion is anſwered by <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ccalino,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ragvagli di Parn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſo.</note> and tis worthy the read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; All the great ones came to the Oracle of <hi>Apollo</hi> to enquire concerning themſelves, at laſt came the Biſhops exclaiming won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully againſt errors and hereſies, that the Romane Catholike A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolike Church was quite deſtroyed by them, and the Ieſuites la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented the want of love and charity, and ſaid all was for want of order and uniformity; the Biſhops deſiring to know when their errors and hereſies would ceaſe, and the Ieſuites deſiring to know when there would be love and charity; great expectance there was to know the Anſwers, at laſt the Oracle ſaid that errors and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies would inſtantly ceaſe if the Biſhops and their Succeſſors were aboliſhed; and that love and charity would abound when the Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuites and their Accomplices were extirpated: Obſerve two things, firſt, that perſecution for Conſcience ſake is the only brand of
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:114508:25"/> the Antichriſtian Church; ſecondly, that thoſe that complaine ſo much of errours, are the greateſt occaſioners of them; and he that bids look to your purſe, is the moſt dangerous fellow in the crowd. I am ſure, if Gods glory were aimed at, no difference of opinion amongſt Proteſtants could poſſibly break the bond of love; may we meet in Heaven together to praiſe God eternally, and ſhall not we live lovingly together under one King? Is there any man in <hi>London</hi> but ſayes he hopes to be ſaved by faith in Ieſus Chriſt? or if not, ſhall we ſend him to Hell unleſſe he diſturb the publick peace? (which no man muſt doe, for a Kingdome muſt preſerve it ſelfe,) as that precious King <hi>E.</hi> 6. ſaid, when the Biſhops would have had him burnt a Heretick; whither will his ſoul goe ſayes that young, truly young S. <hi>Edward;</hi> to Hell ſaid thoſe bloody Biſhops; but he ſhal not if I can help it, ſayes he; do you endeavour to convince him; however, I will not ſend him thither before his time; tis preſumed Theeves &amp; Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therers repent, he does not: Thoſe are bloudy butchers, ſons of that ſcarlet Whore, that would have many men (as free from errors per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adventure as themſelves) in their dayes burnt for Hereticks upon the Stat. of 5. <hi>H</hi> 4. made againſt Proteſtants. Was not that <hi>H.</hi> 4. a Uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per? Who was it that murthered, <hi>R.</hi> 2? Who but purpurated Perſecutors and bloudy wolves will deliver poore Chriſtians to death or to cruell jaylors, which is all one; for there is no <hi>magis</hi> and <hi>minus</hi> in perſecution. Matters of wrong and offence are puniſhable, but not matters of Conſcience, unleſſe they bee proditorious poſitions. If Proteſtants had been guilty of a Powder Plot in <hi>France,</hi> I believe they would never have been tolerated longer: hath not <hi>England</hi> paid deare enough for innocent bloud? God hath been reckoning with Us for the bloud of <hi>Barrow, Green<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood, Tiſdale, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>dall, Cappinger,</hi> and <hi>Oyers:</hi> doe but reade that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Treatiſe of that Worthy Author Sir <hi>Simon Dewes</hi> concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning this Subject, which is ſufficient in reaſon to end the great controverſie of the Kingdome, and to caſt water upon, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſh all the flames of our preſent differences in matter of errour.</p>
            <p n="2">2. There is no other expedient left to ſettle the ſubjects liberties, but by the continuance of this Army, for he that knowes any thing of the temperature and conſtitution of our Governours and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment muſt acknowledge that in probability, a Reformation in Courts of Iuſtice, and a meet liberty for tender Conſciences, two things of the higheſt concernment, cannot without the interven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and aſſiſtance of this Army be expected, for who will conſent
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:114508:26"/> to prejudice himſelfe, or derogate from his own profit for the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique good: put caſe the Biſhops were ſitting in the Houſe of Lords and the greater part, what hopes were there to paſſe an Act for the aboliſhing of Epiſcopacy? Let all Hiſtories be inſpected and it will clearely appeare that the heart of oppreſſion in any Kingdome or State, was never broken but by the mediation of ſome ſtrength, and therefore we ſhould love thoſe truths which coſt ſo deare: and this not only in matters of Religion (which was introduced by blood in <hi>Germany, France, Scotland, Poland, Sweden, Holland,</hi> and all places where it is eſtabliſht, ſave only in this Kingdome; yet the Prophecy was,<note place="margin">By <hi>Groſted</hi> Biſhop to H. 3.</note> 
               <hi>Populum Dei in Anglia non liberari à Papatu, niſi in ore gladii cruenti</hi>) but in matters of Civill Right, and Common Iuſtice. And now that God has proſpered our Worthies in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and made this Army ſo ſuccesfull, ſhall the Kingdome be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent with halfe their liberties? or remove the Court of Wards only, and let the poore Client be plagued and perplexed in other Courts as he is, and no hopes of redreſſe? oh happy <hi>Indians</hi> that have no Law Suits, or ſuddenly ended. Concerning both, I truſt this Kingdome will ever magnifie and reverence them as the ſupreame Court; and as all the members of the body have a care of the head, and venture all to ſave that; ſo muſt all the people of the Land, venture their lives to maintaine the Honour and juſt priviledges of the King and Parliament; my meaning is, that wee ought to have this eſteeme, not only of this ſupreame Court, and the conſtitution of the Government, but of every particular member, untill it plainely appeares that the Acts and Votes againſt the liberty of the Subject, and mindes his own profit, gaine, and the preferment of himſelfe and his friends, driving on furiouſly like <hi>Iehu</hi> amicable and peculiar intereſt, and neglecting the publique welfare of the people; that being priviledged himſelfe from all ſuites, is not ſenſible of the Clyents ſufferings. I have often thought that it were to be wiſht that Magiſtrates had ſuffered in their own private conditions, that ſo they might learn to pitty others; cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly for a Parliament man that is elected to guide the Ship of State, to looke after the Cockboate of his own private fortunes, and cares not whether the Kingdome bee Shipwrackt ſo as he may with the broken plankes build himſelfe a habitation; as it is the higheſt Treaſon that poſſibly can be committed, as being a breach of greateſt truſt; ſo certainly ſuch a man, to ſay no more, deſerves expulſion from the Honourable ſociety. And if by the long continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:114508:26"/> of Patliaments (which I take to bee the preſent caſe) ſome members ſhall joyn confederate together to advance themſelvs and their own party, and d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>preſſe all others that ſhall oppoſe their am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious deſignes; and by their active vigilance and ſtudied premedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations preſent matters ſo plauſible in the Houſe, and having the moon and ſtarre-light of naturall parts and other politique advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages, ſhall ſo prevayl to carry a Vote to the infringing of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples Liberties; if ſuch an extraordinary caſe happen, it will require an extraordinary remedy. I confeſſe when a Vote of great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment is carried but by 3 or 4, the leſſer number is included in the greater, as 4 in 5; and when there is 203 vote for it, and 200 againſt it, the Vote is not paſt by 3, but by 203: and as <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> ſayd, two are better then one, therefore no better way hath been deviſed; yet it cannot bee imagined that a fourth part in the Honourable Houſe ſhould ever vote againſt the Liberty of the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, if the deſign be rightly apprehended, unleſſe it be in a matter wherein they are exceedingly concerned in point of profit, in which caſe they are to be intreated to be abſent: but muſt a kingdom be undone in ſuch a caſe? his Majeſty agrees that there is a power in both Houſes more then ſufficient to reſtrain Tyranny, and that his Prerogative is but to defend his peoples Liberties; ſure then the Parliament will give mee leave to inferre without any offence to that ſupream Court (which is the honour and glory of the Engliſh Nation) that there is in the people a ſufficient power reſerved to preſerve themſelves from ſlavery and oppreſſion, if thoſe whom they have choſen to infranchiſe them, ſhould be the infringers of their liberties: But here I ſhall be demanded, why ſhould not the Army beleeve that the Parliament will, as they declare, ſettle the juſt rights of the King, and his ſubjects? Truly not to beleeve a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, is morall Infidelity, ſpecially ſuch a Parliament which hath done ſuch wonderfull things for the good of the ſubject as this hath done; for our forces had not been ſo victorious abroad, had not our Councels beene moſt wiſe at home; but yet reaſon againſt ſence is ſophiſticall. Nor can I beleeve what ſome of the Aſſembly pretend, that hee which is impriſoned for his conſcience, has the liberty of his conſcience; and now I have named that which is the great Apple of contention in this kingdome; for to ſpeak my thoughts freely, though I beleeve moſt of the Aſſembly are men regenerate, and good Chriſtians, and therefore I love them; yet had they never met, I am as confident as confidence it ſelfe can
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:114508:27"/> make me, that this kingdome had long ſince been ſetled in a peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able poſture; for we may thank them for their learned diſtinction of <hi>Presbyter</hi> and <hi>Independent,</hi> between whom lovers of peace deſire to make the difference very ſmall, but contentious ſpirits ſtudy to make it a wound incurable. For my own part, I confeſſe it is very improper for me, and unwilling am I to meddle with differences out of my proper element; yet there being a great work to be done in this generation, and the only playſter that is large enough to cure all the diſtempers in this kingdom; I conceive after twelve yeares ſtudy, being inevitably put upon the ſtudy of it by a ſpeciall providence, and ſcarce knowing any other controverſall point in Divinity worth ſtudying, the Prieſtly and Propheticall office of our bleſſed Saviour being in good meaſure (bleſſed be God) vindicated and redeemed out of the hands of thoſe <hi>Romiſh Huckſters;</hi> and whether the Inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of men ought any more to bee mingled with the Inſtitutions of Chriſt in his kingly office then their good works in his prieſtly office, is now the great diſpute. That the difference between them is not eſſentiall but graduall (for I look upon <hi>Presbytery</hi> as a ſtep to <hi>Independency</hi>) not in the body, but in the gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and therefore undoubtedly time and wiſedome may temper a Reconciliation; only through pride and covetouſneſſe comes this contention concerning liberty for tender Conſciences. Truly, whether the ſword can be any better imployed then for the defence of the true Religion, and whether it be not as lawfull to fight for Chriſts Kingly Office againſt the oppoſers of it, as for his Prieſtly Office againſt the Papiſts, it is not my intention to cleare any particular, but to give ſome generall hints, hoping that all Gods people though of different judgments in this particular, deſire a ſound and durable peace accompanied with truth and piety.</p>
            <p>What my opinion concerning a univerſall Tolleration of all Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligions; whether it be tollerable or inſufferable I will not deliver any opinion of it, becauſe it is not the thing in queſtion; I know none but Proteſtants that deſire this liberty, and that not ſo much in Doctrine as in Diſcipline. I think there is ſcarce a Papiſt in the Kingdome but either actually or vertually in their deſires at leaſt, hath been in Armes againſt the Parliament; 'tis clear that Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt fought for the late <hi>Oxford</hi> party, whether they fought for him or not: 'tis much that Chriſt and Antichriſt ſhould pitch their tents in the ſame field; and therefore certainly, 'tis a fond Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that men make; If you ſuffer <hi>Independents,</hi> then why not
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:114508:27"/> 
               <hi>Papiſts?</hi> becauſe thoſe that have been faithfull to the <hi>Parliament,</hi> and are of the ſame Religion, may in juſtice and equity have the liberty of their Conſciences, not diſturbing the peace of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; does it therefore follow that Enemies to the <hi>Parliament,</hi> of a different Religion, whoſe Religion in the power and practiſe of it is flat Rebellion, their Head Antichriſt, their Doctrine Hereſie, and worſhip Idolatry, holding pernitious principles, deſtructive of State Policy, that theirs ought to be ſuffered? If any Papiſt bee better principled and will take an Oath to bee true to King and Kingdome where they live, in all points, and will not make it their work to ſeduce others, and the number ſo ſmall, that the State need not probably fear any danger by them, as in <hi>Holland;</hi> I ſay nothing with it nor againſt it: but I would faine break the neck of that abſurd Argument, If you ſuffer a Proteſtant you muſt ſuffer a Papiſt; does every diverſity of opinion preſently make a different Religion? I will aſſure you there are more differences between the Papiſts about thoſe five little words, <hi>Hoc eſt enim corpus meum,</hi> this is my body, then there is between all the men in this Kingdome, and yet who more loving then they; before the Councell of <hi>Lateran,</hi> it was good Divinity to ſay at the Maſſe (which gets a maſſe of money) <hi>adoro te ſi tu es Chriſtus,</hi> I adore thee if thou be Chriſt; but ſince Tranſubſtantiation is ſetled by their Law, they are ſo fallen out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt themſelves, how to make the body of our Saviour to bee there as it was when he Inſtituted the Sacrament; that 'tis moſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable; and I think it better beſeeming us that are Proteſtants to laugh at thoſe Antichriſtian fopperies, and to pity one another; the ſtrong not to diſpiſe th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> weak, nor the weak to oppoſe the ſtrong: let me inſtance in ſome of their differences concerning their Tranſubſtantiation: Some Papiſts hold that Chriſt is not in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, becauſe he is in the Hoſt, others that there are two Chriſts, others are much troubled about the time that Chriſt continues with them; ſome hold that his body goes not into the ſtomack being full of humors, but then thinking there would be little fruit of it, they ſay he ſtayes till digeſtion, therefore they uſe not to eat for three or foure houres after; others hold the body never parts, but then no man needed to Communicate but once, and they could ſell their God but once, and the party ſinnes after, which could not be; then becauſe this body cannot annihilate, being as impoſſible here, as 'tis in the heavens, they differ what is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of the body; ſome hold that it was gone to heaven, but that
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:114508:28"/> cannot bee ſay others, becauſe it was there before, then the doubt is, how can accidents nouriſh the body? ſome hold that ſo ſoon as the ſtomack ha's changed the form of the Wafer cake, that God Creates a new ſubſtance of nothing; but againſt that ſome Prieſts finde that the wine does preſently comfort them, and Prieſts have been drunk with much wine; then they are much troubled where our Saviours head and his feet are, leaſt the Prieſt through ignorance ſhould hold him with his heeles upwards, and ſome hold that the head is alwayes upppermoſt, hold it how you pleaſe; another Prieſt was very angry with mee for asking him ſuch a queſtion that he knew not how to anſwer, but ſayes the face is alwayes towards the Prieſt for reverence; I know not how tis poſſible not to believe, but to imagine ſuch a confuſed <hi>Chymaera.</hi> Then they diſpute how the Organicall Body of Chriſt can be in a thing ſo little, therefore they ſay, the more wine the better; But the Prieſt does not ſee the wine in the Flaggon, yet ſay ſome the vertue of the words penetrates into it, others ſay tis Idolatry to attribute vertue to words, and others hold that the Pope took away all the vertue from the Greek words, and put it into the Latin; then they differ exceedingly whether the body of Chriſt came at the firſt word <hi>hoc,</hi> or at the ſecond word <hi>eſt;</hi> ſome hold that there is much vertue in the word <hi>enim</hi> by vertue of the Popes Vnction, and that when the word <hi>enim</hi> is pronounced, if the Prieſt ſtop there, then it is 3 parts fleſh and 2 parts Bread, becauſe the <hi>Lutherans</hi> that hold Conſubſtantiation, ſay they are wiſer then the Papiſts, for they eate bread with their fleſh, the Papiſts raw fleſh without bread; ſome Prieſts would pronounce the words with a very loud voice, thinking thereby to bring Chriſt the ſooner from Heaven; The people are angry with the Prieſt, and ſay it is an incivility to invite a man to a Dinner and not make him drink, others hold that no Article of faith can be contrary to a mans ſenſes. The Lord knowes that I write not this out of any Irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence to the bleſſed Sacrament,<note place="margin">Dominicani, Daem nic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ni, Franciſcani, Fraudiſcani, Carmelitani, Carnalitani, Mendicantes, Manducantes, Cervi, Servi.</note> but to ſhew that the Papiſts have more differences among themſelves then the Proteſtants, for he that will but read <hi>Mounſeiur</hi> St. <hi>Aldegonds Table</hi> of d ffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences between the Papiſts, ſhall finde that there are above 500. differences between them about the point of Tranſubſtantiation, which <hi>Trent</hi> makes an Article of their faith; and they differ in above 20. ſeverall points among themſelves, the <hi>Ieſuites</hi> conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding for the Immaculate Conception of the Virgin <hi>Mary;</hi> The
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:114508:28"/> 
               <hi>Dominicans</hi> tooth and naile oppoſing it, every order of <hi>Monkes</hi> and <hi>Fryars</hi> ſtudying to advance themſelves and commend their own Saint and Patron, and debaſe others in compariſon: ſo as if there ſhould bee as many ſubdiviſions in every point wherein they are divided, as about Tranſubſtantiation; which I think is no hard matter to make good: I might conclude that there are 10000. differences among the Papiſts, and yet they all agree cordially againſt the Proteſtants, and live as lovingly as if they were univerſally of one opinion; and in <hi>Luthers</hi> time haveing a generall meeting for the reconciliation of all theſe differences, one of their Biſhops, ſubtile and politique, fearing that <hi>Luthers</hi> Arguments would take w th the People, to make the Maſſe an arrant ſtrumpit, deſires to make one ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection for his ſatisfaction againſt it, the which was that either Chriſt held in his hand bread, or his body, or the accidents of bread, or ſomething elſe, or nothing; if bread then the word, <hi>this</hi> muſt be taken for this bread, and that would be repugnant, if his body, it had been abſurd to ſay my body is my body, and they ſay it is no body, till after the prolation of the words, if the accidents, then the Tranſubſtantiation was before the words, and to break accidents is not to break bread, if any thing elſe, what was it? if nothing, the Scripture is falſe, for hee took, and to ſay that the word <hi>this</hi> demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates nothing as preſent, but what ſhall be; this is to make our Saviour a Iugler to deceive their ſenſes; concerning the Virgins conception without ſin, he was likewiſe puſled becauſe the Scripture ſaies all have ſinned but only Chriſt, and how then do they keep a Holyday for the Virgins Conception? for no day may be kept holy for an unholy thing: Others ſaid it was but tolerated not approved, but ſaies the Biſhop, brethren you ſee theſe are rationall doubts, and your jarring will be the <hi>Lutherans</hi> uniting: therefore Pray, ſince wee can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not all agree in opinion, leaſt our differences ſhould advantage the common Enemy, let us live in love, and baniſh all ſtrife and contention: and I doe here by Authority from the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolique See, decree an <hi>Amneſtia</hi> and Oblivion of all diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences that have ſprung up amongſt any Papiſts concerning
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:114508:29"/> variety and d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fferences in judgement, the hearkning to which advice as ſome Polititians obſerve,<note place="margin">An Act that all that differ in opinion ſhall li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e lovingly <hi>non obstante.</hi>
               </note> was a meanes to continue the greateſt part of <hi>Germany</hi> in the Romiſh Religion; I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that at <hi>Paris</hi> going to ſee the <hi>Cardinalls</hi> Library which was kept by Doctor <hi>Smith</hi> our Countryman, a ſubtile man, and a great Schollar Biſhop of <hi>Chalcedon (alias terra incognita)</hi> he was very earneſt with me to reconcile my ſelfe into the boſome of the Roman Church; abuſing that Scripture that <hi>the Nation which did not ſerve her ſhould bee deſtroyed,</hi> and ſo muſt <hi>England.</hi> I told him that myſticall <hi>Babylon</hi> muſt bee deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: and he ſpeaking ſomething uncivily of <hi>England,</hi> ſaying he was perſecuted for his ſervice done to his honoured Miſtris and deare Mother the Church of <hi>Rome:</hi> I made bold to tell his Lordſhip that he Courted a foule Miſtris, not becauſe ſhee was foule, but becauſe ſhee was in the darke: and in the dark <hi>Pope Ioane</hi> is as good as my Lady. Amongſt other diſcourſe, he told mee, that the Proteſtants in <hi>England</hi> would deſtroy themſelves, and intreating his reaſon, ſaid he, do not you ſee how they perſecute the Puritans in <hi>England,</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> and at <hi>Geneva?</hi> And in the <hi>French</hi> Church, Maſter <hi>Melletier A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marant,</hi> for ſmal differences in opinion? who being men more ſingular for zeale then the reſt are diſgraced; whereas in our Church thoſe which are moſt zealous are moſt honoured, and the humility and auſterity of the <hi>Capuchines</hi> and <hi>Cordeliers</hi> helpe to make amends for the luxuriance of other orders. I wiſh every underſtanding man would but ponder this Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument: can that Religion ſubſiſt and flouriſh, where the moſt ſtrict and powerfull profeſſors of it are the objects of malice, and oppreſt for their Conſciences? Wee allow ſaies he, a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter latitude of opinions in the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the inquiſition, then your Biſhops will do in <hi>England;</hi> I told his Titulary Lordſhip that is was the intereſt of <hi>England</hi> to bee as zealous for the Proteſtant Religion, as the <hi>Spaniard</hi> was for the Pop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſh; The purity of the Goſpell and the free exerciſe and practice in the power of it, is now the intereſt of this Kingdom, and there is no ſuch way under Heaven to make this Kingdom ſuddenly happy as for all godly men though of diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:114508:29"/> judgments to unite cordially together againſt the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Enemy. I think no man will ſay but that the <hi>Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants</hi> are as great Adverſaries to Popery as any others are in this Kingdome. But now ſayes the Reader, I perceive you are for <hi>Liberty of Conſcience,</hi> that <hi>Babell</hi> of confuſion, and monſtrous <hi>Chymera,</hi> as men call it. Stay good friend, if you be a ſpirituall man and a new creature, that haſt found any mercy from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to thy poore ſoule, I ſhall ſpeak a few words with you about this buſineſſe, for ſpirituall arguments to a dead heart are but as warm water to a dead man; for a carnall man to ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue of ſpirituall priviledges, is for a man to take out a hot Iron with his fingers. Conſcience is a Diamond, and only wrought upon by the duſt of a Diamond; men that have no Conſcience know not what it is. The beſt argument that hath bin brought againſt the Congregationall way, is that which the Papiſts urge againſt Chriſts Prieſtly office in point of ſatisfaction, that it is more lyable to Abuſes and Hereſies, then the way of Claſſes; ſo ſayes <hi>Aquinas,</hi> if good works do not merit, who wil do any good works? the prudentiall way certainly to move men to doe good works, is to tell them that they merit by ſo doing; but look at the Inſtitution, what is the will of Chriſt? I doe not intend to argue it, but to the former queſtion, can the ſword be better imployed then to defend good Chriſtians? what injury hath the Goſpel of grace done to this Kingdom, this 100 years, that all men ſhould not venture their lives to maintaine it, if any ſhould unjuſtly goe about to deprive us of it? but did not the Chriſtians in primitive times ſuffer Martyrdome? Tis true, Chriſt Jeſus had newly ſuffered, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>od would have the firſt ſeeds of Religion watered with bloud, and Religion then was but a novelty, and in its infancy; children are ſubject to be abuſed by every one, which being of age will defend themſelves; but for a conſiderable number of men to fly or ſuffer death, is rather to be ſheep then men: does Religion overthrow na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture? That example of the <hi>Theban</hi> Leaguer under <hi>Maximi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi> was miſtaken by <hi>Tertullian,</hi> for the Chriſtians were diſperſed and knew not their own ſtrength; and that Saint <hi>Maurice</hi>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:114508:30"/> had 5000 in Armes, and would not fight againſt the King of <hi>Thebans,</hi> is not reported by any credible Author, but that 20000 Chriſtians were martyred on Chriſtmas Day under <hi>Diocletian,</hi> poſſibly it may be ſo; and ſo it was in <hi>Paris</hi> at the <hi>S. Bartholomew</hi> 1575. ten thouſand Proteſtants maſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred. But all theſe Arrowes fall ſhort of the mark where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at they are ſhot. 'Tis certainly more valour and Religion to fight for the maintenance of the true Religion eſtabliſht by a Law, then to ſuffer patiently; active Martyrdome in ſuch a caſe is better then paſſive, and this is no Hoſtility; they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin no warre, they provoke not, the perſecutors may have peace when they pleaſe, let them not ſtrike, and give aſſurance of it to thoſe which are in Armes for their Religion, and they will lay down Armes preſently, as the <hi>French</hi> Proteſtants told their Kings. Will the Cardinalls ſuffer an hereticall Pope, as they call hereſy? no; will the Biſhops ſuffer hereticall Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinalls? no; will the Prieſts ſuffer hereticall Prieſts? no; will the common Papiſts ſuffer hereticall Biſhops? no; do wee not defend againſt God himſelf by phyſick, and by food againſt ſickneſſe? If a man have a ſword in his hand, 'tis abſurd to tell a Theife of Law and Iuſtice, but fall upon him: <hi>Conſtantine</hi> fought againſt <hi>Licinius</hi> in <hi>Paleſtine,</hi> and made him give Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to the Chriſtians; to ſtand by and ſuffer a brother to bee killed is worſe then the Murtherer, for the one may be through choler and the violence of a temptation, but not to help my brother argues a baſe ſpirit: and is it not fratricide in me not to ſeek for juſtice upon him that hath kil'd my brother? I fear the death of <hi>Barrow</hi> and <hi>Greenwood,</hi> &amp;c. lay heavie upon ſome who might have oppoſed the Biſhops. What muſt the pillars of juſtice and truth be ſhaken for Uniformity? muſt rights be invaded and violated for Formes and Ceremonies? tell mee thou Beleeving ſoule, does thy Religion conſiſt in an ocular beauty and out-ſide uniformity, or in a reall love and inward conformity to the Lawes of Chriſt? is thy ſoule at reſt, in the enjoyment of thy God, in the face of Chriſt? and doſt thou vex and diſquiet thy ſelfe at Formes and ſhadowes? doſt thou
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:114508:30"/> perſecute thy poore brethren, partakers of the like precious faith with thy ſelfe? impriſon his body and vex his righteous ſoule, becauſe his eye-ſight poſſibly is not ſo clear as thine, and yet pretend that Conſcience is not enforced, but only the outward man, and ſo mock and jeere at the calamity of thy brother? who poſſibly hath greater enjoyments of God, and lives more by faith and leſſe by ſence then thy ſelfe? but ſayes one, may not God ſanctifie this way to reclaime him from his errour? muſt it bee an errour becauſe thou ſayſt ſo? and if it be ſo, wilt thou bee unjuſt becauſe I am erronious? I pray thee, which is the greateſt ſinne? the manner of Gods worſhip is no matter of juſtice; many Chriſtians doe not meet in the publick places, having been conſecrated to Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrous uſes, and there was no naturall uſe for them; and are not ſatisfied when I tell them that by the ſame reaſon they may not worſhip in this Kingdom becauſe dedicated to <hi>S. George,</hi> nor upon any day in the week, every day having been dedicated to ſome Saint or other; it ſatisfies them not, for of the dayes and times there is a naturall neceſſity, but none for the places and grounds, which by ſpeciall command were to be aboliſhed; for my one part I conceive this to be an errour; but may any man therefore violate juſtice, the queen of morall vertues; the ſupporter of Thrones and States, and commit palpable injuſtice, the quean of vices, and ſupplanter of States and Kingdomes, by invading theſe mens houſes which are by law their Caſtles, and offer violence to their perſons who are praying for the Magiſtrate, that under him they may live godly and quiet lives, and deſtroy all civill and naturall rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; haling the poore husband from his wife to a priſon, and puniſhing the innocent wife and children, who are not er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roneous for the husbands errour. if this bee not injuſtice there was never any done under the cope of Heaven. Can it be for the publick good to impriſon a man becauſe he will not ſin? therefore, can this Kingdome be happy without ſuch a Liberty of Conſcience? and is it likely to bee obtained if this Army were disbanded? ſpeak plainly, did not perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:114508:31"/> come on like an armed man? would not cruell perſecutors and Oppreſſors have had, if they might, the ſame power over Gods people as the <hi>Romans</hi> had over their ſlaves, if they ſpared, it was a courteſie; had not every man in the Army the next day after their disbanding been in the ſame condition for his Conſcience as the Papiſts are, if theſe men might have had their wils upon them? And are not ſome which have ventured their lives againſt Popery and Tyranny in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dited upon the Statutes of Recuſants? which were made to diſtinguiſh betweene the Ieſuited practiſing Papiſt and the peaceable Recuſant? who till the eleventh yeare of the Queene repaired conſtantly to our Churches, and after fearing leaſt the Papiſts ſhould bee too rich, the wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of State, impoſed a penalty upon them of twenty pound a Moneth for their abſenting from Church: and what comminations have there lately beene to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed againſt poore Chriſtians upon the Statutes of <hi>Hereſy</hi> made in time of Popery againſt the Lollards, which were Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, and <hi>Wickliffes</hi> followers, one of our protomartyrs of <hi>England?</hi> truly <hi>Superſtition</hi> is an unreaſonable thing; ſuch bloody opinions prove the Authors to bee rather beaſts then men. Honeſt faithfull men becauſe they cannot in all things come up and conform to the opinion of ſome Prelaticall ſpirits, muſt be denyed the liberty to breathe, and civill cohabitation; or if that favour be obtayned, they muſt be made hewers of wood, and drawers of water, as if the ten Tribes ſhould have been ſlaves to the <hi>Gibeonites,</hi> nay worſe then ſlaves, their very Oxen to plough for them, and reap for them; the honey by thoſe men was not intended for the Bees; <hi>ſic vos non vobis, &amp;c.</hi> Tell me now, is it not more mercy to kill the wolfe, then to let him go? is it not better to be nouriſhed by a Theefe, then kild by a Shepheard? is it not better to be healed by an Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perick, then to be poyſoned by a Phyſitian? But in the former Caſe that I put, where twenty choſe a Captain to command them (for he is as truly a King, though not ſo great and glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous a King, that reignes over twenty, as hee that reignes over
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:114508:31"/> twenty millions. Many of the Kings mentioned in Scripture, of <hi>Sychem, Iericho, Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah,</hi> never had ſo large a command as the Lord Mayor of <hi>London.</hi> No King in <hi>Iſrael</hi> was Conductor of the people. <hi>Governour</hi> is the generall word, and to bee a King is but one kinde of Government: <hi>Florence</hi> and <hi>Muſcovy,</hi> but Dukes in name, have the greateſt power of any Kings in Chriſtendome) if the ſeventeen deſire to ſerve God contrary to the Captains judgement, with the Common Prayer Book for the purpoſe; the Captain with the other two comes to the houſe where the ſeventeen are worſhiping, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupts them, and will hale them to a priſon; they alleadge for themſelves, that they doe not any way diſturb the preſent Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of State, but deſire freedome in their Conſciences; the queſtion is, Whether in this caſe it be againſt the word of God, for theſe ſeventeen to defend their owne profeſſion, and to deſtroy the Captain and the other two for the liberty of their conſciences, if otherwiſe they cannot preſerve it? my mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is, after all meanes of entreaty uſed to the Captain, to bee indulgent to them in ſo pretious a thing as Gods Service is, and flying b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ck to a wall, as we ſay, as farre as a man can when he is purſued, and ſo to make it but a pure <hi>ſe defendendo.</hi> For my own part, I think that it is not only lawfull, but a thing moſt neceſſary, that if theſe ſeventeen men ſhould ſuffer themſelves to bee impriſoned for their conſciences by their Captain and two others, that God would be angry with them for being ſo unnaturall and unjuſt to themſelves. But then the queſtion will be, If the Captain and ſeventeen ſhould be of one opinion, and the other two contrary minded, and the eighteen make it capitall, and condemn the other two for Heretiques; whether may the other two reſiſt in this caſe? I anſwer, they may ſave themſelves by flight if they can, but for two to take up Arms againſt the eighteen, I am doubtfull whether it bee lawfull, at leaſt convenient, becauſe there is no probable hopes of ſucceſſe; and it is the minde of God, that theſe two ſhould ſuffer pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently what they cannot help; and this will fall within that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Rule, Of two evils the leaſt is to be choſen; the two are ſure to loſe their lives, therefore they muſt ſuffer patiently ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:114508:32"/> then to endanger the lives of others with them; for the God of peace does not delight in warres: and then an evill is judged to bee inevitable when there is no apparent ordinary way to avoyd it, becauſe without an extraordinary warrant wee may not preſume of Gods extraordinary power and aſſiſtance; as if an honeſt man with a ſword bee ſet upon by two theeves with piſtols; now in this caſe I hold it wiſdome to deliver his purſe to ſave his life, becauſe two are ſtronger then one. Nature is Gods Lievtenant and efficient, by a power from God received, continued, &amp; permitted; and in humane affaires we are to look what the courſe of Nature may probably effect, if not checked: when God ſayes this ſhall be becauſe I will not hinder it, then Nature of its own nature produces ſuch effects. What King with a thouſand will fight againſt him that comes with ten thouſand? and as the uſe of lawfull means for ſafety, does not argue a confidence in the creature, but a ſubordination of the meanes, that God without meanes can do it, but meanes with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out God cannot doe it; yet ſomtimes God puts more ſtrength then ordinary into the creature, and acts more immediatly, by ten ſometimes chaſing a thouſand, therefore I paſſe it over: But my meaning is, that a warre for deſence of Religion is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtionable, but the manner is alwayes to bee pondered; and that in any Kingdome or State where ſuch a conſiderable num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of people which are the ſtronger part, ſhall upon good grounds bee convinced in their judgements that they cannot by reaſon of the prevalency of ſome proud, domineering, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetous, or malicious ſpirited men, that had rather loſe a Kingdome then that ſome men ſhould enjoy too much of heaven upon earth; and would ſet the Kingdome together by the eares to get their Eare-rings; who while they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claym againſt <hi>Conventicles,</hi> and private meetings of honeſt people, are themſelves the moſt dangerous, and only Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venticlers that I know in the Kingdom; having their conſtant meetings how to oppreſſe and degrade all that ſtand in their way, both in ſoules and bodies; it being ſuch clandeſtine and factious Ends onely, that in judgement of Law makes a Conventicle; for a hundred men to aſſemble to carry a Tree, is no offence;
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:114508:32"/> and will not let honeſt and peaceable men have freedome and liberty to ſerue God, according to that light they have received from the Father of lights, and to receive common juſtice, ſubmitting for conſcience ſake to every ordinance of man: in ſuch a caſe it is not onely permitted but commanded that theſe men manfully defend themſelves and their liberties, or elſe they are in effect ſelfe-murtherers, and in ſuch a caſe, the truth of God is of that value, that his meekeſt ſervants will fight for it, rather then it ſhall be indangered: what Doctor <hi>Ferne</hi> obj<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cts againſt it is but ſtubble and combuſtible, and will not beare the weight of a feather in the ballance of the Sanctuary, for will any man that is ſound in his intellectuals, (unleſſe he deſire to be a Biſhop) Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine that ever Saint <hi>Paul</hi> commanded the poore Saints in <hi>Neroes</hi> houſehold to be ſubject to <hi>Nero</hi> in Church matters, that was an ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my to them, or to <hi>Caligula,</hi> that wiſhed that all Chriſtians had but one naturall head, as they had but one myſticall; I wiſh there were no <hi>Caligulaes</hi> amongſt us, that would be cutting off many heads at one blow. Indeed if any Court might enforce mens conſciences, what miſerable things were Chriſtians? Truth ſhall be ſure to be ſhut out of doors, for the moſt are ſeldome the beſt; <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks of legall, civill authority, the Saints in <hi>Rome</hi> are but a handfull, and had no law for their Religion. That there ſhould be ſome government is Gods inſtitution, as in the fifth Commandement, which bindes the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in poſitive Laws, though hard and rigorous, but the manner of it is mans appointment and conſtitution, of whoſe power and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, good and evill actions are the proper and adaequate objects. I willingly grant that the Magiſtrate who is a good Chriſtian ſtands upon the advantage ground, and ought to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand the people for Gods ſake, to yeild obedience to the Laws of God, and to be exemplary in his converſation, and to protect Gods people by declaring againſt errours, and that no man ought to beare with an errour in his deareſt conſort; but perſwaſion is the Goſpel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lary way without all diſpute in matters not fundamentall. My Lord <hi>Bacon</hi> was of that opinion, he that is not againſt us is with us. Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall maladies muſt have ſpirituall remedies; in matter of opinion I wrong no man; if he be offended at me, it is his weakneſs, I intend it not, I ſpeake of errours in Religion, not errours againſt Religion, with a toleration whereof no State or Kingdom can ſubſiſt. 'Tis a fruit of the Turks Religion, not to couzen nor ſteale, and to make con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:114508:33"/> of an Oath, to doe no murther nor adultery: 'Tis againſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trinſicall rules of all government, to permit any of theſe, nor muſt any errour be permitted, that is a ſworne enemy to peace and policy. Man can give no power but what God gives, therefore it is no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting of authority when there can be no ſuch authority given; mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of conſcience are not giveable nor takeable. If I bid any man kill me, and tye my hands, yet I may breake the cords; I cannot give power to enſlave my ſelfe, nor ought any man take it. If there ſhould be any Covenant made to enforce conſcience, it is an unjuſt Oath, and to keepe it is to adde a greater ſinne to a leſs, as if the firſt were too little, whereas the leaſt is too great, and ſhould be leſned not enlar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged,; and though I am bound to loſe by my Covenant, yet not to be undone by it. When the Lord viſits us with ſickneſſe, doe not we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend our ſelves againſt his bleſſed Majeſty by Phyſick, by food and rayment? And nothing more lawfull and naturall then ſelfe defence, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt which no Canon can be of force, as it was reſolved at <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance,</hi> that a Canon made in favour of an angry Pope, that he might ſtrike any man, and no man ſtrike him, was void by the Law of nature: for what is it but to arme ſin againſt the Law? did not <hi>Swe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, Holland, France, Germany, Poland,</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> introduce Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion by the ſword? <hi>Calvin, Beza, Bellarmine, Carrerius, Junius, Turquet, Bucanus,</hi> maintained the lawfulneſſe of it, and <hi>Bilſon</hi> in the Queens time wrote a book in defence of it; not to invade the Turke becauſe he is not a Chr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſtian, but for the freedome of their own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences. King <hi>James</hi> in his Epiſtle to <hi>Perron,</hi> juſtifies the French Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants fighting for their Religion, calling it a defenſive Warre, that he which offers the wrong is alwayes on the offenſive part, as he that denies the debt begins the ſuit, and ſuch a wrong doer cannot be wronged. <hi>Geneva</hi> in 1536 caſt off the Biſhop their Prince, and <hi>Calvin</hi> ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yes, Populars may reſtrain all kinde of tyranny, as the <hi>Ephori</hi> did the <hi>Lacedemonian</hi> Kings, and the Tribunes curbed the Conſuls; and if for bodies much more for ſouls: the reaſon is becauſe every people in the conferring of power, reſerve ſo much to themſelves to attaine that end whereunto they are ordained, which is the glory of God and their own freedoms and welfare. Certainly God never commanded any Magiſtrates to lay any clogs or Fetters upon the conſciences of his own people, that's the apple of his own eye; yet ſo, as if by force his people be deſtroyed, they muſt take it patiently, dye like lambs
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:114508:33"/> for the Lambs ſake that dyed for them, but they may not ſuffer if they can oppoſe it, that's to be guilty of ſelfe murther. The ſufferings of Jeſus Chriſt were voluntary, and when wee reſigne our wills to a thing enforced, we make it willing and ſo the Martyrs were ſaid to lay down their lives willingly, and yet they could not help it. This fighting for Religion is not to fight to promote it in others, not to kill any tyrants that oppoſe it, but to preſerve Religion and the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors of it.</p>
            <p>All Magiſtrates are tyed to the Laws of God and nature, and 'tis a leſſe ſinne for a private man to breake thoſe Laws then the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate who is intruſted to keepe them. For a Commiſſioner to breake a truſt is the higheſt prevarication; againſt which illegalities ſelf-defence is lawfull, if the party can help it; men may free themſelves from tyrants, if they can; if not, what remedy but patience? the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is perſpicuous becauſe no man can impower another over him to command againſt both, or either of thoſe Laws, and therefore the meaning of thoſe commands of honouring the King, our parents and governours, is to obſerve all ſuch lawfull commands as are not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to God and nature, for God is the God of order, which he ſhould not be, if Governours were to be obeyed diſorderly.</p>
            <p>If a King or Governour be mad, muſt all the Kingdom be fools to obey ſuch a Devill as that Duke <hi>D' Alva</hi> was, that made the Hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans place in <hi>Flanders</hi> better then the Chancellours. If ſuch a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate be drunke, and reſolved to kill whomſoever he meets, may not the people ſhot him up all night from doing miſchiefe? to take away a madmans ſword from him, is not to take away the property but to prevent the miſchiefe. Many of <hi>H.</hi> 7. freinds had ſworne fealty to <hi>R.</hi> 3. yet <hi>H.</hi> 7. did well to kill him, and we never read of my pardon obtained from the Pope; the Royall race of <hi>H.</hi> 7. inherits ſtill in our Soveraigne Lord King CHARLES, to whom God im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part as many graces as to all his Anceſtors, that as he hath made the heart of Gods people ſad, ſo he may now make it his royall ſtudy to ſet Jeſus Chriſt upon his Throne, by whoſe gain his Majeſty can be no loſer; and long may that Royall race continue to adminiſter and exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute good and wholſome Laws for the proſperity of theſe Nations, by which it is more honourable to command 10 free men, then to ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannize over 10000 Gally-ſlaves. If the Magiſtrate in a Proteſtant Kingdom ſhould introduce Popery, as in Queen <hi>Maries</hi> time, a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:114508:34"/> man may not oppoſe; but the Parliament might and by the Law of God ought to have oppoſed it: But if the Lord had put a ſword into the hands of the Smithfield Martyrs, able in probability to have defended themſelves, theſe could not have dyed with com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort for their Religion; for I cannot judge him a good Chriſtian that is not a morall man, and he that will not doe right to himſelfe to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend his own life will hardly doe right to his neighbour, he that hath but a little minde can be but a little vertuous.</p>
            <p>I affirme, that the Army may not disband in point of honour, till this Kingdome be in a better way of ſettlement, for I ever thought that there was more to be done for the happineſſe thereof, then the humiliating and geniculating of the late <hi>Oxford</hi> party, whoſe ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then out reformation might be the cauſe thereof, for doe not their adverſaries brag before the victory? if many cruell men might have their wils, what could the Army expect when disbanded? There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if they ſhould hereafter ſuffer, they would undoubtedly make themſelves a <hi>Ludibri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> and deriſion to all the world; what? 20000 armed men victorious and veteran Commanders and Souldiers, (not fleſh but bone) that feare nothing but to offend God, neither the ſons of <hi>Anak</hi> not the ſons of <hi>Cain,</hi> that ſpeake big like Gyants, and perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute their brethren <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>an Army that hath the juſtice of heaven on their ſides the prayers of Gods people the good will of the whole Kingdom, that have been the <hi>Joſhuahs</hi> that have led Gods people into the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall <hi>Canaan,</hi> that are plainly told, that if they were disbanded, they muſt not have a mouthfull of ayre in this Kingdome, but in a priſon; unleſſe they will put out their own eyes, to ſee by the ſpectacles of other men in point of Gods ſervice and worſhip<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that are called trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blers of the State, Heretikes and Sectaries, that had been better, the liberties of the Kingdom had been loſt then ſaved by them, and all this to their faces with their ſwords in their hands. For ſuch an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my as this, I ſay, to thinke upon disbanding as the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſe ſtands, I muſt make bold to tell them, that if they ſhould, Jeſus Chriſt would take it unkindly from them, and they would make themſelves culpaple of all the precious bloud that ſhould be ſpilt in a way of perſecution, and all the reproaches mockings, ſcornes, ſcourging<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> baniſhments, impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, contempts, ignominies, diſgraced and affronts, that ſhall be caſt upon any Chriſtian, and the Goſpel of Chriſt, which any of Gods people ſhall hereafter in any wiſe ſuffer in this Kingdeme for their
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:114508:34"/> conſciences and ſincerity in Gods ſervice would be laid upon their ſcore; and I ſolemnly profeſſe with words of ſobriety, upon the Altar of truth, that Gods people and this whole Kingdome would have cauſe to blame them as the greateſt prevaricators of all others; for to be treacherous for honours is diſhonourable: for a great Office to betray a truſt is ſordid and mercenary; to betray a truſt for feare is cowardly and ſervile; for flattery or inſinuation is weake, effeminate, and childiſh; for love or relation is not ſo great an offence, becauſe more humane (howbeit, all treaſon committed againſt a mans Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey is inhumane and unworthy:) but for one Chriſtian to betray another, is of all treacheryes the moſt abominable: and here let me make this argument for the Army, will it be ſufficient for them to ſay if perſecution ſhould ariſe after their disbanding deare friends we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not help you, the Parliament are all for the Presbytery, many of the Aſſembly and City Miniſters were ſo importunate with many of the honourable Members to ſettle their Presbytery, that we have left all things to them, would it not be anſwered; what, <hi>Hath the Lord that gave you courage taken away <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cir wiſdome? did you begin in the ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>irit and end in the fleſh? Is this the requit all we muſt expect for all our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>es for you, who have prayed and beleeved you into all your victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior?</hi> You ſay it had been moſt noble, and ſo indeed it had, for the Parliament before you engaged, to have told you plainly, <hi>Gentlemen, We ſuſpect many of you to be Independents, be adviſed what you doe, if you give us the victory we intend to ſettle a Preſbytery, and to ſuffer none to live in the Kingdome, but ſuch as ſhall conforme to the preſent government; if you will fight to ſettle Preſbytery, well and good; but your victory will be your ruine for the King promiſeth a liberty and indulgence to tender conſciences.</hi> Might not your friends in the City and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, as well have expected as much from you, that you ſhould have told them, provide for your own indemnity, the Biſhops being by our means put down and aboliſhed, and the Presbytery ſetled, wee intended no more, as for the freedome of our conſciences and yours, and finding out an expedient for cheap and quick juſtice to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred in all places which might make the poore Kingdome ſome good amends for all the charges they have been at, if the Parliament pleaſe to doe it well and good, we have that which we fought for, <hi>Et gaudeant poſſidentes.</hi> 'Tis therefore but a taking of Gods providence in vain by many, that looking only at the outſide of things ſay, that
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:114508:35"/> this Army loſes much of their Honour they had gained by not Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banding, 'tis quite contrary, they had endangered the loſſe of their Honour indeed, if they had disbanded before Laws and Liberties be ſetled; perſeverance is the Crown of Action, to fight for Laws and Liberties, and then to ſuffer an inconſiderable number of Intendiaries to trample upon the Priviledges of the Subject; this had been a ſtain of a deep dye; the truth is, that the bellows are blown by ſome of the Clergy themſelves. Who knows not but that Divines (as they call themſelves) have by their Divinations almoſt infatuated all <hi>Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome?</hi> but there is no Enchantment againſt <hi>Iſrael,</hi> nor Divination againſt <hi>Jacob;</hi> ſays <hi>Luther,</hi> If Popery had laſted but two years longer in <hi>Saxony</hi> the Prieſts would have made the papiſts to have eaten ſtraw with the Oxen; were not moſt Kingdomes in <hi>Europe,</hi> governed by Cardinals, Biſhops, Prieſts and the Clergy? who did not eaſily fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee in <hi>England,</hi> but that it was an impoſſible thing to aboliſh Biſhops without a War, the <hi>Hierarchy</hi> had ſuch a deep rooting, that without a great Earthquake it could never have been ſhaken. I have heard when the Parliament began, ſome worthy Members being in diſcourſe about the putting down of Biſhops, Maſter <hi>Pym,</hi> and other gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant men ſayd, <hi>It was not poſſible to be done;</hi> and when the Aſſembly firſt met, they thought it impoſſible to take away the Common Prayer Book, but we ſee what the Lord hath done, for his people by his bleſſing upon the Parliament and our Armies; miſtake me not, I doe not rejoyce that the COMMON PRAYER BOOK; is ſuppreſſed; for my part if the PARLIAMENT ſhall ſo pleaſe, let thoſe that are ſo earneſt for it, keepe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it ſtill; much good it may do them, though I think little good will it do to them: it never did hurt to Papiſts, nor good to Proteſtants; unleſſe it be to ſhew them their dangerous condition: for they pray that their lives may be more pure and holy, and yet many of them ſcoff and jecreat purity and holineſs; but though we be not all one in judgement and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, yet let us be all one in affection and live lovingly together as Brethren, for he that loves another onely becauſe he is of his opinion, loves himſelf in that man.</p>
            <p>A friend of mine too violent for the Claſſicall way, ſeemed to be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry angry becauſe his Majeſty was permitted the uſe of the Common Prayer Book, I asked him whether in caſe his Majeſty would be gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly pleaſed to allow him the uſe of the Directory, hee would not
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:114508:35"/> think it fit that his MAJESTY ſhould have the liberty of his Conſcience? he ſayd, wee had Covenanted againſt it, to take it away as a branch of Popery; I told him the ſpeciall point of popery to be rooted out, is all domineering and tyrannizing over the conſcience. Are wee not all the ſervants of God? why ſhould wee Lord it one over another in matters of conſcience? but hee replyed, that we were to bring all to the neereſt Uniformity; I anſwered, that neereſt was not the ſame. Many ſhips ſayl neer a Rock that come not to it, the Common Prayer Book and Directory are very neer of kin; I know no reaſon, why they may not bear with one another, if his Majeſty and the Parliament pleaſe. I remember, being at <hi>Sedan,</hi> a paſſage not unworty to be inſerted; the Duke of <hi>Bullun</hi> Prince of <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dan,</hi> whoſe Anceſtors and himſelfe had been ſpeciall friends to the French Proteſtants, for the love of a beautifull Romiſh Lady, changed his Religion and turned papiſt. The Town being all Proteſtants, as good reaſon they had accordingly oppoſed it; He entreated them that he might be married by a prieſt in the Towne, they refuſed it: The Duke left his Mother, the good old Madam in the Caſtle, went away and was married, &amp; return'd with his Lady, but the Inhabitants ſhut the gates againſt him, and ſo hee went to one of his Summer houſes, two leagues from the Town, and there were ſeverall Treaties between him and his Subjects about his Re-admittance. He alledging, that ſince he and his Anceſtors had been the procurers of their Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, why ſhould they envy him the liberty of his conſcience? they ſayd, He was a Star faln from Heaven, and it would be dangerous for them to be under his command. An <hi>Engliſhman</hi> diſcourſing with <hi>Moli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naus</hi> and <hi>Ramburſius,</hi> two learned Miniſters about it, aſſumed by way of argument, that as that caſe ſtood with all its circumſtances, for them to deny him the exerciſe of his conſcience, who had purchaſed their Liberties, was moſt unjuſt in it ſelfe, and would be prejudiciall to other Proteſtants by incouraging Catholike Princes againſt them, and might bring miſchief upon their own heads; at laſt he had liberty to come into the Town; &amp; the Lady Ducheſs his wife, and Maſſe was ſayd in the Caſtle, allowing her two prieſts and no more: but not long ſince the <hi>French</hi> King made advantage of it againſt them, that they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed liberty to their naturall Prince, and they are now, I feare as the <hi>Rochilers</hi> are, and no freer. But this I drive at, Rigid Presbytery is but yet a <hi>Probationer,</hi> if it ſhould be ſetled in this Kingdom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in the height and power of it, it would undoubtedly coſt ten times more
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:114508:36"/> bloud to remove it, then ever it hath done to aboliſh Epiſcopacy; I ſpeak of a Rigid ſtrict <hi>Preſbytery,</hi> that make their judgement as the Kings Royall Standard, to weigh and meaſure all opinions by them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to walk by their rule, which will admit of no Exceptions; if you would know what ſuch a <hi>Preſbyter</hi> is; you may take it thus; A Rigid <hi>Preſbyter</hi> is he that is againſt every man, and every man againſt him; he will endure no man in the Kingdom but thoſe that are of his opinion <hi>in omnibus;</hi> and therefore no man in the Kingdome hath rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to endure him; I aſſure you that that grievous Diſeaſe called the <hi>Sudor Anglicus,</hi> the <hi>Sweating Sickneſſe,</hi> which laſted about forty years in this Kingdome, that ſwept away ſo many, that Harveſt could not be Inned in many places, was not ſo dangerous to this Kingdome, as this <hi>Rigid Preſbytery,</hi> if it ſhould grow inveterate; there is a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie in <hi>Scotland, It began with</hi> Knoxs, <hi>and muſt end with knocks,</hi> my prayer is, that the Rulers in that Kingdom would have a more favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable regard to tender Conſciences, and give free liberty to Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in their Native Kingdome. There are many <hi>Scots</hi> baniſhed into <hi>Holland</hi> and other places for matter of Conſcience, whom I verily believe to be precious Chriſtians: ſome of them told mee that their parents had been principall Inſtruments in the Reformation of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion in that Kingdom, and therefore took it unkindly that they ſhould be exiled for ſome differences in opinions, no way fundamentall or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive of State-policy; for why, in the name of God; ſhould it any more diſturbe the peace of the Kingdom, to permit Chriſtians to pray together in a private Chamber, then for others to meet there a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout their ordinary buſineſſe?</p>
            <p>I deſire deerly to be conceived when I uſe the word <hi>Preſbytery;</hi> the Lord knows my heart, I uſe it onely for diſtinction ſake, not for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach, I do not oppoſe nor ſpeak againſt a moderate <hi>Preſbyter;</hi> but look upon it as an excellent way to reſtrain vice; and for my own part I like it, for that which many fear it. Namely, it will be a means to prevent many frivolous quarrels and contentious Law-ſuits: Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly, there is an externall beauty in that Government in <hi>Scotland, Geneva,</hi> &amp; the <hi>French Congregations,</hi> but truly the power of Godlineſs is ſeen but little amongſt them; I have known in a <hi>Preſbyterian</hi> Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters houſe, that there hath bin no prayer nor Family dutyes performed twice in a yeare, and Examination before the Sacrament counted ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluous, and if any thing have been queſtioned, no other anſwer; but the <hi>Puritans</hi> in <hi>England</hi> will be under no Order nor Government.
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:114508:36"/> Is it not fit that Gods people for whoſe ſake the World continues ſhould have a being in the World if they can mayntain it? nor do I ſay any thing againſt moderate Presbyters; I believe there are many godly men of the Presbyterian judgment, though not as they are Presbyters; Saint <hi>Peter</hi> oppoſed Chriſt in the worke of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, for which our Saviour ſayd unto him, <hi>Get thee behind me Satan,</hi> and the devout women oppoſed the Apoſtles in the planting of the Goſpel: <hi>Amaziah</hi> and <hi>Jehoſaphat</hi> good Kings of <hi>Judah,</hi> yet took not away the high places; <hi>Hezekiah</hi> did, and <hi>Joſiah</hi> yet more and more; all godly men are not equally enlightned: Were there not ſome godly Conformiſts (think you) in the Biſhops time that op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed Nonconformiſts? He that is the ſtricteſt Presbyter now, poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly ſeven yeares ſince was for Biſhops, and ſeven yeares hence, if God give repentance for keeping his Son Chriſt out of his throne, may be an Independent. But this is the miſery, that thoſe men which are the moſt zealous promoters of the Rigid Presbyterian way are Politicians (whoſe greateſt Religion is to be of no Religion at all) that play their game ſo cunningly, that the godly Presbyterians not diſcerning their ambitious aymes, which is to make themſelves <hi>Grandees</hi> in Church and State, joyne and concur with them; as I have told you what the Rigid Presbyter is, ſo I ſhall expreſſe whom I mean by the godly Presbyter; I am well acquainted with many of them, and I verily believe, in my conſcience, that hee is ſuch a one who really intends the glory of God and the welfare of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and fearing nothing ſo much as Errours and Hereſies, concludes upon the whole matter, having read all arguments <hi>pro</hi> and <hi>con,</hi> that it is better to ſuffer a miſchief then an inconvenience, better that many good Chriſtians ſhould be impriſoned for their conſciences, then that under the Notion of <hi>Independency</hi> the peace of the Church ſhould be indangered by Errours and Hereſies, and gives his vote though with ſome reluctancy, that thoſe that cannot ſubmit to a Government, let them go beyond ſea, where they may enjoy their liberty, and not having faith enough to beleeve that truth will at the length get ground of errour, nor cleerly underſtanding that the ſword of the Spirit muſt cut down Errours, takes the materiall ſword which was never ſanctified to that purpoſe: whereby it will appeare how vain that objection is, that the Army hereby loſes all their honour in not disbanding upon vote, being commiſſionated
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:114508:37"/> by the Parliament, as if a man that takes a Commiſſion to fight for Laws and Liberties, that concerns himſelfe and others, hath any reaſon to ſheath his ſword till he hath obteined what he fought for, ſince by Gods infinite bleſſing upon, and gracious preſence with our Noble Worthies in Parliament, and victorious Armie, the ſhip of this Kingdome, after many <hi>Herricanes</hi> is ſafely arrived full fraught with thoſe precious commodities of the Subjects Liberties and properties, whereof Liberty of Conſcience is the maine, ſo as no man pretend a conſcience to diſturb the peace of the Kingdome, which every Student of the Law knows when the peace is broken. Thoſe men that by the Oars of their peſtilent Counſels ſhal be work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to row this ſhip back again into the ſea of a ſecond and more bloudy warre, are unworthy of their generation, unworthy to breath in Engliſh ayre, be they reckoned the great <hi>Catoes</hi> for coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, or any other incendiaries in the Kingdome, who thinke they cannot ſtand faſt and permanent, but by the ruine of others more faithfull then themſelves: there is no neceſſity for a man to be of this judgement or that, but there is an abſolute neceſſity of peace and preventing new troubles; 'tis abſolutely neceſſary to maintain the royall law of love; all Laws and Orders for uniformity muſt doe homage to the law of unity and brotherly love, we muſt not cut mens toes and fingers to make them all of a length: if uniformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty were ſo abſolutely neceſſary; then ought they to conforme to thoſe wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ch out of conſcience cannot come to them, rather then the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome ſhould be deſtroyed; for they may ſafely come to them, and what would not an honeſt man doe to ſave a Kingdom, that may be done with a good conſcience?</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> They ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> bound by the Law of God to deliver Gods people and this whole Ki<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gdome from all oppreſſions both in ſoules and bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies. A man may be damned for not doing his duty, as well as committing a great ſinn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>: <hi>Moſes</hi> ſayes, <hi>that they that forſake their brethren, ſhall never come into Canaan:</hi> ſo <hi>Mat.</hi> 25. <hi>In priſon and previſited me no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>;</hi> his Army ought by the equity of that Scripture to keepe all honeſt conſcientious men that offend no juſt Laws out of priſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s: you may read in that Chapter that Jeſus Chriſt is that great Travailer who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> this Aſcention tooke his journey into a far Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, and delivered his goods to his ſervants, as it is in the parable of the Talents, and in a time of Reformation every Chriſtian muſt help
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:114508:37"/> to facilitate the worke; for Chriſt appoints no Lord Treaſurers to impropriate his gifts but all ſteward<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>y out what God b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to every man for the good of the Kingdom of heaven; that I take to be the meaning of <hi>Mat.</hi> 6. To ſet the Crown upon the head of Chriſt; every man ought to ſerve God by ſerving his Countrey in his lawfull calling, the end whereof is not to multiply riches, but to doe good in his generation: men abuſe their callings,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Called</hi> Contra formam Colla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionis.</note> and an action will be brought another day againſt many rich men in this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom. Take another Scripture <hi>Thou ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lt love the Lord thy God with all thy ſoule, toto corde anima &amp; mente.</hi> with all thy heart coura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giouſly; for courage belongs to the heart; the ſoule of religion is to be valiant for Religion, and to fight againſt thoſe that would rob us of it; not to kill them, but to preſerve it with all thy ſoule affectio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately; for <hi>Anima</hi> is the ſource of all the affections; what a man loves he will defend: Religion is a miſtreſſe well worth fighting for her defence with all thy minde; the minde is the ſuperiour part of the ſoul, ſpiritually &amp; diſcreetly with zeal according to knowledge. The thing I intend is that Chriſt muſt be honoured with ſtrength and power, as well as with other naturall parts, and abilities, and riches, or any other gifts: ſome have written (which yet is ſo weake an errour that I wonder it ſhould deceive any man) that the ſword ought not to be employed for Religion, that though I may fight to defend my clothes or my cattell, I may not fight to defend my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion; like ſome Indians that will fight for a pin but not for gold. Poſſibly a mans pen and his heart may differ in opinion: I know there were ſome in <hi>Germany</hi> pretended that no man ought to fight in Gods cauſe, but to contend <hi>lachrimis &amp; precibus;</hi> (as King <hi>H.</hi> 8. was wont to ſay, merrily: If it be a good Religion it will defend it ſelfe, if a bad one, it is not worth defending let God alone with Religion) but theſe very men did afterwards fight for Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in pretence at leaſt, and ſaid their former opinion was good unleſſe God puts the Sword into their hands: It ſeems to me that the Revelation holds forth cleerely, that the Saints muſt have the honour to deſtroy <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> whoſe ſpirit reigns in all thoſe that will domineere imperiouſly over the conſciences of their brethren, for therefore is he called THE <hi>Antichriſt.</hi> It would be an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent worke for ſome judicious Miniſter to explain that in the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velations,</hi> how the holy, faithfull, and choſen, ſhall make a warre
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:114508:38"/> for the Lambe againſt the Beaſt, and prevaile, and whether any of the ten Kings ſhall hate the Whore; it might be very ſatisfactory.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> This worke of the Army is Gods own handy-worke, their not disbanding had its immediate riſe from heaven, the Lord would not have them loſe the glory of all their victories: the very truth is, that it is meerely and purely for the love of this Kingdome that they keepe the Sword a little longer, and not for any pecuniary re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects, or ſelf-ends: I am credibly informed, and I verily beleeve it, that notwithſtanding, any thing ſaid or done againſt them, they were fully reſolved and concluded to disband, and to commend their righteous cauſe to their heavenly Father, with the reſt of their brethren in this Kingdome: but as the hearts of Kings ſo the hearts of Armies are in Gods hands, as clay in the hands of the Potter, the new moulding of this Army was viſibly from heaven, and the Lord hath carried them all over this Kingdome as his belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved darlings, with much love in his breſt towards them, and he that ſuffered no man to doe them wrong, would not have them to wrong themſelves, becauſe he moulded them for veſſels of honour, and now being at reſt in God, and thinking to reſt from their labours, the bleſſed Spirit begins to witneſſe to their ſpirits, that all is not yet as it ſhould be, and their ſouls being troubled within them, how they might glorifie God, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e interceſſors to the Parliament for the liberties of this Kingdome, the Lord ſaid unto them, <hi>Seeke yee my face,</hi> and they anſwered, <hi>thy face Lord will we ſeeke,</hi> and ſequeſtred two daye at <hi>Saffron Walden</hi> to ſeeke the Lord by faſting and prayer, a thing unheard of in the Germane Wars; to ſee a Noble Generall and valiant Commanders that had encountred with Lyons and walls of braſſe, to lye groveling upon their knees, and pouring forth fervent prayers (the breath and voice of God in them) asking counſell from heaven, begging light and direction from the Father of lights, praying for wiſdome from above; what a rare example is it? how admirable is God in all his workings? And when they roſe up to eate, and their countenance was no more ſad, the Lord had, by the powerfull influence of his good Spirit, given in a ſweet return of Prayer for their continuation together; and thereupon the ſouldery deſiring a generall Rendevouze, the horſe and foot met with ſuch a generall re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oycing, and ſuch an unanimous reſolution to live and die together, for the juſt rights of King and people, that it
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:114508:38"/> is moſt admirable to conſider, ſuch a wonderfull conjunction of mindes, and ſuch noble Principles, that money, which is the Load<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone that draws the iron hearts of moſt Souldiers, is no more reckoned by them then dirt in compariſon of juſt liberties; who can ſay but that this is altogether of a divine off-ſpring; which to oppoſe, what is it but to deſpiſe the ſpirit of grace? I am confident that they which kick their heels againſt this Army, will in the end break their necks.</p>
            <p>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>xt, I ſhall onely ask the queſtion, whether out of thoſe quivers of arguments uſed by the Parliament, to juſtifie their raiſing forces, I might not draw many, even take them all out one after another to juſtifie the Armies not disbanding; all was done by the Parliament for the publike good. The Parliaments Motto is <hi>pro ſalute p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>puli,</hi> and the Armies, <hi>pro ſalute populi Dei, &amp; totius Angliae;</hi> no leſſe can be preſumed from the Army; for they who have adventured their lives for the good of the Kingdom, will never do any thing to endanger it. Certainly, hee that ſaved my life, I owe it to him; I will never diſtruſt him: they have the character of God upon them, and of his Conſecration; the Parliament hath lately voted them their Army, the whole Kingdom favours them, and all good Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians have cauſe to love and honour them, and yet there are ſome calumnious ſpirits that would rob Chriſtall of its brightneſſe, but the Sun of the Armies innocence will quickly melt the ice of all theſe Calumnies.</p>
            <p>It is not my deſigne to improve thoſe popular arguments formerly uſed, that for Papiſts to maintain the Proteſtant Religion was a pernicicus contradiction. What is it to hold, that to impriſon men for their Conſciences that break no Law, is for the Liberty of the Subject; as ſome Kindle-coals affirme; that honeſt Juſtices were weeded out of the Commiſſion; has there been no honeſt men, grand inſtruments of Liberty, diſplaced and diveſted of their truſt, to the grief of Gods people, for no other reaſon, but becauſe they were not <hi>Preſbyterians?</hi> That many as bad as <hi>Arminians</hi> are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred, and faithfull men diſgraced and diſplaced; and all this by the cunning artifice of malevolent ſpirits; nor what the Parliament ſaid that his Majeſty by his many Declarations and Proteſtations, for the maintenance of our Laws and Liberties, intended no more but that we ſhould have ſuch a Religion, and ſuch Laws as his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:114508:39"/> Biſhops and Judges would afford us, and ſhould conceive to be beſt for us; judge whether that be not a blinde implicite obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to truſt the Biſhops with our ſouls; what is the Law but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very mans birth-right and the rule of life, and therefore fhould be plain and eaſie, that every man may know<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>? For a guide to be blinde, how unreaſonable is it; if ſome men may have their deſires, ſhall we be in any better condition? I ſhall humbly crave leave, to vindicate the high Court of Parliament and the Army from ſome Objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons lately darted againſt them. The lightneſſe of ſome mens follies exceeds the weight of their malice, they are content to be fools rather then to acknowledge the worthy labours of that ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preame Court; they are ſuch ignorants, that they know not any good the Parliament hath done thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> many years, ſaying, that they have made our Religion worſe, and they do not intend to make our Laws the better. No, let all honeſt men ever bleſſe God for this Parliament; how gladly would this Kingdome have made themſelves ſlaves for ever, had not this Parliament ſtood mightily for their Liberties? I but (ſay ſome) the Parliament by impriſoning ſuch as have been faithfull Labourers in the Vineyard for diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence in opinions, are undoing all that they have done, and we fear things will be as bad as in the Biſhops times: judge not raſhly, there is no Ordinance yet to reſtrain Gods people from private meetings, nor for ſuppreſſing of ſeperate Congregations; Compare what is paſt with preſent times, and 'tis very much that things are no worſe for former kindneſſes, which Parliament and City have ſhewed to honeſt people: I truſt the bleſſings of Heaven ſhall be upon them forever; however, do not for the abortion of the twentieth childe, kill the nineteenth: believe it, this Parliament is the ſpring and conſervatory of all our Liberties and Properties, having removed old Grievances, and laid the foundation for innumerable benefits and advantages to the Kingdome. There are in both Houſes moſt excellent <hi>Moſes</hi>'s, <hi>Nehemiahs, Jeremiahs,</hi> and <hi>Pauls,</hi> that have ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventured for the people; ô, the infinite love of many of our finite <hi>Moſes's,</hi> and Worthies. What had become of <hi>Iſrael</hi> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> he had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken his charge upon every tumult and queremony of the people? What innumerable difficulties have our Worthies in Parli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ment ſurmounted? Able to have daunted and ſtinted the moſt noble re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions, though the command of God lay heavy upon them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:114508:39"/> deliver this Kingdome, and let the oppreſſed go free; as the Diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of <hi>America</hi> by <hi>Columbus</hi> a <hi>Genoa</hi> Merchant; though a ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall man, skilfull in Mathematicks, might have concluded that there was a Weſtern part of the World not diſcovered, yet the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprize was ſo tranſcendent, that few men would have had the courage to have attempted it, though ſure to ſucceed. And though there are ſufficient reaſons publikely known to the Kingdom to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire the Army not to disband by any means, till publike Liberties be ſetled and ſecured: yet there is not the leaſt ground for the people in the leaſt meaſure to withdraw their affections and due reſpects from the Parliament; ſome Taxes indeed ſtill, but for a ſhort war a long peace; 'tis not a years purchaſe now, I hope, for the abſolute inheritance. Now, hearken ye prudent Wiſe-men, and lovers of your Countrie; that which is every Engliſhmans intereſt and bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe in this juncture of time is, that the whole Kingdome as one man preſently declare againſt a ſecond war, which is a ſickneſſe eaſily prevented, but hardly cared; not to ſuffer any forces directly or indirectly to be raiſed againſt this Army, under any pretence what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever; and in the name of God, let thoſe whom the Army ſhall ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe, come to a fair triall and receive juſtice with mercy, becauſe we profeſſe Chriſtianity. Let all Treaſurers and Committee-men give a faire accompt, and ſo receive an <hi>Euge, Well done thou faithfull ſteward,</hi> or an <hi>Apage, Depart unfaithfull man:</hi> and let thoſe that have ſwallowed the Kingdoms treaſure vomit it up again.</p>
            <p>There are many that have got greateſtates in the late Wars up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ruines and ſpoyls of the people, but as wee ſay proverbially, <hi>They that have ſtolne the Kingdomes Gooſe, the feathers will ſtick in their ſtomacks.</hi> If a Town or City be on fire, and every man is intreated to help; now for any man to carry away his neighbours goods, and to enrich himſelf by a generall conflagration; what is this but to add affliction to the afflicted, and little better then Felo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny? Nor is it to the purpoſe to ſay, <hi>I got it honeſtly;</hi> the law of God and reaſon ſays that no man ought to get a great eſtate in a time of publike calamity, by any profeſſion or trade whatſoever; I ſay, under favour, no man ought to increaſe his eſtate in a time of a Civill War (unleſſe he be a ſouldier) if he get more then to mayntain himſelfe and family, the overplus muſt go to the State for the mayntenance of the War: to get 1000 <hi>lib. per annum,</hi> and to lend 500 <hi>lib.</hi> to the Parl.
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:114508:40"/> is but Sophiſticall. I know it was a high point of State policie, for the greater encouragement of covetous men, to allow them extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary gains for ſuch moneys as ſhould paſſe their hands, and that ſome men ſhould have offices and other places ſufficient for foure or five men: but I hope theſe men make account that they are the Kingdoms purſ-bearers, in the former caſe that I put, 'tis a neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourly part to preſerve his goods, whoſe houſe is on fire, but he ought in conſcience to reſtore them, that many poor country men that were inforced for the ſafety of their lives, being indebted, ſhould now be undone by uſe money; that old Uſurers ſhould thrive in a time of Warre, and honeſt men that have ventured their lives for the Kingdome, ſhould now be made ſlaves to a company of greedy Uſurers: what a horrible ſhame is it? A friend of mine having borrowed 100 <hi>lib.</hi> which he layd out in cattell, was conſtreined to forſake his houſe and goods for the ſafety of his perſon, his houſe plundered and his cattell driven away, yet being returned home, procures the 100 <hi>lib.</hi> and intreats the Creditor to remit the Intereſt, the Uſurer ſtormes at the motion, and puts the bond in ſuit for the Intereſt: meeting with him, I told him he ſhould doe very well to ſhew himſelfe a Chriſtian, and to take his principall; what tell you me of a Chriſtian ſaid he? I have nothing to live upon but my In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt; but ſaid I, your Debtor loſt the Principall, will not you abate the Intereſt, or rather then fail, half of it; not he. The Lord deliver this Kingdom from ſuch Jews, in whom there is no more mercie then milke in a male Tyger: for my part I thinke their goods are to be confiſcated, and they ought in reaſon to be baniſhed, as Jews, by the equity of the Statute;<note place="margin">De Iudaiſmo.</note> for the Jews did but lawfully rob the Kingdome in time of peace. I am not againſt all taking of uſury when the borrower gains by it. But can any man imagine that if the late <hi>Oxford</hi> party had prevailed, they would have ſuffered any of their friends to have been impriſoned for uſe money? The bloudy Rebels in <hi>Ireland</hi> had ſo much mercie and wit to ordaine that no intereſt ſhould be paid in time of warre, the Law of God is plain for it in <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> and our Hiſtorians tell us, that after Civill Wars there were alwayes commiſſions granted to enquire who had in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed their eſtates in a publike calamity, and out of their ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluities they were enforced to relieve the neceſſities of poore men: I am perſwaded that there are 100 men about the City of <hi>London,</hi>
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:114508:40"/> that have got enough ſince the Wars began, to provide comfortably for all the poor people in and about <hi>London.</hi> B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e Law of Armes ſome profeſſions are more ſpecially priviledged <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> a time of Warre then others, as Prieſts, Surgeons, Husbandmen, and thoſe that keepe Vineyards, and theſe ought not to be taken priſoners on either ſide, becauſe there is a neceſſary uſe for them, which party ſoever prevailed: Yet in the Civill Law I finde it adjudged that thoſe men muſt not make an immoderate gain of their profeſſions, becauſe eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man is bound to regard the publike welfare more then his owne private ends; &amp; therefore after the war ended, the Magiſtrates that govern by the Civill Law in <hi>Italy,</hi> and other places, call theſe men to account and order them to reſtore whatever they got during the war, maintenance for their Families being onely allowed them. What a gallant courſe might there be taken for the relief of poore people in this Kingdome, that there might not be a beggar amongſt us? But pardon this digreſſion, the thing I intend is, that there are thouſands and thouſands that will be undone by this cruell Uſury, if the wiſdome of Parliament do not prevent it: but let us not have ſo much as one hard thought of the Parliament, for that Court is the Liberty of the Subject wrapt up and conſerved. How happy are <hi>Engliſhmen</hi> that cannot be made miſerable but by ſuch whom they chooſe and elect to vote for them; If they be enſlaved, they may thank themſelves. What a precious priviledge is it for this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom that the Legiſlative power is in the Parliament, and what an excellent Conſtitution of Government is it, that the King ſhould take an Oath at his Coronation to keep the Laws, when the people make their own Laws, and the King ſwears to keep them? How free is that people, and yet (under co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rection be it ſpoken) there are two things conſiderable in the Conſtitution of the Honourable Houſe of Commons.</p>
            <p>That every Member is not as well ſworne to Vote nothing but <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> what he believes is for the Common good, and to enact good Laws, as the King to mayntain them: peradventure, an Oath in ſuch a Caſe might do no hurt. For, though Father that ſwears to educate his Childe in good nurture and literature, be no more obliged to do it then he was before; yet the obligation of an Oath whet's the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of that duty upon him to do it with more alacrity and
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:114508:41"/> reſolution for his Oaths ſake; I know there is a ſtrong reaſon to be given why it is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>dleſs; becauſe in true policy Intereſts are, and better State ſecurity then oaths. The Lords and Commons Vote for themſelves, for their own goods as well as the Kingdomes. If the Kingdome ſuffer they ſuffer in their private Eſtates, and therefore the higheſt point of policy that humane prudence can reach unto, is this, when a man cannot hurt mee, but hee muſt hurt himſelfe, when he cannot pluck out one of my eyes, but hee muſt pluck out both his own: for our Parliament Worthies are Elder Brothers, and have a double portion in this Kingdome. In ſuch a caſe I may ſafely truſt them; for which reaſon the King and Judges have been ever ſworn, but the Commons not.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> It is much objected that they cannot adminiſter an Oath, and why ſo? Becauſe they do it not? that's no good Conſequence; they that may lawfully put the Kingdome into a martiall poſture to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend their own Liberties may certainly adminiſter an Oath, if they pleaſe. But there are two Reaſons why it hath not been accuſtomed.</p>
            <p n="1">1 A violent preſumption in Law, that nothing can be done in the Kingdome but the Houſe muſt have notice of it, for ſo the Law ſays, that every private man muſt be preſumed to take notice of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very thing done in his own Hundred or County.</p>
            <p n="2">2 For the great reverence every man is preſumed to beare to that great Aſſembly, that no man dares affirme an untruth before that Honourable Preſence. I am ſure, that <hi>Legem dare, eſt ſummitas Imperii:</hi> They that have the greater power, muſt have them leſſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded. Nor do I l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ke thoſe expreſſions, that the Commons are the Kingdoms ſervants, and receive wages for their ſervice by Law. Magiſtrates doe not ſo much ſerve the people, as the good of the people, and ſo are ſuperiour: the Members Vote as well for their own Intereſts; they are the moſt conſiderable men of parts and qualities in the Kingdom; the reaſon of the Kingdom reſides in both Houſes of Parliament, to them I muſt ſubmit my Intereſt, though my judgement is not enthralled; the ultimate reſolution of all things not againſt the Laws of God and Nature (which only nter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pret themſelves) is in Parliament. This principall of ultimate reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:114508:41"/> which in ſetled times is joynt in the King, Lords, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, may (under favour) be divided in a Caſe of neceſſity with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any change or deſtruction of the Government, and without any prejudice to the mixture of the ſeverall eſtates, when that neceſſity is removed.</p>
            <p>Nor do I like ſeverall other expreſſions to the ſame purpoſe, as that of the Potter and the Veſſell, that the Counties are the Fathers begetting, and the Boroughs the Mothers that conceive and bring forth the Burgeſſes; and that if <hi>Abſalon</hi> riſe againſt <hi>David,</hi> it is high Treaſon. Theſe are truths, but little to the purpoſe for which they are produced; but many honeſt people are much troubled at the burning of a Petition which was lately preſented to the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Houſe; &amp; what greater miſchief can befall a people in time of Parliament, then that thoſe which have ventured their lives for the Petition of Right, ſhould be denyed the liberty to petition? truly I dare not preſently cenſure every thing for which I do not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend a ſufficient reaſon. Many grains muſt be allowed to reaſons of State, ſo long as Governours have a generall Care, and ayme to the publike good; and do not of Common-wealths men become private-Wealths men, nor turn the edge of that power againſt the people w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> they put into their hands; certainly, there is no Counſel in the world but may erre: let the chiefe Incendiaries, who undoubtedly miſ-informed the Houſe, anſwer it. Our Honorable Worthyes which like the heavenly bodies have been in continuall motion for the good of this Kingdome, ſo many yeares, deſerve all poſſible vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration; and he that runs all day, and trips, it, may be, once or twice, being wearied with multiplicity of buſineſſe, 'tis no imputation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt wiſe and judicious men. For as God does not judge a man by every action but the whole tenour of his life, ſo muſt the people judge of great Counſels: What hath the generall bent and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of the Parliament been ſince their firſt convention, but the ſafety and liberty of the people? Had this Kingdom been in a way to happineſſe but for this Parliament? 'tis true the Army hath been principall Inſtruments of our deliverance, but who rayſed this Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, and put the ſword into their hands? If <hi>Timotheus</hi> had not been, we had not had much ſweet Muſique; inſtead of ſinging <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſannaes</hi>
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:114508:42"/> to the moſt High, we might have hanged up our Harps, and ſung <hi>Lachrimae;</hi> but if <hi>Timotheus</hi> his Maſter had not been, we had not had <hi>Timotheus.</hi> The Parliaments chiefeſt care hath been the ſafety of the Kingdom, and if in the carrying on of that, ſome of their own private good hath been too much involved, and many of themſelves enriched in this time of Calamity, and ſome Votes not authentick in the Court of Heaven; It is not well done in right reaſon, it ought not ſo to be; but this does not diſſolve the Contract, nor ſo much as looſen the knot between the Parliament and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; it ſhould only put thoſe Worthyes upon a Rectification of what hath been irregular. The husband promiſes faith to his wife, one unkind word or action towards her, does not violate his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe for civill matters of property; many Errours and great Taxa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are to be cheerfully tolerated and endured, ſo long as it appears that the higheſt Court in any Kingdome hath a care to make good their promiſe to the people; the greateſt wiſdome is to chuſe the leaſt evils, which is ever to mayntain the Honours of Parliament, as being the glory of this Nation, the Fountain of all lawfull Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and the Defender of all Civill Enjoyments: if the Ship be in danger, throw out part of the goods to prevent a totall ruine; let the <hi>Jonahs</hi> be caſt out and the ſtorm will ceaſe; when <hi>Sheba</hi> the ſon of <hi>Bichri</hi> was diſprotected, <hi>Joab</hi> and the Army made an Honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Retreat. 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 20.</p>
            <p>I cannot but ſmile at ſome printed Pamphlets, that to ingratiate themſelves with ſome that are not the Kingdoms beſt friends, ſay that the Army hath ſome dangerous deſigne; juſt as bloudy <hi>Bonner</hi> ſayd, that the way to deſtroy the Kingdome, is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> have the Bible in Engliſh. Doth the Army demand any thing but what they firſt adventured for? and was there any radicall errour in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning? ſurely none; if they ſhould, unlawfull demands may be law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully denyed; ſo far as the Army hath the Juſtice of heaven on their ſides; ſo far they will prevail againſt all the world of oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers, and no further: what, will any rationall man be afraid of him that draws his ſword in his defence? Put the caſe that <hi>I. S.</hi> and his followers travelling through a dangerous Forreſt, meeting with <hi>I. D.</hi> and his ſervants, ſhould intreat <hi>I. D.</hi> to draw his ſword for
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:114508:42"/> all their defences, who does ſo, and meeting with ſuch as would rob them, <hi>I. D.</hi> and his friends, moſt manfully and valiantly make good every paſſage, by killing many, till they are paſt the moſt dangerous place; then ſayes <hi>I. S.</hi> now pray thee <hi>I. D.</hi> put up thy ſword; nay, ſays he, there may be more wolves yet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uickly ſtart out of the wood, let's ſtand upon our guard till we be paſt all dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger; and diſcourſing, they differ by the way in matters of opinion, and ſome of <hi>I. S.</hi> party tels him that he is not fit to live in a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth, let him change that opinion or he muſt be oppoſed: pray ſayes <hi>I. D.</hi> ſince our way lies together let us journey lovingly, let us live and bleſſe God that hath preſerved us all; ſayes one of <hi>I. D.</hi> friends, better our lives had not been preſerved, then to be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by ſuch dangerous fellows as you are. I intend this Treatiſe wholy for the Readers brain in point of explication, little to his affection in point of application: but let no man be ſo groſely er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roneous as to ſay, that the Army is <hi>Anti-magiſtraticall,</hi> and <hi>Anti-parliamentary:</hi> what ayme can a Houſe of Commons have but the common good? The Parliament being intent to the true ends and noble grounds of their raiſing Forces, and the Army wholy minding the reaſons of their ingaging, and both ſincerely, really, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly the Parliament, as the ſupreame Councell of the Kingdom, and their Army as the ſervants of Juſtice, endeavouring a ſpeedy accompliſhing of the moſt honourable and glorious ends, <hi>viz.</hi> the juſt rights of the King, juſt priviledges of the Parliament, and juſt liberties of the ſubjects common ſafety, juſt liberty, and equitable propriety, to which the Armies proceedings have a naturall tenden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie and proclivity, as the ſtone to fall downwards; 'tis impoſſible any differenc ſhould ariſe: Counſell is the right hand of Policy, and the ſword is the left, which may aſſiſt and promote without any face of oppoſition: the truth is, that there are ſome whoſe pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate intereſts are contrary to the publique intereſt of this Kingdom, they are the troublers of the pure waters, that the people ſhould not drinke, they trouble and diſquiet the fountain, and then the ſtreams muſt needs run muddy; they are men of the ſame ſpirits from whence the miſeries of this Kingdom did at the firſt flow, that is, obſtructers of the free courſe of Religion and Juſtice, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the obſtructers of poore <hi>Irelands</hi> reliefe: But who muſt be
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:114508:43"/> Judges of the matters in agitation? Truly the Parliament, in all matters judiciall, we muſt have no Judge of Scripture but it ſelfe; that point of Popery hath coſt us deare; we muſt not light a candle to ſee whether it be day; who knowes not that every man ought to have his own without vexatious attendance? and that it is injuſtice to make a man ſpend 10 <hi>lib.</hi> to recover 5 <hi>lib.</hi> who ſhall judge whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thoſe that have ſaved the Kingdom ought to have the liberty of ſubjects? who knows not but that Petitioning is a way of peace and ſubmiſſion, and that for Chriſtians to meet in private to ſerve God, is no breach of the peace? The Lord grant that this Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, by the help of the Army, may be the ſetlers and the reſtorers of this divided Kingdome, the neck-breakers of all oppreſſions in ſoules, bodies, and eſtates, the repairers and relievers of poor <hi>Ireland,</hi> which was formerly called the Iſland of Saints.</p>
            <p>Another <hi>Objection</hi> is, that the Armies not disbanding obſtructs the reliefe and indangers the loſſe of dying <hi>Ireland:</hi> Ah, poore <hi>Ireland,</hi> my ſoule is much troubled for thee; I knew thee, not long ſince, <hi>Englands</hi> younger ſiſter, but thou art now the land of <hi>Ire:</hi> but he that runs out to quench the fire in his neighbours houſe, when his own is almoſt burnt, I ſhall rather admire his zeale then commend his diſcretion. I confeſſe poore <hi>Ireland</hi> is on ſuch a flame, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but Gods infinite bleſſing upon the wiſdome and endeavour of this Parliament can be able to quench it; but Engliſh liberties, which have been bought at ſo deere a rate, muſt firſt be ſetled and ſecured. The Army declared their reſolutions, to have ingaged in that ſervice, in one entire body, which was not thought conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent; if then the Army were hindered by any plot or contrivement from going thither, not they, but the hinderers are culpable of <hi>Irelands</hi> continued miſeries; but as the Army hath ever been ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervant to all the juſt commands and orders of Parliament; ſo I hope that if hereafter they ſhall ingage in that ſervice, they will be well ſatisfied in point of conſcience, what it is that they fight for: It is poſſible that <hi>Antichriſt</hi> with his left hand, may fight againſt his right. To fight againſt Popery further then it is deſtructive of State policie, to introduce a uniformity in the Proteſtant Religion, is, in my opinion, little better; but if it be to bring thoſe bloud-thirſty
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:114508:43"/> Rebels to condigne puniſhment, and not to ſpare a man that hath had his hand in bloud, ſo far it is of God, and he will own it, but for thoſe expreſſions which ſome pulpits ring of, of rooting out that Nation, and daſhing the little childrens bones againſt the ſtones; I confeſſe it makes my heart to tremble to thinke of it, but thoſe that will not ſubmit to a generall Government muſt be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> But we feare the Army will over-awe the Parliament; and Counſels not free ſtand but for Cyphers, and that Juſtice it ſelf may not be forced, but timely haſtned.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sol.</hi> 1. The Parliament hath anſwered this Objection in his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Caſe. The King ſayes they refuſe to treat, unleſſe wee deliver the Sword into his hands, which is to yield the queſtion; when any differences ariſe, all things muſt reſt as they are, untill all be deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined and concluded.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Inforcements are juſt, when juſt things are inforced, the ſword is a ſervant of Juſtice, and is never better employed. That which the <hi>Hollanders</hi> alledge for themſelves is univerſally true: if a Magiſtrate will not do juſtice, the Laws mayn intention for juſtice muſt not be loſt; and King <hi>Philip</hi> not doing them juſtice, was the Authour of all the miſchiefs that hapned. Rebellion is, not to obey a law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Magiſtrate in a lawfull Act, not contrary to the Laws of God or Nature, beſides which all Laws are Arbitrary by the Supreame Court of every Kingdome; If the Army ſhall entreat any unjuſt things (as the Sun may be in an Eclipſe) Never were any juſt Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers deſtroyed by force; there was a riſing againſt <hi>David,</hi> and great ſtirs in <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixth's and Queen <hi>Eliſabeths</hi> time, but quickly huſht and ſubdued: I think no Hiſtory can be produced, that ever any good Magiſtrates were ſubdued by force, for God ſits upon the Bench with them; but many times Kings and Governours have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed to do juſtice, till the people have enforced them. Hitherto the Army hath had the juſtice of Heaven, and ſo long as they intreat in the Kingdoms behalf things Honourable and ſafe for the Parliament to grant, their Continuance is the beſt aſſurance that our Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyes
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:114508:44"/> in Parliament can deſire: For what great King or Court but receives honour by a faithfull and victorious Army; who will ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly facilitate the work, and prepare the way for our Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary Worthyes? as <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt did for our bleſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour. I hope I have ſatisfied every rationall man, that it is not poſſible in a prudentiall conſideration; that without the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tervention and interceſſion of this Army, this Parliament, as things ſtand, can never be able to ſettle the publike Liberties, and happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of this Kingdom; for who ſees not what a ſpirit of malignity there is ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll working in this Kingdom? Is all the malignant bloud drawn out or dryed up? Did never Serpents re-aſſume their poyſon upon occaſion? Are not the Jeſuites negotiating a reconc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lement be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Catholike Princes hoping to eat up <hi>Holland</hi> at a break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt, <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland</hi> for their dinner, and all other Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants at ſupper; and all to erect a univerſall monarchy, and what's their pretence? Mark it I beſeech you, to avoyd diſorder and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion, for it can never be well ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y they, till one man have the ſole power over ſouls, and another over bodies and eſtates, I am confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent that before <hi>Rome's</hi> fall, there will be a generall Warre between Proteſtants and Papiſts, without any other ground of the quarrell. Is it not the extremity of madneſſe, for Proteſtants to fall out to maintain Antichriſts cauſe who is our ſworne enemy? How lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vingly doe Proteſtants and Papiſts aſſociate in <hi>France, Poland, &amp;c?</hi> The French Miniſters preach that the French King, Queen, and all are damned, unleſſe they forſake their Idolatry; the Prieſts quite contrary, that not a <hi>Hugonet</hi> can be ſaved: in the name of God what ails us? cannot we like bees hive into one body poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique becauſe we differ in opinion, yet are of the ſame Religion? ſhall ſmall matters disjoyne them whom one God, one Lord, one Faith, one Spirit, and one common cauſe, bonds of ſuch great ſtrength and force have linked together?</p>
            <p>Oh yee learned <hi>Preſbyterians,</hi> ſuch of you as are like dead flies in the ointment of our good names, to make us unſavoury to our No<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>le Parliament (which yet I truſt yee ſhall never be able to doe) Will yee not take warning by the Biſhops? Did not they tell the King that the w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y to prev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nt errours was to ſuppreſſe the Puritans? The Rams of the flock are demoliſhed, will not you tremble? I tell you,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:114508:44"/> that the way to make us all of one minde in the things of God, is to grant liberty to all; in things not fundamentall: poſſibly there are ſome by whom the way of truth is ſcandalized; wee may thank the Biſhops and their Succeſſours for it, let the waters a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone and they paſſe away quietly, but ſtop the Current, and throw in ſtones, and the waters rage. An <hi>Engliſhman</hi> ſcorns to have his Religion cudgelled out of him, but deale with him in the ſpirit of Chriſt, ſhew him where his feet ſlide, you take his judgement, and affections priſoners. If the Biſhops had not preſt Subſcriptions and Conformity to the Statute of 13 <hi>Eliz.</hi> they might have been longer lived, for any thing I know. It grieves me that you ſhould take ſuch pains to deſtroy your ſelves, but come, there is no falling from grace: true repentance is half innocent: tell our <hi>Parliament</hi> Worthyes, that onely a liberty to tender conſciences can break the heart-ſtrings of popery; t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>at never any but Antichriſt denyed a freedome of conſcience to people of our quality and profeſſion, who deſire it no longer then we are Proteſtants, and live in all dutifull Conformity to the Civill Government; tell them that Jeſus Chriſt will never proſper thoſe that perſecute ſuch as are humble ſuitors in the behalf of his Kingdom; Doe yee think he will? tell them that the free exerciſe of the Goſpel for Doctrine &amp; Diſcipline is of ſo harmleſſe and peaceable a nature, and carriage ſo far from wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any Magiſtrate in Sovereignty and Power, that the <hi>Perſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ns</hi> and the <hi>Turks</hi> admit it. The <hi>Roman</hi> Emperours in policy gave leave to build Temples. Politike <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth ſayd, There was no other way to peace, but by a liberty for all Proteſtants; ſo <hi>Maximilian</hi> that ſucceeded him: &amp; <hi>H.</hi> 3. of <hi>France.</hi> Ah ſaith <hi>Philip</hi> the ſecond, when he was dying, <hi>If I were to live again, my firſt thing ſhould be to grant liberty to Proteſtants:</hi> Ah ſayes the Emperour, <hi>How gladly would I grant a liberty of conſcience if that would now ſerve the turn, and that would have ſerved at firſt.</hi> I beſeech you marke me, when the King of <hi>Sweden</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered <hi>Germany,</hi> he propounded nothing but what was moſt juſt, liberty for Proteſtants, baniſhment of Jeſuites, reſtitution to the <hi>Palatinate;</hi> his coſen <hi>Mechelburg,</hi> and ſome other oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Princes, with the Emperour would not grant, but being
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:114508:45"/> victorious, nothing would content him then, but to be declared King of the <hi>Romans,</hi> and ſo heire apparent of the Empire. Be wiſe in time. A moderate, meet liberty will not ſatisfie every man, and you may proceed in your own way; if hereafter you ſuffer in point of Tithes, you may thank your ſelves: you know whoſe pride and covetouſneſs hath brought their honour into the duſt. Your ridged Presbytery is no more <hi>Jure Divino</hi> then Epiſcopacy was; you may as well call Divinity damnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Doe not think that this Kingdom will ſuffer you to be Judges in your own Caſes. Your <hi>Ipſe Dixit</hi> will not do it, your Votes cannot make Hereticks nor Schiſmaticks; men are wiſer in the South then far North: the Sun cleers the judgement; to that Son of Righteouſneſs I commend you, deſiring to walke with you in love and peace.</p>
            <p>I ſhall conclude with a requeſt to the Army: you precious ſouls, as ye have been preſidents to others for honeſty and ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, ſo be a preſident to your ſelves what to continue; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue juſt, be content with what you can get, and take not the value of a pin from any man, but in caſe of neceſſity; 'tis fit that you who have ſaved the Kingdome ſhould not ſtarve; injuſtice is a very great ſin, the want of morality excludes from Heaven. His Majeſty was wont to ſay, that there were none in arms, but Independents, Anabaptiſts, and Browniſts, who would deſtroy all Laws and Religion; the eyes of all the World are upon you: you know beſt why you tooke up arms, was it not for Laws and Liberties; ſtand faſt in the Lord and in the power of his might; be true to your firſt principles, as ye are <hi>Engliſhmen,</hi> as ye are Souldiers, and as ye are Chriſtians; treaſon is the betray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the greateſt truſt, hee that is true to his end, cannot be a Traytor. The War firſt undertaken for the defence of Laws and Liberties, hath had a great influence upon Religion; and pray anſwer me this Queſtion, if the Parliament had told you at the firſt, that you ſhould not expect any Liberty of Conſcience in caſe of prevayling; but that you muſt ſerve God according to the precepts of men, whether you ſee reaſon for it or no, would you have engaged ſo cordially upon a promiſe of freedom for
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:114508:45"/> your temporall eſtates? What is all the World worth if a man enjoy not the freedom of his ſoul? peradventure you will ſay that the world cannot deprive you of the liberty of your Conſciences, for the Saints are as free in priſon to enjoy God as if they were abroad, as ſweet experience can teſtifie, and the more we glorifie him by ſuffering for him here, the more conformable are wee made to our Head, and ſhall be glorified with him; and Jeſus Chriſt is eminently all Ordinances in himſelf; moſt true; but in the dark the beſt eyes have need of Candles. We are not yet as we ſhall be, we live upon the beams here, and not the body; and it derogates much from the wiſdome and the love of Chriſt, to reckon that as a ſhadow which he hath appointed for a ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Ordinance; Religion teacheth nothing againſt nature: pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety doth not ruinate humanity, but makes one man worth twenty. I aſſure you, Gods people hope that you will deliver them from the Biſhops ſucceſſors, as well as themſelves, by what title ſoever they be called. I doubt not but you have both naturall and ſpirituall affection to this poore Kingdom; the poore Saints that are rich in faith, act faith in Chriſt for deliverance by you: they ſay they care not what becomes of them, ſo as the Crown may be ſet upon the head of Chriſt, and fealty and alleagance ſworne unto him, who is no enemy to any juſt governours; they are perſwaded that the Parliament of themſelves intend no leſſe, and that there are very many in both Houſes, moſt cordiall ſervants to Jeſus Chriſt, who are even ſick for the love of him, that dyed for the love of them: but here is the caſe, there is a potent faction within this Kingdom, men that have enriched themſelves in theſe times of danger and calamity, (a baſe thing ſo to build upon the ruines of our brethren) that count gain god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe; and theſe conſiſt of ſubtill, Atheiſticall, and depraved Polititians, on the one hand; and devout, ſuperſtitious, rigid Zealots on the other hand: who by ſpecious pretences, and plauſible inſinuation, worke upon the candor and devotion of many honeſt men; whoſe mindes are vertuouſly diſpoſed, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlave this Kingdom for their own ends, and this under a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of Gods honour, ſervice, worſhip, and uniformity; and
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:114508:46"/> this deſigne ſo politikely carried on, that the wiſeſt men may be miſtaken, for he that thinks no hurt himſelfe is ſeldome ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious of others. The chiefe Religion of theſe Polititians is to have no Religion in the power of it, but ſuch a forme eſtabliſhed as is moſt ſutable to his Grandor, and they thinke it a ſin to let any man live in this Kingdome, who will not eat up, as ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, all their Orders and Sanctions: our noble Worthies in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, would quickly be as wholſom, medicinable, reſtora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives to heale the wounds of this Kingdom, but that they like byting corroſives ſtudy to make them greater and more dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, ſetting up all ſails to ſail withall, and rowing with all manner of Oares, but being diſcovered, will, I hope, be ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horred by all honeſt men. Now to reſtrain the malice of theſe ambitious men, the Lord hath preſerved you to this houre, and me thinks I heare Ieſus Chriſt be-ſpeaking you in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner: <hi>Hearken yee noble Army of Martyrs, in affection and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, who carryed your lives in your hands for my ſake, and for morall juſtice, wherewith I am delighted, I take it as kindly from you, as if you had given me your lives, but keepe them, I am pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring manſions for you, but your worke is not yet done, you muſt ſtand up for the liberties of your brethren, you muſt ſtand up in the gap for me, who alone trod the wine-preſſe of my Fathers wrath for you? why have I impowred you, but to purchaſe liberty for my people? Did I preſerve you from active martyrdome, that you ſhould bring your ſelves to paſſive? Would not I have taken your lives as kindly from you at</hi> Naſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>bey<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Briſtol, &amp;c. <hi>as if after diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banding you ſhould be impriſoned, and put to death for Heretiques, or Schiſmatiques? Is not my kingly government as precious to you, and as well worthy fighting for as my Prieſtly office? But if you ſhould be diſbanded before Gods people have their liberties ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured I ſhould have covered my face, and onely thought that you did not ſo well underſtand the Doctrine of Chriſts government, and dom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nion in his Churches and amongst his Saints, as the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of ſatisfaction by faith in him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Is it not moſt apparent that the day of your disbanding is in probabi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ity, the Eye of the Kingdoms ruine? for does not this po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:114508:46"/> faction ſay, they will not ſuffer an Independent, that they cannot live but by the death of the Independent party?</p>
            <p>Hath God preſerved you hitherto in times of War to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſibly deſtroyed in times of peace? Was not your Commiſſion to fight for Laws and Liberties, whereof Conſcience is the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt; hath not the Kingdom ſufficiently diſhonoured Religion for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly in the Biſhops times, but muſt they now under a pretence of uniformity ſeek the life of her Children, and of Religion it ſelf; do they not ayme at the life of Religion which is the heart of God, and the lives of his children, which are the apple of his eye? The <hi>Me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>curialiſts</hi> at Court did but ſtrike at the letter of the law in ſome things, but theſe <hi>Phaetons</hi> would ſet all on fire, and ayme at the power of Religion, the very life of our Laws, whoſe humours are ſo corrupt, that the leaſt ſcratch turns into a <hi>Gan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>green.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For I am confident, that theſe cruell men cannot bring one argument for themſelves, but what I may improve for the Popes Supremacy, which was pretended to be for orders ſake, to avoid confuſion, but in reality hath been the occaſion of all Tyranny. But many words are not proper to an Army, you have won the heart of Gods people, in you is fulfilled that propheſie, <hi>Eſay</hi> 49. <hi>That Kings ſhall be your nurſing Fathers,</hi> Commanders, perſons of Eminency: for what the watchfull Conſtable, worthy Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer, reverend Judge, and all other Officers of Juſtice do in pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing Traitors in times of peace, the ſame in effect is done by Armies in time of War: every Souldier hath been a judge to do juſtice and execution upon the enemy.</p>
            <p>I have but this requeſt to make to you, that you hearken not to any Syren ſongs, but be ever true to your firſt principles; let the Honour of Parliament always be of moſt high account and precious eſteem with you; your jarring with that Supreame Court would be a pleaſant melody to many that will pretend faire to you, ſpeak you fair to borrow your hands to take out the Cheſtnut for them, that would have you crack the ſhell for them to eat the kernell.</p>
            <pb n="86" facs="tcp:114508:47"/>
            <p>It is reported of the Lioneſs or the Bear, that if a whelpe dye ſhe will roar in the Den exceedingly over the carkaſs, or elſe ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving got ſome gobbets of fleſh, hopes by continuall clamour to put life into it; ſome ſuch there are, that by daily exclamation againſt the Supream Court, think to vivifie their dead Cauſe, and to put life into a carkaſs; that will not acquit our renowned Worthyes from the higheſt Crimination; and yet will juſtifie your ſtation by the Law of the Land. I beſeech you, if the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament had no power to Commiſſionate you to redeem out Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties; what are you, that have acted by their authority? I hate diſſimulation; the happineſs of this Kingdom will reſt prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally in this, that all the godly, though of different opinions, favour and aſſiſt one another, and that all honeſt peaceable men joyn together as one man to break the neck of all oppreſſion and injuſtice. Let every man contend for the Honour and Priviled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of the King and Parliament, in the preſervation of the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties and Birth-rights of the people. And when the Kingdome is happily ſetled, let us ſay, that God hath done all, yet honour them whom he hath honour'd.</p>
            <trailer>The End.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
